<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Habits on Jalyn Cai</title>
    <link>https://jalyncai.com/tags/habits/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Habits on Jalyn Cai</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 20:14:58 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jalyncai.com/tags/habits/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Morning routines - from chaos to calm</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/morning-routines/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 20:14:58 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/morning-routines/</guid>
      <description>I used to be that person. You know, the one who would wake up at 8:47 if I had to be out of the house by 9, patting myself on the back for not wasting any time.
The routine was planned down to the second:
Get out of bed (3 minutes to roll around and contemplate why I have to wake up, groan, and check my phone notifications) Go to the bathroom (7 minutes — no time for sun screen!</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I used to be <em>that</em> person. You know, the one who would wake up at 8:47 if I had to be out of the house by 9, patting myself on the back for not wasting any time.</p>
<p>The routine was planned down to the second:</p>
<ul>
<li>Get out of bed (3 minutes to roll around and contemplate why I have to wake up, groan, and check my phone notifications)</li>
<li>Go to the bathroom (7 minutes — no time for sun screen!)</li>
<li>Put on my clothes and socks and shoes, and grab my bag (1.5 minutes, hope fervently that I haven’t forgotten any items)</li>
<li>Run down to the bus line (1.5 minutes, and then I pretend I’m not gasping for air once I’m on the bus)</li>
</ul>
<p>Sometimes, if I did these things fast enough, I’d even have time to check my Instagram feed before the bus arrives. Score!</p>
<p>All in the name of optimization, right?</p>
<h2 id="why-a-morning-routine">Why a morning routine?</h2>
<p>Here’s the question I struggled with, as I learned more about other people’s morning routines: Why bother with doing other things in an actual routine, when I could be ready in 13 minutes from bed to bus?</p>
<p>The answer, I find out after begrudgingly experimenting, is that not everything is about efficiency.</p>
<p>A chaotic morning sets the tone for an equally chaotic day. Rushing through those 13 minutes left me constantly playing catch-up, both physically and mentally. I wasn’t starting the day on my own terms; I was simply reacting to the world around me.</p>
<p>Even on weekends when I had nowhere to be at 9, the chaos followed me in different ways, like picking up my phone and staying glued to it, (doom-)scrolling until half the day had slipped by.</p>
<p>By noon, I’d have nothing to show for it, but a drained battery — my phone’s, and my own energy — and that familiar foreboding sense of “I should’ve done something”.</p>
<p>For me, the morning routine is about setting the day right, and how I show up for myself every day by completing what I have set out as a <a href="/non-negotiables"  >non-negotiables</a>.</p>
<p>More than that, it’s a guard rail against procrastination, knowing that I have a series of objectives I want to hit and <a href="/streaks"  >continue my streaks on</a>.</p>
<h2 id="the-components-of-a-routine">The components of a routine</h2>
<p>It shouldn’t come as a shock that an intentional morning routine plays a crucial role in setting the day right.</p>
<p>Some parts are unavoidable, like the fact that you’d have to go to the bathroom, or getting dressed (and helping the kids too, if you’re a parent!).</p>
<p>But there are experiments that you can tailor and build for your own needs:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Hydration:</strong> Getting some water in you, whether that means plain, or mixed with minerals and electrolytes</li>
<li><strong>Movement:</strong> Any kind works — walking, stretching, yoga, gym, pilates, running… as long as you’re not jumping back under your blankets</li>
<li><strong>Mindfulness:</strong> Small practices that yield big mental dividends with journaling, gratitude listing, morning pages, meditating, or praying</li>
<li><strong>Light exposure:</strong> Getting the sunlight into your eyes, as popularized by Dr. Andrew Huberman, proven to trigger hormones that increase your energy and mood</li>
<li><strong>Reading:</strong> Try a few pages, or see how much you can read in 10 minutes</li>
<li><strong>Breakfast:</strong> Bonus points if you’ve prepped for this so you can just pop it into a microwave oven</li>
<li><strong>Skincare:</strong> A little goes a long way with some moisturizer and sunscreen</li>
<li><strong>Cold shower:</strong> A bracing way to energize and shock yourself into action</li>
<li><strong>Hobby-time:</strong> If you’ve always felt like you have no time to spend on something you find meaningful and fun, build that into your mornings while your mind is still fresh</li>
<li><strong>Caffeine:</strong> Coffee, tea, pre-workout — whatever you need to keep the sluggishness away</li>
<li><strong>Planning:</strong> Look ahead at your day, and get clarity and prioritize what needs to be done</li>
</ul>
<p>Remember, the key isn’t to do <em>everything</em>, but to see which ones could positively impact your day.</p>
<p>Falling into the trap of trying to do too much, too soon, is too easy. Evaluate what you can make stick. Like other habits, consistency is going to help make this an automated part of your life.</p>
<h2 id="my-routine-in-experimentation">My routine, in experimentation</h2>
<h3 id="the-waking-moment">The waking moment</h3>
<p>I wake up at 6:30am, walk about ten steps away to my desk, and switch the phone alarm off. In a new note in Obsidian, I quickly jot down my dreams, or what I can remember of them, and in the subject of the note, <a href="/waking"  >I pen down what I’m grateful for in the moment</a>.</p>
<h3 id="skincare">Skincare</h3>
<p>Then, I head into the bathroom. After, I wash my face and slap some sunscreen on.</p>
<h3 id="hydration">Hydration</h3>
<p>I step on my smart body scale to document my weight and body fat percentage. After that, I drink about 500ml of water.</p>
<h3 id="movement">Movement</h3>
<p>It diverges into 2 paths here:</p>
<ul>
<li>Gym day: I grind some coffee beans, mix the espresso with protein powder for a pre-workout drink, and spend the next hour and a half at the gym</li>
<li>Walking: This is a new one that I’ve implemented just over a month ago! I put on my walking shoes and walk for 45 minutes, while the morning air and ground are cool. Previously, I’d jump straight to showering and starting on the day’s work.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="cold-shower--meditation">Cold shower &amp; meditation</h3>
<p>When I come back from either, I take a cold shower, then do a quick 15-minute meditation at my desk.</p>
<h3 id="hobby">Hobby</h3>
<p>Recently, I’ve added a 15-minute Duolingo session. I know it’s not the most efficient way of studying a new language, but it’s fun and it helps my brain to shift into a different mode.</p>
<h3 id="planning">Planning</h3>
<p>Finally, once that is done, I look at my calendar and personal kanban board, to remind me of what’s possible for the day.</p>
<h2 id="the-evolution-of-the-morning-routine">The evolution of the morning routine</h2>
<p>Shaping the routine is going to be an ongoing process.</p>
<p>There will be periods when your life demands a more streamlined approach, and you’ll have to stick with the essentials.</p>
<p>Other times, you might find yourself with more space and time to add on components to your build.</p>
<p>The key, as with other things in your life, is being flexible and experimenting with what works for <em>you</em> and your intentions.</p>
<h2 id="your-turn-starting-small">Your turn: Starting small</h2>
<ol>
<li><strong>Identify your drivers:</strong> Figure out what you want to get out of a structured routine. Is it more energy, a sense of accomplishment, or a calmer start?</li>
<li><strong>Start with one thing, and be consistent:</strong> It’s better to do one thing well than five things haphazardly.</li>
<li><strong>Experiment and adjust:</strong> Evaluate after a week. Keep a log (mental, or otherwise) of how you feel about each component. If it’s working, great! Let’s add another. If it doesn’t, replace it based on your drivers in step one.</li>
<li><strong>Be kind to yourself:</strong> You’ll have setbacks when you feel like doing anything but the routine. Progress, not perfection, is the goal.</li>
</ol>
<p>What’s one change you’d like to make to your morning routine? I’d love to discuss what’s working and what isn’t, and your victories and challenges!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Streaks, and not letting go of a good one</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/streaks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2024 21:23:15 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/streaks/</guid>
      <description>There’s just something about streaks.
The dopamine hitting as I see the numbers go higher, the satisfaction of knowing I kept a small promise to myself.
Then there are the actual benefits of these streaks, which are the habits that are now ingrained in my life, like the mental clarity with mediation, the documentation of my days and life while journaling, the cultivating of a more resilient and happier mindset with a gratitude practice, and then some.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There’s just something about streaks.</p>
<p>The dopamine hitting as I see the numbers go higher, the satisfaction of knowing I kept a small promise to myself.</p>
<p>Then there are the <em>actual</em> benefits of these streaks, which are the habits that are now ingrained in my life, <a href="/non-negotiables"  >like the mental clarity with mediation, the documentation of my days and life while journaling, the cultivating of a more resilient and happier mindset with a gratitude practice, and then some</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p>I started keeping streaks after reading the popular books about habits — Atomic Habits, Tiny Habits, The Power of Habit and so on.</p>
<p>The premise is simple: you start, and then you do it again the next day.</p>
<p>Then the next.</p>
<p>And the next.</p>
<p>Before you know it, you’re well into habit formation territory, and it’ll be a part of your day and life from here on out.</p>
<p>The extra benefit of seeing a big number is not wanting your perceived momentum to stop.</p>
<p>I experimented with different methods:</p>
<ul>
<li>Analog, with a habit tracker drawn out on a page and crossing boxes out</li>
<li>A tracking app that consolidates the streaks during that season of life</li>
<li>Individual apps with their own tracking widgets (and, as I am learning after using Duolingo for nearly two weeks, threats of meltdowns)</li>
</ul>
<p>But there is a dark side to this.</p>
<hr>
<p><em>&ldquo;I don&rsquo;t really have a lot to write today, but I&rsquo;m still opening this app and typing something so that I don&rsquo;t lose my streak.&rdquo;</em></p>
<p>Entries like this in my journaling app happen once every few months, when I’m dead tired and it’s 11pm, way past my bedtime, and I have the widget telling me there’s a circle that needs filling in.</p>
<p>Or the days when I would startle out of bed when I remember I haven’t done something, and the slight relief when I sneak in under the wire.</p>
<p>There is a subtle shift, I think, from the purpose of building the habit, to keeping the streak alive.</p>
<p>Such as:</p>
<p>Am I being intentional and mindful of the time spent with my thoughts, or am I going through the motions to settle into a session, simply to maintain my meditation streak?</p>
<p>Do I practice actual gratitude when I’m writing it first thing in the morning, or am I being grateful for grateful’s sake for the continued motion?</p>
<p>Then there is that toxic view of how I feel like I’m erasing all my past <em>xxx</em> days worth of effort, by not continuing for a day.</p>
<hr>
<p>Still, though, I think the good outweighs the bad.</p>
<p>There’s something grounding about having the structure in place. Sure, some days they feel like an obligation, but they’re also a guard rail to me veering off-course when things get overwhelming and messy (and they do!).</p>
<p>And maybe it’s less about being perfect, and more about being a human and being persistent. These streaks are the tangible things I can hold and say hey, I’m trying. I’m showing up for myself. It is less about the habit, and more about who I am and I’m becoming.</p>
<p>So I’ll keep going. Because in the daily repetition, I see the quiet promise of growth, and the reminder that showing up still counts, even if it’s imperfect.</p>
<p>Just like I’ll show up to write these every week, or thereabouts. Not for the streak, but for the story that I’m still learning to tell.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non-negotiable habits</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/non-negotiables/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2024 11:53:40 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/non-negotiables/</guid>
      <description>There are things in life that people do automatically, like motor reflexes with blinking and swallowing, or actions like locking the door and — unfortunately — checking the phone for notifications.
Similar to values that you do not compromise on, your actions stack towards habits that form the cornerstones of your life. These actions set the tone for how you feel and provides the momentum for other positive habits you’re trying to build.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There are things in life that people <em>do</em> automatically, like motor reflexes with blinking and swallowing, or actions like locking the door and — unfortunately — checking the phone for notifications.</p>
<p>Similar to <a href="https://www.rd.com/article/non-negotiables/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >values that you do not compromise on</a>, your actions stack towards habits that form the cornerstones of your life. These actions set the tone for how you feel and provides the momentum for other positive habits you’re trying to build.</p>
<hr>
<p>With a few years of experiments on my belt, here are my non-negotiable habits as of August 2024.</p>
<h3 id="one-liner-gratitude-when-i-wake-up">One-liner gratitude when I wake up</h3>
<p>When the alarm on the phone goes off, I make the ten-step hike from my bed to the table and switch it off.</p>
<p>I start a new entry in my daily log on Notion; take a pause through the haziness of sleep, and write one thing that I am grateful for, in the title of the entry.</p>
<p>Logging it on Notion serves as a time stamp for my wake-up times, which is always useful for trend-spotting each month.</p>
<p>I try to log down my dream(s) in the body of the note. <a href="/waking"  >They disappear like wisps, sometimes.</a></p>
<h3 id="tracking-my-time-nutrition-and-expenses">Tracking: My time, nutrition, and expenses</h3>
<p>Even though we now know that the quote <a href="https://nesslabs.com/what-gets-measured-gets-managed"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >“what gets measured gets managed”</a> is a misnomer at best, and an opposite interpretation at worst, it is still helpful for me.</p>
<p>First, it gives me the outputs for my behaviour.</p>
<p>Want to know how many minutes I’ve invested in traveling this year? I see it in <a href="https://toggl.com/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >Toggl</a>, and because I’ve been tracking since 2018, I can work out how many experience dividends I’m getting from year to year.</p>
<p>Want to know how much money I’m spending on groceries up until today for the month? <a href="https://www.spendee.com/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >Spendee</a> tells me the amount, because I’ve made it a habit to log every purchase the moment I make them.</p>
<p>And for nutrition? It’s the same logic, and helpful as I keep track of the amount of protein I ingest every day.</p>
<p>Secondly, and more importantly, the act of doing the thing makes me want to be more conscientious and deliberate. This has been a huge mind shift in the way I approach these building blocks of life.</p>
<p>(Though there is something to be said about the scarcity mindset I have observed in me sometimes. Something to experiment more on!)</p>
<h3 id="work-outs-at-least-three-times-a-week">Work outs, at least three times a week</h3>
<p>My workout routine has me completing four workouts a week, so three times is keeping it safe on weeks where I feel like <a href="/spondy"  >my back can’t handle more than</a>, or if I fall sick/injured.</p>
<p>On typical weeks when I’m not traveling, I pick myself up first thing in the morning to do them. It sets my energy levels higher through the day when I do, but there are slight differences in power and endurance when I do them later on in the day.</p>
<p>As an addition, at a minimum I’m aiming for <em>activity</em> every day. It’s a morning walk these days, on days I don’t go to the gym.</p>
<h3 id="meditating-at-least-10-minutes-a-day">Meditating, at least 10 minutes a day</h3>
<p>I don’t have a set time for when I do this; even with a 1,695 day streak, I’m still playing around with what works best.</p>
<p>But the important thing is that I <em>do</em> it, whether it is right before I settle into working, during a break in the middle of the day, or when I am walking.</p>
<h3 id="reading-at-least-ten-minutes-a-day">Reading, at least ten minutes a day</h3>
<p>My Kindle (a pretty laggy 7th-gen Paperwhite) is never far from me — on my desk, on the table, in my bag — and if I have free moments in between calls at work, I’m trying to reach the end of a chapter in a non-fiction book.</p>
<p>Additionally, I block half an hour before bedtime to do light fiction reading, though the time expands and contracts depending on when the work day ends; something to work on more diligently.</p>
<h3 id="journaling-before-i-sleep">Journaling before I sleep</h3>
<p>Through my life I have trialed and tested many different mediums (digital vs. a proper journal), timings (mornings vs. nights), and methods (free writing, lists, bullet, unsent letters…).</p>
<p>For now, I journal on <a href="https://dayoneapp.com/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >Day One</a> through my phone (it’s telling me I have a 1,413 day streak today!), where I have two journals: one for free-form writing about what happened during the day, and another to answer the daily prompt.</p>
<p>The free-form writing journal gives me the chance to unload what is on my mind that has been playing incessantly throughout the day.</p>
<p>I find that reflecting on my actions, and dumping the contents of my brain to work through potential solutions, ways I should be reacting, and paths forward has been helpful in clarity.</p>
<p>For the daily prompts, that’s just a fun way to surface topics I wouldn’t think of, and reach to the edges of diving into them.</p>
<hr>
<p>I’m probably forgetting non-negotiables that are second nature to me (i.e. drinking 2 litres of water, using dental floss, applying sunblock), but that is not a bad thing.</p>
<p>More that I am thinking about: Is there an optimal number or a maximum of habits before the system falls apart? What about rigidity vs. fluidity of the way I act upon them? Psychological barriers or breakthroughs?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meditating (and how I kind of suck at it, but that&#39;s the whole point)</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/meditating/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2022 14:43:15 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/meditating/</guid>
      <description>My mind is not a quiet place.
It’s full of thoughts; rooted in anxiety, in worry, over things I can’t control and things I can. More often than not, random lyrics and quotes are also bouncing in the ol’ noggin, in specific cadences and lilts as they were spoken in the medium I watched them in.
Late in 2019, I decided to give meditating a spin. I’ve heard the benefits of meditation many, many years ago, but have always dismissed it as a woo-woo new-age alt-medicine (is that enough hyphens yet?</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My mind is not a quiet place.</p>
<p>It’s full of thoughts; rooted in anxiety, in worry, over things I can’t control and things I can. More often than not, random lyrics and quotes are also bouncing in the ol’ noggin, in specific cadences and lilts as they were spoken in the medium I watched them in.</p>
<p>Late in 2019, I decided to give meditating a spin. I’ve heard the benefits of meditation many, many years ago, but have always dismissed it as a woo-woo new-age alt-medicine (is that enough hyphens yet?) practice. Yet, it has been shown that there are actual benefits to doing it: improving focus, decreasing anxiety, reducing stress, amongst others.</p>
<p>So, I did what I knew best: I read books<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, and used All The Apps<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>. I fumbled and wondered what I was doing wrong, and tried different things to see if this time, it’ll be the one that sticks.</p>
<h2 id="how-it-started">How it started</h2>
<p>I began with guided meditations.</p>
<p>Sometimes I fell back asleep if I did it as part of my waking up routine, which is bad because I would have turned my alarm off by that point. I’ve been lucky that I haven’t overslept by too much!</p>
<p>Meditating at night, too, helps me fall right asleep (except for recordings that have long pauses in between voices, in which case I would be on the precipice of sleep before getting jerked awake because of the unexpected voice in the dark). Now, if my aim was meditating for deep sleep, then this is a good outcome.</p>
<p>My priority was to build my focus and attention through mindfulness though, so the next thing I tried was using just the timer. I breathe in for four seconds, hold for four, and breathe out in – you guessed it – four seconds.</p>
<h2 id="how-its-going-badly-right">How it’s going (badly, right?)</h2>
<p>Meditation seems simple, but it’s not easy.</p>
<p>Here’s the thing that I’ve learned: Like sets of exercise for your body for your body, each ‘loss of focus  awareness  focus’ rep is your brain working out. That goes for every time you catch yourself drifting away, and bring yourself back to the present.</p>
<p>Now, I’m by no means an expert obviously, since I’m still fumbling. Even with 376 consecutive days under my belt, every morning still feels like a really tough 10 – 15 minutes. I find myself trying to remember more of my dreams that are slowly fading away, the things I need to put on my things-to-do list, or the next steps I need to take once the session is over.</p>
<p>I’m not gonna lie, I’ve been frustrated because I find myself getting distracted with tangential thoughts and having to pull myself back into focus. Sometimes the latter doesn’t happen, and I catch myself in the middle of a daydream as the ending bell sounds its gong.</p>
<h2 id="how-to-meditate-if-you-want-to">How to meditate, if you want to</h2>
<ol>
<li>Decide if you want to try it guided or unguided – I really like Insight Timer for both, especially for the latter, but Headspace is pretty cool for guided practice, with different lengths that you can choose from</li>
<li>Choose when you want to meditate, and make that a habit. I do it in the morning when I wake up, but that means I have to fit that in my morning schedule. If that doesn’t work for you, at night works as well</li>
<li>Close your eyes, and while they are close, lower your gaze (I learned this in Jay Shetty’s book, Think Like A Monk)</li>
<li>Start with short sessions, and build incrementally</li>
<li>You’re not doing it <em>wrong</em>, because there isn’t a right or wrong way</li>
</ol>
<p>Here’s to building your brain muscle!</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Mindfulness in Plain English, 10% Happier by Dan Harris, Conscious by Annaka Harris, Mindfulness: A Practical Guide to Awakening by Joseph Goldstein, Think Like A Monk by Jay Shetty&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Insight Timer, Calm, Headspace, and most recently, the Fitbit app&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why and how I track every minute of my life</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/tracking-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Aug 2021 16:11:11 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/tracking-time/</guid>
      <description>It’s 2015, and my workplace was exploring different tools for resource management.
It started when the team lead wanted a way to “sell” our services as an in-house team (and I’ll be honest, I’m not sure that quantifying time spent was the way to do it but that’s a story for another day), so we went through a few, finding the pros and cons of each before settling on Harvest.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It’s 2015, and my workplace was exploring different tools for resource management.</p>
<p>It started when the team lead wanted a way to “sell” our services as an in-house team (and I’ll be honest, I’m not sure that quantifying time spent was the way to do it but that’s a story for another day), so we went through a few, finding the pros and cons of each before settling on Harvest.</p>
<p>I think it’s because it was the cheapest per seat, maybe?</p>
<p>But that whole exercise of finding a tool and figuring out what worked and what didn’t also led me to think about my <em>own</em> hours, outside of work.</p>
<p>I hadn’t come across <a href="https://lauravanderkam.com/2017/09/welcome-168-hours-time-tracking-challenge/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >Laura Vanderkam</a>‘s content at that point, so it was trial and error on my part to figuring out what I was tracking.</p>
<p>I remember polling my friends and colleagues about my information architecture — or really just categories or buckets of time, occupational hazard aside — and trying to see if I was being too pedantic about some things, and too general for others.</p>
<p>So… I guess the question begs: Why do I track my time?</p>
<p>It started out as a way for me to find out where I was spending (wasting) my time — back in 2015, the time I took to commute was definitely an issue on my mind, and I feel like being able to clock that time made me aware of 1) how much it was, and 2) where it ranked amongst my other ‘smaller’ activities, like going to the gym.</p>
<p>More than that, I figured that if I knew what I was doing, and for how long, I could in theory optimize my time and productivity. I also remember thinking a lot about what that tipping point would be, for me to use money to buy time, instead of spending my time to get money instead.</p>
<h3 id="things-i-should-know-with-common-sense-but-instead-knew-for-sure">Things I should know with common sense, but instead knew for sure:</h3>
<ul>
<li>I spend way too much time beyond my 40 hours a week for work</li>
<li>(That isn’t counting the work-adjacent activity, which includes things like training, development courses/classes that are specifically applied at work, and as of 2021, mentoring sessions)</li>
<li>Meal prep is a really effective time saver, even though the upfront cost of it seems high (I spend about 45 minutes every Sunday doing it, compared to ~25 minutes a day)</li>
<li>Being lazy in bed is an actual bad habit of mine</li>
<li>Sometimes I chunk a lot of activity under “Internet”, even though I have specific buckets for media consumption, reading, fandom stuff etc. Pretty sure that’s indicative of a bigger problem, which is that I (falsely) think I can multitask</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>That said, Toggl — the app I’ve been using since 2015 — <a href="https://twitter.com/toggltrack/status/1431554352506884096"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >had a functional error</a> over the weekend, and it’s thrown me off the loop as I keep trying to open the app on my phone. Hopefully that gets resolved soon.</p>
<p>Let me know if you try out tracking your time, even if just for a week, and if you see any surprises in there!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The seven sins (and why my top-ranked is gluttony)</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/gluttony/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Aug 2021 16:12:18 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/gluttony/</guid>
      <description>Out of the seven sins, I feel like my top three rotate between gluttony, sloth and pride.
Some days, I am one with sloth; I am the sloth; sloth becomes me, etc.
Gluttony, on the other hand, strikes me in cycles.
(Note: Possible trigger for disordered eating here!)
I try to put guardrails on my life, with habits like meal prepping, or working out and hitting a specific step count every day.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Out of the seven sins, I feel like my top three rotate between gluttony, sloth and pride.</p>
<p>Some days, I am one with sloth; I am the sloth; sloth becomes me, etc.</p>
<p>Gluttony, on the other hand, strikes me in cycles.</p>
<p>(Note: Possible trigger for disordered eating here!)</p>
<p>I try to put guardrails on my life, with habits like meal prepping, or working out and hitting a specific step count every day.</p>
<p>This year… has been kind of rough, on all these aspects. I’m not sure what has changed, and if it’s just an accelerated version of burnout in the time of this pandemic, but it is somehow significantly worse than this time last year.</p>
<p>Instead of meal prepping, I either:</p>
<ul>
<li>Skip a meal because there’s nothing I really want to eat, or;</li>
<li>Go on my phone and start (to the tune of Waving Through a Window) tap-tap-tapping for food to magically show up at my door steps, anytime from 30 to 50 minutes later</li>
</ul>
<p>In Thomas Aquinas’ <a href="https://www.newadvent.org/summa/3148.htm#article4"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >Summa Theologica</a>, he outlined the five ways that gluttony is committed. These include food that is:</p>
<ul>
<li>too expensive (I have two extremes with my cravings: 40 cents instant noodles, or a $250 buffet)</li>
<li>too elaborately prepared (Maybe not so much on this one? Score?)</li>
<li>too much in quantity ()</li>
<li>eaten too quickly (I guess? It depends. If I’m eating by myself, I tend to do it quite fast so that I can do other things)</li>
<li>eaten too early (my teammates might dispute this, because I eat lunch at 3pm, reallll healthily like, so… reverse-gluttony?)</li>
</ul>
<p>Oooh, boy. Lots to unpack here. I also know that the only way is through, so I just have to identify my obstacles in meal prepping again to do it more consistently now.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
