<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Mindset on Jalyn Cai</title>
    <link>https://jalyncai.com/tags/mindset/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Mindset on Jalyn Cai</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2024 20:49:34 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jalyncai.com/tags/mindset/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Challenges create change</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/change/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2024 20:49:34 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/change/</guid>
      <description>For years, I found comfort in the structure of a job — good performance and network building made for predictability, a sense of security, and an upward trajectory of what I thought I should be focusing on.
But here’s the thing — well, two things: firstly, that security just isn’t true anymore, in the landscape of layoffs; secondly and importantly, comfort doesn’t lead to real growth.
Sure, there is growth in the form of small income increments, or focusing on a niche (in my case, of user experience and design, and managing within the constraints of a team and client expectations).</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For years, I found comfort in the structure of a job — good performance and network building made for predictability, a sense of security, and an upward trajectory of what I thought I should be focusing on.</p>
<p>But here’s the thing — well, two things: firstly, that security just isn’t true anymore, in the landscape of layoffs; secondly and importantly, comfort doesn’t lead to <em>real</em> growth.</p>
<p>Sure, there is growth in the form of small income increments, or focusing on a niche (in my case, of user experience and design, and managing within the constraints of a team and client expectations).</p>
<p>But there is much more I want to learn and do, outside my expertise. Despite trying avenues within a corporate setting (like getting into the next-generation leadership team, and leading every extra-curricular interest group I was interested in), it wasn’t the exponential growth curve I was craving for.</p>
<p>There are questions, too, that I’ve been asking myself, about measuring the impact I’m making, and aligning my values with the work I’m doing.</p>
<p>So, here I am! I want to navigate uncharted territories, in the form of writing and sharing the synthesis of my learnings, in topics that are much more important to the foundation of how we live life, rather than the products and services we use.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s going to start as an <a href="https://www.instagram.com/jalyn.cai"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >Instagram</a> (apparently that&rsquo;s where the cool kids hang out to network, along with Twitter, but I don&rsquo;t think I want to go back to that platform), and then a <a href="https://newsletter.jalyncai.com"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >newsletter</a>.</p>
<p>I already know this is going to be a journey, and there will be mis-steps along the way. But I’m excited for the growth, and every step I take towards that.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Motion, not action</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/motion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2024 21:44:01 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/motion/</guid>
      <description>It’s easy to get caught up with doing things.
The dopamine hits make us feel accomplished, as if we have achieved our goal.
But what is our goal? Are we getting distracted from our true purpose?
There is a danger of mistaking action for motion.
Consider:
We don’t read to get faster at scanning words — we read to understand ideas and synthesize insights.
We don’t meditate to get better at meditating — we meditate for a clearer mind.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It’s easy to get caught up with <em>doing things</em>.</p>
<p>The dopamine hits make us feel accomplished, as if we have achieved our goal.</p>
<p>But what is our goal? Are we getting distracted from our true purpose?</p>
<p>There is a danger of mistaking action for motion.</p>
<p>Consider:</p>
<p>We don’t read to get faster at scanning words — we read to understand ideas and synthesize insights.</p>
<p>We don’t meditate to get better at meditating — we meditate for a clearer mind.</p>
<p>We don’t study to pass tests — we study to grasp human nature, and draw parallels in our present and to shape our future.</p>
<p>We don’t travel to get stamps in our passports — we travel to broaden our perspectives and connecting with others.</p>
<p>Let’s strive for purposeful motion over rote action.</p>
<p>Let’s measure the immeasurable: growth, impact, and connection.</p>
<p>It’s not about the quantity or speed of our actions, but the quality of the outcomes and the journey of growth along the way.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Travel, and what it&#39;s for</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/travel/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 20:22:34 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/travel/</guid>
      <description>We’re told that travel is for escaping. Exploration. Finding ourselves. Change.
In recent years, my travels have been comfortable. Predictable, safe; filled with activities I knew I like.
Then along came my nephews, and the impetus to give them opportunities that my sister and I never had in our childhoods.
Suddenly, I find myself in places I wouldn’t have naturally chosen, and doing activities that terrify me.
Like skiing and navigating bunny slopes.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We’re told that travel is for escaping. Exploration. Finding ourselves. Change.</p>
<p>In recent years, my travels have been comfortable. Predictable, safe; filled with activities I knew I like.</p>
<p>Then along came my nephews, and the impetus to give them opportunities that my sister and I never had in our childhoods.</p>
<p>Suddenly, I find myself in places I wouldn’t have naturally chosen, and doing activities that terrify me.</p>
<p>Like skiing and navigating bunny slopes. Like water parks and going down twisting, gravity-defying slides. Like amusement parks and charging down from great heights.</p>
<p>(Maybe this whole piece is about a fear of heights I didn’t formally realize I have.)</p>
<p>The boys rush into each new experience, squealing with laughter. I hesitate, climbing the heights with my heart pounding each time.</p>
<p>They laugh when I scream, and insist they aren’t scared at all.</p>
<p>But there is something infectious in their enthusiasm, and something humbling about their trust in the process. They don’t pause to overthink.</p>
<p>So, I try.</p>
<p>I try to rediscover wonder in places I’ve avoided and overlooked. Lead through discomfort, and push through the fear. It’s the core thesis of travel, right? Discovering parts of ourselves that that remain dormant, until we’re forced to confront them.</p>
<p>It doesn’t always work, but sometimes it is the thought that counts. I try, conceptually, to grow.</p>
<p>(And not just from eating a lot of good food, because “vacation”.)</p>
<p>These trips aren’t the poetic solo travel we romanticize. They’re loud, chaotic, and emotions get big. But they’re also transformative, with the change that comes from within and beyond.</p>
<p>I still hesitate at the top. But now, I’m learning to look forward to that moment when fear gives way to exhilaration.</p>
<p>When it does, I know what I’d have gained — these memory dividends that we’ll reap, for years to come.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reframe, rethink</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/reframe/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 20:28:59 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/reframe/</guid>
      <description>(Inspired by Brianna Wiest’s 101 Essays That Will Change The Way You Think)
You’re still functional — physically, at least. You can walk and you can sit, and you can shrug off the pain when it gets a little too much. You hold on to your values, even when it’s easier to just go with the path of least resistance. You can be proud of who you are. Work is tough, and some days it’s annoying, but so many people would love to be doing what you do.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>(Inspired by Brianna Wiest’s 101 Essays That Will Change The Way You Think)</p>
<ol>
<li>You’re still functional — physically, at least. You can walk and you can sit, and you can shrug off the pain when it gets a little too much.</li>
<li>You hold on to your values, even when it’s easier to just go with the path of least resistance. You can be proud of who you are.</li>
<li>Work is tough, and some days it’s annoying, but so many people would love to be doing what you do.</li>
<li>You earn enough to live comfortably, to go where you want and eat what you desire; enough to live on your own terms.</li>
<li>You’re allowed to think and ponder about what <em>living on your own terms</em> mean, and know that even though life isn’t ideal or where you’d thought it would be, it’s still a journey to get to where you envision it to be.</li>
<li>You have the weekend to decompress, even if decompressing means losing track of time as you doom-scroll through Reddit.</li>
<li>You just spent a good hour preparing for your lunches in the week ahead, and that is going to help with keeping track of actually eating lunch, which is something that has been a miss for so much of the last two years.</li>
<li>You have comfort shows and movies that you can dive back into; an embrace into a familiarity that makes your brain feel happy.</li>
<li>You have amazing friends. Quality &gt; quantity, especially in this case.</li>
<li>You think about all the different ways to get better, and to be better. You might fail and stumble along the way, but you’re still trying. You’re figuring it out. You’re still here.</li>
</ol>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meditating (and how I kind of suck at it, but that&#39;s the whole point)</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/meditating/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2022 14:43:15 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/meditating/</guid>
      <description>My mind is not a quiet place.
It’s full of thoughts; rooted in anxiety, in worry, over things I can’t control and things I can. More often than not, random lyrics and quotes are also bouncing in the ol’ noggin, in specific cadences and lilts as they were spoken in the medium I watched them in.
Late in 2019, I decided to give meditating a spin. I’ve heard the benefits of meditation many, many years ago, but have always dismissed it as a woo-woo new-age alt-medicine (is that enough hyphens yet?</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My mind is not a quiet place.</p>
<p>It’s full of thoughts; rooted in anxiety, in worry, over things I can’t control and things I can. More often than not, random lyrics and quotes are also bouncing in the ol’ noggin, in specific cadences and lilts as they were spoken in the medium I watched them in.</p>
<p>Late in 2019, I decided to give meditating a spin. I’ve heard the benefits of meditation many, many years ago, but have always dismissed it as a woo-woo new-age alt-medicine (is that enough hyphens yet?) practice. Yet, it has been shown that there are actual benefits to doing it: improving focus, decreasing anxiety, reducing stress, amongst others.</p>
<p>So, I did what I knew best: I read books<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, and used All The Apps<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>. I fumbled and wondered what I was doing wrong, and tried different things to see if this time, it’ll be the one that sticks.</p>
<h2 id="how-it-started">How it started</h2>
<p>I began with guided meditations.</p>
<p>Sometimes I fell back asleep if I did it as part of my waking up routine, which is bad because I would have turned my alarm off by that point. I’ve been lucky that I haven’t overslept by too much!</p>
<p>Meditating at night, too, helps me fall right asleep (except for recordings that have long pauses in between voices, in which case I would be on the precipice of sleep before getting jerked awake because of the unexpected voice in the dark). Now, if my aim was meditating for deep sleep, then this is a good outcome.</p>
<p>My priority was to build my focus and attention through mindfulness though, so the next thing I tried was using just the timer. I breathe in for four seconds, hold for four, and breathe out in – you guessed it – four seconds.</p>
<h2 id="how-its-going-badly-right">How it’s going (badly, right?)</h2>
<p>Meditation seems simple, but it’s not easy.</p>
<p>Here’s the thing that I’ve learned: Like sets of exercise for your body for your body, each ‘loss of focus  awareness  focus’ rep is your brain working out. That goes for every time you catch yourself drifting away, and bring yourself back to the present.</p>
<p>Now, I’m by no means an expert obviously, since I’m still fumbling. Even with 376 consecutive days under my belt, every morning still feels like a really tough 10 – 15 minutes. I find myself trying to remember more of my dreams that are slowly fading away, the things I need to put on my things-to-do list, or the next steps I need to take once the session is over.</p>
<p>I’m not gonna lie, I’ve been frustrated because I find myself getting distracted with tangential thoughts and having to pull myself back into focus. Sometimes the latter doesn’t happen, and I catch myself in the middle of a daydream as the ending bell sounds its gong.</p>
<h2 id="how-to-meditate-if-you-want-to">How to meditate, if you want to</h2>
<ol>
<li>Decide if you want to try it guided or unguided – I really like Insight Timer for both, especially for the latter, but Headspace is pretty cool for guided practice, with different lengths that you can choose from</li>
<li>Choose when you want to meditate, and make that a habit. I do it in the morning when I wake up, but that means I have to fit that in my morning schedule. If that doesn’t work for you, at night works as well</li>
<li>Close your eyes, and while they are close, lower your gaze (I learned this in Jay Shetty’s book, Think Like A Monk)</li>
<li>Start with short sessions, and build incrementally</li>
<li>You’re not doing it <em>wrong</em>, because there isn’t a right or wrong way</li>
</ol>
<p>Here’s to building your brain muscle!</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Mindfulness in Plain English, 10% Happier by Dan Harris, Conscious by Annaka Harris, Mindfulness: A Practical Guide to Awakening by Joseph Goldstein, Think Like A Monk by Jay Shetty&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Insight Timer, Calm, Headspace, and most recently, the Fitbit app&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>#IAmRemarkable</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/iamremarkable/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2022 14:49:09 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/iamremarkable/</guid>
      <description>Two weeks ago, I had the pleasure of attending an #IAmRemarkable session hosted by Akua Nyame-Mensah. The hour and a half flew past like it was nothing, and filled me with the hope that one day, too, I will not be filled with dread when it comes to talking about my own achievements.
(Even typing that! “My own achievements”…)
Why I attended this More than just for personal growth though, I definitely want the ladies and other marginalized members of my team to be able to have the confidence and competence to talk about what they have done and achieved.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Two weeks ago, I had the pleasure of attending an <a href="https://iamremarkable.withgoogle.com/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >#IAmRemarkable</a> session hosted by <a href="https://www.akuanm.com/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >Akua Nyame-Mensah</a>. The hour and a half flew past like it was nothing, and filled me with the hope that one day, too, I will not be filled with dread when it comes to talking about my own achievements.</p>
<p>(Even typing that! “My own achievements”…)</p>
<h2 id="why-i-attended-this">Why I attended this</h2>
<p>More than just for personal growth though, I definitely want the ladies and other marginalized members of my team to be able to have the confidence and competence to talk about what they have done and achieved.</p>
<p>I’ve never been someone who likes talking about myself, and I used to prefer sticking to the background and “doing the work” — just like a good little worker should, I thought. It served me well for a few years early in my career, because I had bosses who noticed the good work done, and I was rewarded appropriately.</p>
<p>When I moved to a consultancy, that changed. It was a culture shock in that area, being given the agency to chart your own career and having that be the norm. It wasn’t the greatest of workplaces though, and there were a lot of factors going into an appraisal beyond “work” done, like utilization hours… and how well you knew your leaders.</p>
<p>Now, though, where I work? There has been a giant shift to ‘owning’ your career, and the biggest change is having to put your own promotion package together and deciding when you’re ready to take the leap, instead of passively waiting for your manager to tell you that you’re ready. I went through that whole process earlier this year, and it was nerve-wracking and filled me up with so much imposter syndrome.</p>
<h2 id="moving-from-criticizing-to-self-love">Moving from criticizing to self-love</h2>
<p>There was definitely a lot of emphasis on shifting our mindsets, and moving yourself from one end of this spectrum to the other:</p>
<p>Criticizing → Constructive criticism → Self promotion → Self-love</p>
<h2 id="iamremarkable-because">#IAmRemarkable, because:</h2>
<p>The workshop also included some time for us to think about our own #IAmRemarkable statements, both writing them down and speaking out loud (or typing it in the chat).</p>
<p>I’m not gonna lie, I had to google for some inspiration because I needed a starting point, but here are my statements just in case I come up in your search, and you needed something to guide you too</p>
<ul>
<li>#IAmRemarkable, because I am always looking out for my team’s well-being</li>
<li>#IAmRemarkable, because I always want to do better and <em>be</em> better</li>
<li>#IAmRemarkable, because I am resilient through life changes and revelations</li>
<li>#IAmRemarkable, because I pay attention to the small details</li>
<li>#IAmRemarkable, because I try to live through my <a href="/authentic-life"  >core values</a> and using them to guide my decisions</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stoicism, and what we can control</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/stoic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2021 16:27:43 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/stoic/</guid>
      <description>I am the one thing in life I can control, Hamilton‘s Aaron Burr sings.
I grew up in a household where behaviours are mostly reactive, when sometimes it felt like things happening to you are a personal affront. It’s something that I have grown to reject, as I grew older (and hopefully wiser), but I also wanted a way to frame my thoughts and attitudes around things.
That’s when I discovered stoicism.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I am the one thing in life I can control, <em>Hamilton</em>‘s Aaron Burr sings.</p>
<p>I grew up in a household where behaviours are mostly reactive, when sometimes it felt like things happening to you are a personal affront. It’s something that I have grown to reject, as I grew older (and hopefully wiser), but I also wanted a way to frame my thoughts and attitudes around things.</p>
<p>That’s when I discovered stoicism.</p>
<p>There’s a lot with stoicism that leaves me scratching my head, confused if these men (all of them are, naturally) really did live their lives void of emotion when bad things happen, and worshipped logical thought as its own god.</p>
<p>Epicetetus wrote, “If, for example, you are fond of a specific ceramic cup, remind yourself that it is only ceramic cups in general of which you are fond. Then, if it breaks, you will not be disturbed.”</p>
<p>I thought, yeah, that makes sense. Things belong to you, and you don’t belong to things.</p>
<p>Then, he followed it up with, “If you kiss your child, or your wife, say that you only kiss things which are human, and thus you will not be disturbed if either of them dies.”</p>
<hr>
<p>Excuse me, <em>what</em>?</p>
<hr>
<p>I dove into Marcus Aurelius’ Meditations too.</p>
<p>That was an interesting read – I know it’s heralded as one of the leading texts to stoicism, and the emperor himself is regarded as one of the most influential humans and not just on stoicism. Some parts of the journal definitely felt like he was trying to convince himself that stoicism is the answer, too. It made sense, since he’d apparently never intended these private journal entries to be published.</p>
<p>I know if my journal entries, safely logged on Day One, were to be published one day, people would be befuddled too.</p>
<p>Ultimately, stoicism is still a domain that I’m <em>really</em> new at and exploring the different facets of.</p>
<p>At a glance, it seems like an answer, though at this point I’m not quite sure what the exact question is.</p>
<p>I’m still the one thing in life that I can control, which means: Things happen, and the only thing we can control is how we respond to them.</p>
<p>So I’m going to take this, probably struggle with it for a long time, but hey. At least I’ll be trying.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
