<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Stoicism on Jalyn Cai</title>
    <link>https://jalyncai.com/tags/stoicism/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Stoicism on Jalyn Cai</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Oct 2021 15:59:46 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jalyncai.com/tags/stoicism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>In/out of control</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/control/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Oct 2021 15:59:46 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/control/</guid>
      <description>My mentor asked me a simple question when I was catching up with her: What’s in your control, and what’s not?
—
I’ve touched on this topic before, while talking about stoicism and what we can control. That was February of this year, which seems both like a short time and a lifetime ago. I had a pretty pithy line to summarize then:
Things happen, and the only thing we can control is how we respond to them.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My mentor asked me a simple question when I was catching up with her: What’s in your control, and what’s not?</p>
<p>—</p>
<p>I’ve touched on this topic before, while talking about <a href="/control"  >stoicism and what we can control</a>. That was February of this year, which seems both like a short time and a lifetime ago. I had a pretty pithy line to summarize then:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Things happen, and the only thing we can control is how we respond to them.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Well, turns out, in life, things do happen.</p>
<p>With work, what is it that I can control? What is it that I struggle with accepting that I can’t control?</p>
<h3 id="i-cant-control">I can’t control:</h3>
<ul>
<li>The (types of) clients the team engages with</li>
<li>Other people’s actions, reactions, and decisions</li>
<li>Whether people would participate in one thing, and not another</li>
<li>How others perceive me</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="what-i-can">What I can:</h3>
<ul>
<li>How I react to these things happening</li>
<li>How I respond — a slight nuanced difference from the first thing, which is more in the moment</li>
<li>How much action I take, or do not take</li>
<li>The mindfulness I take towards my actions</li>
</ul>
<p>I vaguely alluded to a big shocking announcement at work last week; cue me googling ‘what to do when manager is laid off’ — <a href="/work-ethics"  >the same manager that was understanding of my morals at work</a> — and still trying to process it, about a week and a half after.</p>
<p>I’m still trying to figure out what it means for me (my own job security, my next step forward, building my promotion case) but it’s definitely given me a lot to think about, when I’m not being busy with actual work and calls, and dealing with bad timing (on my part) to try and get a CSR initiative off the ground.</p>
<p>I’m still on that adjusted working week — from Sunday to Thursday — for at least two more weeks, and I don’t think I’m ever going to get used to that, as long as the rest of my team is on Monday to Friday.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
