<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Writing on Jalyn Cai</title>
    <link>https://jalyncai.com/tags/writing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Writing on Jalyn Cai</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2024 20:49:34 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jalyncai.com/tags/writing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Challenges create change</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/change/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2024 20:49:34 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/change/</guid>
      <description>For years, I found comfort in the structure of a job — good performance and network building made for predictability, a sense of security, and an upward trajectory of what I thought I should be focusing on.
But here’s the thing — well, two things: firstly, that security just isn’t true anymore, in the landscape of layoffs; secondly and importantly, comfort doesn’t lead to real growth.
Sure, there is growth in the form of small income increments, or focusing on a niche (in my case, of user experience and design, and managing within the constraints of a team and client expectations).</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For years, I found comfort in the structure of a job — good performance and network building made for predictability, a sense of security, and an upward trajectory of what I thought I should be focusing on.</p>
<p>But here’s the thing — well, two things: firstly, that security just isn’t true anymore, in the landscape of layoffs; secondly and importantly, comfort doesn’t lead to <em>real</em> growth.</p>
<p>Sure, there is growth in the form of small income increments, or focusing on a niche (in my case, of user experience and design, and managing within the constraints of a team and client expectations).</p>
<p>But there is much more I want to learn and do, outside my expertise. Despite trying avenues within a corporate setting (like getting into the next-generation leadership team, and leading every extra-curricular interest group I was interested in), it wasn’t the exponential growth curve I was craving for.</p>
<p>There are questions, too, that I’ve been asking myself, about measuring the impact I’m making, and aligning my values with the work I’m doing.</p>
<p>So, here I am! I want to navigate uncharted territories, in the form of writing and sharing the synthesis of my learnings, in topics that are much more important to the foundation of how we live life, rather than the products and services we use.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s going to start as an <a href="https://www.instagram.com/jalyn.cai"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >Instagram</a> (apparently that&rsquo;s where the cool kids hang out to network, along with Twitter, but I don&rsquo;t think I want to go back to that platform), and then a <a href="https://newsletter.jalyncai.com"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >newsletter</a>.</p>
<p>I already know this is going to be a journey, and there will be mis-steps along the way. But I’m excited for the growth, and every step I take towards that.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Digital gardening</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/digital-garden/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2024 22:48:16 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/digital-garden/</guid>
      <description>I write: in my journal every night, chronicling my frustrations at myself and working through the mess in my head.
I write: in my notebook that I carry with me, scribbles of snippets from podcasts and books and articles.
I write: in Notion, in chat messages, in emails, in documentations that I am sure no one reads but it is still good to keep a second brain for the team at work (or so I tell myself for comfort).</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I write: in my journal every night, chronicling my frustrations at myself and working through the mess in my head.</p>
<p>I write: in my notebook that I carry with me, scribbles of snippets from podcasts and books and articles.</p>
<p>I write: in Notion, in chat messages, in emails, in documentations that I am sure no one reads but it is still good to keep a second brain for the team at work (or so I tell myself for comfort).</p>
<p>I write: fiction, tucked away in documents not many people have seen.</p>
<p>And so &ndash; am I a writer?</p>
<hr>
<p>I started <a href="/beginnings"  >my blog journey at the very tippy end of 2019</a>, with some ups and plenty of downs.</p>
<p>It was a slow start, with the pandemic roaring through without warning. Then, I tried to tackle consistency in 2021 and 2022, writing every single week, no matter the topic or the banality.</p>
<p>I succeeded, mostly, but writing fell to the wayside when I started preparing for the GMAT in 2023. Writing started to feel like a chore, and so I stopped doing it.</p>
<p>That is, on hindsight, one of the bigger oops on my personal growth journey.</p>
<p>Even in the age of AI and the threat of elimination with our core stack of skills, I believe writing still remains something that would differentiate the thinkers from the followers.</p>
<p>At the very least, the act of writing helps me to synthesize my own thoughts and understanding of myself, the world, and the society we live in.</p>
<p>(And boy, do we live in a society.)</p>
<hr>
<p>For four and a half years, this site lived on Wordpress, bloated with features as they came. I could never get my theme to work the way I wanted; half-baked widgets installed to try things, and hacks in custom css to make it <em>passable</em>.</p>
<p>So I decided: I wanted to build my own <a href="https://maggieappleton.com/garden-history"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >digital garden</a>.</p>
<p>From the perspective of the concept:</p>
<ul>
<li>It should evolve as I do</li>
<li>I get to learn in public</li>
<li>Ideas get to pollinate and cross-cultivate (maybe I am taking the garden analogy to far)</li>
</ul>
<p>For the tech stack:</p>
<ul>
<li>It has to be lightweight</li>
<li>Updating needs to be easy</li>
</ul>
<p>Above all, I want to have fun writing in public again.</p>
<hr>
<p>All of that to say: this site is now powered by Hugo, I had a steeper-than-expected learning curve with git, and my html/css skills are rusty but not completely down.</p>
<p>It also means that I am manually migrating entries over, but this gives me the chance to prune my thinking, and reflect on my past writing.</p>
<p>So &ndash; please expect breakages in links, and things not working (yet! consider this an MVP) as I figure this out. I&rsquo;m excited to be excited about writing again.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>(and at once i knew i was not magnificent)</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/writing-stuff-playlist/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2021 16:26:33 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/writing-stuff-playlist/</guid>
      <description>I call this my ‘writing stuff’ playlist, in which I do everything but.
Run – Daughter Tip of my Tongue – The Civil Wars Set the Fire to the Third Bar – Snow Patrol ft. Martha Wainwright When I Go – Slow Club Blood Bank – Bon Iver Off I Go – Greg Laswell Alaska – Maggie Rogers Thunder Clatter – Wild Cub Challengers – The New Pornographers My Backwards Walk – Frightened Rabbit There’s another version of this playlist that’s basically just all of Little Mix’s discography, Broadway recordings, and The Barden Bellas, so there’s that.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I call this my ‘writing stuff’ playlist, in which I do everything but.</p>
<ol>
<li>Run – Daughter</li>
<li>Tip of my Tongue – The Civil Wars</li>
<li>Set the Fire to the Third Bar – Snow Patrol ft. Martha Wainwright</li>
<li>When I Go – Slow Club</li>
<li>Blood Bank – Bon Iver</li>
<li>Off I Go – Greg Laswell</li>
<li>Alaska – Maggie Rogers</li>
<li>Thunder Clatter – Wild Cub</li>
<li>Challengers – The New Pornographers</li>
<li>My Backwards Walk – Frightened Rabbit</li>
</ol>
<p>There’s another version of this playlist that’s basically just all of <a href="/little-mix"  >Little Mix’s discography</a>, Broadway recordings, and The Barden Bellas, so there’s that.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beginnings</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/beginnings/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2019 16:55:46 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/beginnings/</guid>
      <description>I want to start a blog.
This has been something that has been on my mind for the past ten years, although if I’m being honest with myself (and that’s the goal here!), it has definitely been something I’ve thought of for way longer than the last decade.
I’ve flirted with Blogger as a teen, painstakingly linking my high school friends’ blogs in the sidebar and refreshing each of them daily, before I discovered RSS (and before it faded away).</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I want to start a blog.</p>
<p>This has been something that has been on my mind for the past ten years, although if I’m being honest with myself (and that’s the goal here!), it has definitely been something I’ve thought of for way longer than the last decade.</p>
<p>I’ve flirted with Blogger as a teen, painstakingly linking my high school friends’ blogs in the sidebar and refreshing each of them daily, before I discovered RSS (and before it faded away). I had a carefully curated LiveJournal about my favorite TV shows and films and music, and for a few years, it was such a big part of my life online.</p>
<p>I’d even installed easily a dozen or so WordPress blogs when I started freelancing as a web designer when I was 18, and created endless mental reminders for myself to get the ball rolling on one myself when the blogs I was reading shifted into the mainstream.</p>
<p>Yet, the daunting expectations of being consistent in writing and putting something out into the world, coupled with the imposter syndrome of feeling like my thoughts aren’t worthy enough of documentation gave me pause in my steps towards doing just that.</p>
<p>There isn’t really a grand plan or strategy in place for this little corner of the internet I’m parking myself in, though. Plenty of things and conversations I want to have with people, and it would probably reflect the intersections of my life, my values, and things I find interesting.</p>
<p>More likely than not, it would chronicle my journey in optimizing my life, my path to financial independence, my attempts at intentionality and minimalism, and my lifelong pursuit of fitness (both physical and mental!).</p>
<p>I want to start a blog, and so, as a new year and decade begins – here I am.</p>
<p>Hello, world!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
