<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Corporate Life on Jalyn Cai</title>
    <link>https://jalyncai.com/tags/corporate-life/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Corporate Life on Jalyn Cai</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Oct 2021 15:59:46 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jalyncai.com/tags/corporate-life/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>In/out of control</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/control/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Oct 2021 15:59:46 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/control/</guid>
      <description>My mentor asked me a simple question when I was catching up with her: What’s in your control, and what’s not?
—
I’ve touched on this topic before, while talking about stoicism and what we can control. That was February of this year, which seems both like a short time and a lifetime ago. I had a pretty pithy line to summarize then:
Things happen, and the only thing we can control is how we respond to them.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My mentor asked me a simple question when I was catching up with her: What’s in your control, and what’s not?</p>
<p>—</p>
<p>I’ve touched on this topic before, while talking about <a href="/control"  >stoicism and what we can control</a>. That was February of this year, which seems both like a short time and a lifetime ago. I had a pretty pithy line to summarize then:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Things happen, and the only thing we can control is how we respond to them.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Well, turns out, in life, things do happen.</p>
<p>With work, what is it that I can control? What is it that I struggle with accepting that I can’t control?</p>
<h3 id="i-cant-control">I can’t control:</h3>
<ul>
<li>The (types of) clients the team engages with</li>
<li>Other people’s actions, reactions, and decisions</li>
<li>Whether people would participate in one thing, and not another</li>
<li>How others perceive me</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="what-i-can">What I can:</h3>
<ul>
<li>How I react to these things happening</li>
<li>How I respond — a slight nuanced difference from the first thing, which is more in the moment</li>
<li>How much action I take, or do not take</li>
<li>The mindfulness I take towards my actions</li>
</ul>
<p>I vaguely alluded to a big shocking announcement at work last week; cue me googling ‘what to do when manager is laid off’ — <a href="/work-ethics"  >the same manager that was understanding of my morals at work</a> — and still trying to process it, about a week and a half after.</p>
<p>I’m still trying to figure out what it means for me (my own job security, my next step forward, building my promotion case) but it’s definitely given me a lot to think about, when I’m not being busy with actual work and calls, and dealing with bad timing (on my part) to try and get a CSR initiative off the ground.</p>
<p>I’m still on that adjusted working week — from Sunday to Thursday — for at least two more weeks, and I don’t think I’m ever going to get used to that, as long as the rest of my team is on Monday to Friday.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Feedback and growth in the workplace</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/workplace-goals/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jan 2021 16:29:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/workplace-goals/</guid>
      <description>I’m in the process of setting my 2021 OKRs for work right now. As a starting point, my mentor had requested for me to think about my strengths and how to tie it all together.
Me: Okay, I’m going to need some time to think about my strengths. Also me: Do you want weaknesses too? I can give them to you right now, if you want.
An experiment in gathering feedback I used to squirm at the idea of talking about myself.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’m in the process of setting my 2021 OKRs for work right now. As a starting point, my mentor had requested for me to think about my strengths and how to tie it all together.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Me:</strong> Okay, I’m going to need some time to think about my strengths.
<strong>Also me:</strong> Do you want weaknesses too? I can give them to you right now, if you want.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="an-experiment-in-gathering-feedback">An experiment in gathering feedback</h2>
<p>I used to squirm at the idea of talking about myself. Actually, that’s a lie – I still squirm at the idea, but now I (begrudgingly) recognize its value in allowing people to consider both the quality of my work, and the sum of my character.</p>
<p>I’m always trying to make things easier for myself though, and to that end, I’ve been experimenting.</p>
<p>At the end of each project or phase of work last year, I sent out a really simple Typeform survey to my teammates, which has 4 questions, and a scale to answer. They look something like this:</p>
<ul>
<li>Jalyn was helpful and was aligned to the team’s objectives.</li>
<li>Jalyn delivered a high quality of work and showed her value to the team.</li>
<li>I will work with Jalyn again / I will recommend Jalyn to other teams in the future.</li>
</ul>
<p>And finally, an open-ended area for comments.</p>
<p>This was also something my old team at a previous workplace had done, although that was done on a team/delivery level, and not a personal one.</p>
<p>It’s also interesting, as I have received more useful qualitative feedback through these surveys than the team did with it.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-it-good-for">What is it good for?</h2>
<p>Where it shines in my exercise to find my strengths and weaknesses (which said mentor has reframed as <em>road blocks</em>, which I thought was very nice) is that it gives me a way to cluster the feedback I received.</p>
<p>This way, I get to pull exact quotes across all the different work I’ve done, and be able to back my own perceived performance with this feedback.</p>
<h2 id="a-demonstration-in-action">A demonstration in action</h2>
<p>(Just an example each!)</p>
<p>For my self-anointed strength of:</p>
<p><strong>Collaboration between functions –</strong> “She has good technical knowledge and is able to bridge the gap between design and tech.”</p>
<p><strong>Positive and can-do attitude –</strong> “She radiates passion and inspires her peers to drive and push the work further.”</p>
<p><strong>Providing structure –</strong> “You came in with your usual neat and organised approach, and the new design system is super neat and easy to go through.”</p>
<p>So, let’s chalk this up as an experiment gone well. I’ll have to think about tweaking it to optimize it even further, but I’m definitely going to carry through asking my teammates for some kind of feedback now!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Non-Definitive Guide To Starting A New Job</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/new-job/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2020 20:11:51 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/new-job/</guid>
      <description>I’ve switched jobs — not counting freelance and contract work — twice in my career.
Three times, now, once I start my new job on Monday. My last day at my previous employee was Friday, so you can say that I love cutting things close.
Now, clearly this is an occupational hazard, but a UXer’s gotta UX, you know? So I’ve cobbled together some objectives I want to test out for my new job.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’ve switched jobs — not counting freelance and contract work — twice in my career.</p>
<p>Three times, now, once I start my new job on Monday. My last day at my previous employee was Friday, so you can say that I love cutting things close.</p>
<p>Now, clearly this is an occupational hazard, but a UXer’s gotta UX, you know? So I’ve cobbled together some objectives I want to test out for my new job.</p>
<h2 id="schedule-regular-one-on-one-catch-ups-with-the-manager">Schedule regular one-on-one catch-ups with the manager</h2>
<p>This should probably be self-explanatory.</p>
<p>Earlier in my career, I was more than happy to shy away from these, believing that my work would speak for itself.</p>
<p>Obviously, that’s a naive belief.</p>
<p>I’ve also had managers who were too busy, and these sessions usually got pushed and postponed and eventually, canceled. I’ll have to figure out what to do if this situation happens again, but fingers crossed it wouldn’t!</p>
<p><strong>The plan:</strong> Schedule weekly check-ins (at least for the first month), set expectations, and check in often to see if I’m missing the mark.</p>
<p>We go around recommending the notion of launching fast and failing fast, so why not translate that for my own development?</p>
<h2 id="get-to-proactively-know-my-new-colleagues">Get to proactively know my new colleagues</h2>
<p>I’m a textbook introvert, and some days, I’d rather be at my desk, hunkering down on the actual work. Not to the point of being anti-social, but I’m definitely more charming on a one-on-one basis than a group of more than 30 people, staring expectantly at me.</p>
<p><strong>The plan:</strong> Have lunch/coffee with at least one new person every week, unless I’m away in a project/agile team. And even then! The team will be new to me and vice versa, so it will be helpful for everyone.</p>
<p>The 2019-nCoV might hinder this plan if things keep escalating. We’ll see, though! I’ll still try my best.</p>
<p>This leads in nicely to…</p>
<h2 id="find-mentors">Find mentors</h2>
<p>One glaring thing that I’ve definitely lacked in my previous jobs was diversifying the mentorship I was getting.</p>
<p>I haven’t really branched out beyond direct management, even though I’ve always meant to find mentors outside of my team.</p>
<p><strong>The plan:</strong> Identify at least three mentors within the organization, and see how I can help them with their own goals and metrics.</p>
<p>So, there’s that to cover for the first quarter. There will be plenty to learn as I try to hit the ground running, but it’ll be a fun adventure nonetheless.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
