<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Jalyn Cai</title>
    <link>https://jalyncai.com/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Jalyn Cai</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2025 15:47:33 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jalyncai.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>2024: Year in review</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/2024-year-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2025 15:47:33 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/2024-year-in-review/</guid>
      <description>I’d started writing this on the first day of the new year, as has been my tradition since 2020, but my ceiling started leaking. I’m really hoping that it isn’t a harbinger of things to come in 2025.
Onward!
What went well Strength: If you know me, you know I’ve struggled with fitness my entire life: issues with my lower back, my lungs, a self-imposed limiting belief that I’m “just not athletic”.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’d started writing this on the first day of the new year, as has been my tradition since 2020, but my ceiling started leaking. I’m really hoping that it isn’t a harbinger of things to come in 2025.</p>
<p>Onward!</p>
<h2 id="what-went-well">What went well</h2>
<p><strong>Strength:</strong> If you know me, you know I’ve struggled with fitness my entire life: issues with my lower back, my lungs, a self-imposed limiting belief that I’m “just not athletic”.</p>
<p>But with great aplomb (and a drum roll, please): I lost ~13% of myself in 2024! My InBody scale tells me nearly all of it was fat loss, and I’m not about to argue with it.</p>
<p>This was a combination of nutrition, the 160 workouts I did — approximately one workout every 2.28 days — and physical therapy exercises for my back, which left me feeling lighter and stronger than ever.</p>
<p>A major breakthrough was finally cracking the cardio code: daily treadmill walks for 45 minutes — while reading on my Kindle (important! I look forward to these treadmill sessions because of this).</p>
<p>On the food intake end, my concept of <em>minimal viable protein</em> served me well for days that are both typical, and not (traveling, for example).</p>
<p>Lastly, I addressed loose ends (i.e. fixing my infected implant, getting a cyst on my scalp removed, being better at skincare and sunscreen application, etc etc.)</p>
<p>—</p>
<p><strong>Alignment:</strong> This has been a transformative year internally. A recurring theme in past yearly reviews had been about work, and how much that had vexed me. Those alone should’ve raised alarm bells, but I ignored them, year after year.</p>
<p>In the second half of the year, something clicked: it wasn’t finding another job in the corporate world, nor was it climbing the ladder and losing even more of myself in the process.</p>
<p>Instead, I started examining what my skills (design, operations, strategy) could create impact, beyond the confines of corporate structures.</p>
<p>That’s when the idea of turning the design process inward came, using it to fuel personal development and growth. From this emerged the concept of being a <em>full stack being</em>, centered on building strength, thinking, alignment, connection and knowledge.</p>
<p>This shift transformed my focus from merely staying afloat as a design leader in a consultancy, to writing and using design as a vehicle for exploration and experimentation. It’s a move beyond delivering user flows, screens, and slide after slide of a “UX strategy” destined to be dismissed.</p>
<p>(Can you feel my burnout and jadedness of the craft?)</p>
<p>So far, I’ve launched a newsletter, and an Instagram exploring this concept.</p>
<p>But more on these in the months ahead :)</p>
<p><strong>New skills:</strong> Like my GMAT exam on the day before a year-end trip last year, 2024 repeated that pattern with my driving license (though it was planned to be earlier in November, but I had failed the first attempt). I’m now able to legally terrorize the streets!</p>
<p>I also took on side quests that I hadn’t planned on, with skiing, learning Spanish, and playing chess as my top three highlights of skills acquired. They weren’t part of a grand plan, but they brought me joy and are stark reminders that staying curious and open are my core values.</p>
<p><strong>More traveling:</strong> I zipped around a fair bit: Germany, Austria, The Philippines, The UK, France, Malaysia, then finally to China. It’s a cliche, but I truly do love it.</p>
<h2 id="what-couldve-gone-better">What could’ve gone better</h2>
<p><strong>Improving focus and reducing screen time:</strong> This isn’t an uncommon issue amongst the chronically online. I found myself reaching for my phone, doom scrolling through social media and Reddit, even though I <em>know</em> I should be doing anything else instead.</p>
<p>Case in point: I just wasted 15 minutes scrolling through YouTube shorts. YouTube shorts! How did I even get there?!</p>
<p>Screen time was abysmal; huge chunks of hours without me even realizing it. I’ve put in a few guardrails, like using greyscale mode and setting time limits, but it’s clear I ned more deliberate approaches.</p>
<p>The lack of focus connects to a larger problem: avoiding discomfort and boredom. Recognizing it is half the battle (I hope!) and now it’ll be about sitting with these feelings and finding alternatives.</p>
<p>—</p>
<p><strong>Speed in decision making:</strong> A pattern of overthinking and analysis paralysis underpins this, and ends up with me wasting time by not moving forward and getting stuck in loops.</p>
<p>Or maybe it’s the perfectionist streak in me, with unrealistic expectations of how fast things should move. We’ll unpack this a lot more in 2025, I hope!</p>
<p>—</p>
<p><strong>Managing anxiety more effectively:</strong> I am, by default, wrought with anxiety. It’s basically background noise to me now. I’ve been trying all the usual tricks — meditating, journaling, working out — but there is a baseline that I return to.</p>
<p>Then there were the things I was excessively anxious about: the layoffs in the company, how my teammates were coping, my financial situation in the case that it drops on me.</p>
<p>But I learned an important lesson here: no amount of anxiety makes any difference to anything that is going to happen. Instead, I want to try and shift my focus on the things that are going to move the needle, and converting that into something constructive instead.</p>
<h2 id="themes-from-my-gratitude-journal">Themes from my gratitude journal</h2>
<ul>
<li>Having the time and space to think and experiment</li>
<li>Traveling and exploring new places</li>
<li>The nephews being happy; spending time with them</li>
<li>Doing new things that scare me</li>
<li>Being excited about life again</li>
<li>Doing things that brought joy</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="what-i-want-to-do-in-2025">What I want to do in 2025</h2>
<h3 id="strength">Strength</h3>
<ul>
<li>Feel lighter and more energetic</li>
<li>Get technically better at skiing</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="thinking">Thinking:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Let go of the scarcity mindset and internalize that “investing in yourself is not a waste</li>
<li>Reduce phone usage as default for boredom</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="alignment">Alignment</h3>
<ul>
<li>Build the full stack life in public</li>
<li>Redefine what good enough work and great work look like outside the corporate world</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="connection">Connection</h3>
<ul>
<li>More solo traveling</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="knowledge">Knowledge</h3>
<ul>
<li>Consistently learn how to play the guitar</li>
<li>Leave space for side quests</li>
</ul>
<p>I’m hopeful that the theme of 2025 is one of exploration, and giving myself permission to wander off the main path of conventions and expectations.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Challenges create change</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/change/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2024 20:49:34 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/change/</guid>
      <description>For years, I found comfort in the structure of a job — good performance and network building made for predictability, a sense of security, and an upward trajectory of what I thought I should be focusing on.
But here’s the thing — well, two things: firstly, that security just isn’t true anymore, in the landscape of layoffs; secondly and importantly, comfort doesn’t lead to real growth.
Sure, there is growth in the form of small income increments, or focusing on a niche (in my case, of user experience and design, and managing within the constraints of a team and client expectations).</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For years, I found comfort in the structure of a job — good performance and network building made for predictability, a sense of security, and an upward trajectory of what I thought I should be focusing on.</p>
<p>But here’s the thing — well, two things: firstly, that security just isn’t true anymore, in the landscape of layoffs; secondly and importantly, comfort doesn’t lead to <em>real</em> growth.</p>
<p>Sure, there is growth in the form of small income increments, or focusing on a niche (in my case, of user experience and design, and managing within the constraints of a team and client expectations).</p>
<p>But there is much more I want to learn and do, outside my expertise. Despite trying avenues within a corporate setting (like getting into the next-generation leadership team, and leading every extra-curricular interest group I was interested in), it wasn’t the exponential growth curve I was craving for.</p>
<p>There are questions, too, that I’ve been asking myself, about measuring the impact I’m making, and aligning my values with the work I’m doing.</p>
<p>So, here I am! I want to navigate uncharted territories, in the form of writing and sharing the synthesis of my learnings, in topics that are much more important to the foundation of how we live life, rather than the products and services we use.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s going to start as an <a href="https://www.instagram.com/jalyn.cai"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >Instagram</a> (apparently that&rsquo;s where the cool kids hang out to network, along with Twitter, but I don&rsquo;t think I want to go back to that platform), and then a <a href="https://newsletter.jalyncai.com"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >newsletter</a>.</p>
<p>I already know this is going to be a journey, and there will be mis-steps along the way. But I’m excited for the growth, and every step I take towards that.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Motion, not action</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/motion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2024 21:44:01 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/motion/</guid>
      <description>It’s easy to get caught up with doing things.
The dopamine hits make us feel accomplished, as if we have achieved our goal.
But what is our goal? Are we getting distracted from our true purpose?
There is a danger of mistaking action for motion.
Consider:
We don’t read to get faster at scanning words — we read to understand ideas and synthesize insights.
We don’t meditate to get better at meditating — we meditate for a clearer mind.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It’s easy to get caught up with <em>doing things</em>.</p>
<p>The dopamine hits make us feel accomplished, as if we have achieved our goal.</p>
<p>But what is our goal? Are we getting distracted from our true purpose?</p>
<p>There is a danger of mistaking action for motion.</p>
<p>Consider:</p>
<p>We don’t read to get faster at scanning words — we read to understand ideas and synthesize insights.</p>
<p>We don’t meditate to get better at meditating — we meditate for a clearer mind.</p>
<p>We don’t study to pass tests — we study to grasp human nature, and draw parallels in our present and to shape our future.</p>
<p>We don’t travel to get stamps in our passports — we travel to broaden our perspectives and connecting with others.</p>
<p>Let’s strive for purposeful motion over rote action.</p>
<p>Let’s measure the immeasurable: growth, impact, and connection.</p>
<p>It’s not about the quantity or speed of our actions, but the quality of the outcomes and the journey of growth along the way.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Travel, and what it&#39;s for</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/travel/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 20:22:34 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/travel/</guid>
      <description>We’re told that travel is for escaping. Exploration. Finding ourselves. Change.
In recent years, my travels have been comfortable. Predictable, safe; filled with activities I knew I like.
Then along came my nephews, and the impetus to give them opportunities that my sister and I never had in our childhoods.
Suddenly, I find myself in places I wouldn’t have naturally chosen, and doing activities that terrify me.
Like skiing and navigating bunny slopes.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We’re told that travel is for escaping. Exploration. Finding ourselves. Change.</p>
<p>In recent years, my travels have been comfortable. Predictable, safe; filled with activities I knew I like.</p>
<p>Then along came my nephews, and the impetus to give them opportunities that my sister and I never had in our childhoods.</p>
<p>Suddenly, I find myself in places I wouldn’t have naturally chosen, and doing activities that terrify me.</p>
<p>Like skiing and navigating bunny slopes. Like water parks and going down twisting, gravity-defying slides. Like amusement parks and charging down from great heights.</p>
<p>(Maybe this whole piece is about a fear of heights I didn’t formally realize I have.)</p>
<p>The boys rush into each new experience, squealing with laughter. I hesitate, climbing the heights with my heart pounding each time.</p>
<p>They laugh when I scream, and insist they aren’t scared at all.</p>
<p>But there is something infectious in their enthusiasm, and something humbling about their trust in the process. They don’t pause to overthink.</p>
<p>So, I try.</p>
<p>I try to rediscover wonder in places I’ve avoided and overlooked. Lead through discomfort, and push through the fear. It’s the core thesis of travel, right? Discovering parts of ourselves that that remain dormant, until we’re forced to confront them.</p>
<p>It doesn’t always work, but sometimes it is the thought that counts. I try, conceptually, to grow.</p>
<p>(And not just from eating a lot of good food, because “vacation”.)</p>
<p>These trips aren’t the poetic solo travel we romanticize. They’re loud, chaotic, and emotions get big. But they’re also transformative, with the change that comes from within and beyond.</p>
<p>I still hesitate at the top. But now, I’m learning to look forward to that moment when fear gives way to exhilaration.</p>
<p>When it does, I know what I’d have gained — these memory dividends that we’ll reap, for years to come.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Morning routines - from chaos to calm</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/morning-routines/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 20:14:58 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/morning-routines/</guid>
      <description>I used to be that person. You know, the one who would wake up at 8:47 if I had to be out of the house by 9, patting myself on the back for not wasting any time.
The routine was planned down to the second:
Get out of bed (3 minutes to roll around and contemplate why I have to wake up, groan, and check my phone notifications) Go to the bathroom (7 minutes — no time for sun screen!</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I used to be <em>that</em> person. You know, the one who would wake up at 8:47 if I had to be out of the house by 9, patting myself on the back for not wasting any time.</p>
<p>The routine was planned down to the second:</p>
<ul>
<li>Get out of bed (3 minutes to roll around and contemplate why I have to wake up, groan, and check my phone notifications)</li>
<li>Go to the bathroom (7 minutes — no time for sun screen!)</li>
<li>Put on my clothes and socks and shoes, and grab my bag (1.5 minutes, hope fervently that I haven’t forgotten any items)</li>
<li>Run down to the bus line (1.5 minutes, and then I pretend I’m not gasping for air once I’m on the bus)</li>
</ul>
<p>Sometimes, if I did these things fast enough, I’d even have time to check my Instagram feed before the bus arrives. Score!</p>
<p>All in the name of optimization, right?</p>
<h2 id="why-a-morning-routine">Why a morning routine?</h2>
<p>Here’s the question I struggled with, as I learned more about other people’s morning routines: Why bother with doing other things in an actual routine, when I could be ready in 13 minutes from bed to bus?</p>
<p>The answer, I find out after begrudgingly experimenting, is that not everything is about efficiency.</p>
<p>A chaotic morning sets the tone for an equally chaotic day. Rushing through those 13 minutes left me constantly playing catch-up, both physically and mentally. I wasn’t starting the day on my own terms; I was simply reacting to the world around me.</p>
<p>Even on weekends when I had nowhere to be at 9, the chaos followed me in different ways, like picking up my phone and staying glued to it, (doom-)scrolling until half the day had slipped by.</p>
<p>By noon, I’d have nothing to show for it, but a drained battery — my phone’s, and my own energy — and that familiar foreboding sense of “I should’ve done something”.</p>
<p>For me, the morning routine is about setting the day right, and how I show up for myself every day by completing what I have set out as a <a href="/non-negotiables"  >non-negotiables</a>.</p>
<p>More than that, it’s a guard rail against procrastination, knowing that I have a series of objectives I want to hit and <a href="/streaks"  >continue my streaks on</a>.</p>
<h2 id="the-components-of-a-routine">The components of a routine</h2>
<p>It shouldn’t come as a shock that an intentional morning routine plays a crucial role in setting the day right.</p>
<p>Some parts are unavoidable, like the fact that you’d have to go to the bathroom, or getting dressed (and helping the kids too, if you’re a parent!).</p>
<p>But there are experiments that you can tailor and build for your own needs:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Hydration:</strong> Getting some water in you, whether that means plain, or mixed with minerals and electrolytes</li>
<li><strong>Movement:</strong> Any kind works — walking, stretching, yoga, gym, pilates, running… as long as you’re not jumping back under your blankets</li>
<li><strong>Mindfulness:</strong> Small practices that yield big mental dividends with journaling, gratitude listing, morning pages, meditating, or praying</li>
<li><strong>Light exposure:</strong> Getting the sunlight into your eyes, as popularized by Dr. Andrew Huberman, proven to trigger hormones that increase your energy and mood</li>
<li><strong>Reading:</strong> Try a few pages, or see how much you can read in 10 minutes</li>
<li><strong>Breakfast:</strong> Bonus points if you’ve prepped for this so you can just pop it into a microwave oven</li>
<li><strong>Skincare:</strong> A little goes a long way with some moisturizer and sunscreen</li>
<li><strong>Cold shower:</strong> A bracing way to energize and shock yourself into action</li>
<li><strong>Hobby-time:</strong> If you’ve always felt like you have no time to spend on something you find meaningful and fun, build that into your mornings while your mind is still fresh</li>
<li><strong>Caffeine:</strong> Coffee, tea, pre-workout — whatever you need to keep the sluggishness away</li>
<li><strong>Planning:</strong> Look ahead at your day, and get clarity and prioritize what needs to be done</li>
</ul>
<p>Remember, the key isn’t to do <em>everything</em>, but to see which ones could positively impact your day.</p>
<p>Falling into the trap of trying to do too much, too soon, is too easy. Evaluate what you can make stick. Like other habits, consistency is going to help make this an automated part of your life.</p>
<h2 id="my-routine-in-experimentation">My routine, in experimentation</h2>
<h3 id="the-waking-moment">The waking moment</h3>
<p>I wake up at 6:30am, walk about ten steps away to my desk, and switch the phone alarm off. In a new note in Obsidian, I quickly jot down my dreams, or what I can remember of them, and in the subject of the note, <a href="/waking"  >I pen down what I’m grateful for in the moment</a>.</p>
<h3 id="skincare">Skincare</h3>
<p>Then, I head into the bathroom. After, I wash my face and slap some sunscreen on.</p>
<h3 id="hydration">Hydration</h3>
<p>I step on my smart body scale to document my weight and body fat percentage. After that, I drink about 500ml of water.</p>
<h3 id="movement">Movement</h3>
<p>It diverges into 2 paths here:</p>
<ul>
<li>Gym day: I grind some coffee beans, mix the espresso with protein powder for a pre-workout drink, and spend the next hour and a half at the gym</li>
<li>Walking: This is a new one that I’ve implemented just over a month ago! I put on my walking shoes and walk for 45 minutes, while the morning air and ground are cool. Previously, I’d jump straight to showering and starting on the day’s work.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="cold-shower--meditation">Cold shower &amp; meditation</h3>
<p>When I come back from either, I take a cold shower, then do a quick 15-minute meditation at my desk.</p>
<h3 id="hobby">Hobby</h3>
<p>Recently, I’ve added a 15-minute Duolingo session. I know it’s not the most efficient way of studying a new language, but it’s fun and it helps my brain to shift into a different mode.</p>
<h3 id="planning">Planning</h3>
<p>Finally, once that is done, I look at my calendar and personal kanban board, to remind me of what’s possible for the day.</p>
<h2 id="the-evolution-of-the-morning-routine">The evolution of the morning routine</h2>
<p>Shaping the routine is going to be an ongoing process.</p>
<p>There will be periods when your life demands a more streamlined approach, and you’ll have to stick with the essentials.</p>
<p>Other times, you might find yourself with more space and time to add on components to your build.</p>
<p>The key, as with other things in your life, is being flexible and experimenting with what works for <em>you</em> and your intentions.</p>
<h2 id="your-turn-starting-small">Your turn: Starting small</h2>
<ol>
<li><strong>Identify your drivers:</strong> Figure out what you want to get out of a structured routine. Is it more energy, a sense of accomplishment, or a calmer start?</li>
<li><strong>Start with one thing, and be consistent:</strong> It’s better to do one thing well than five things haphazardly.</li>
<li><strong>Experiment and adjust:</strong> Evaluate after a week. Keep a log (mental, or otherwise) of how you feel about each component. If it’s working, great! Let’s add another. If it doesn’t, replace it based on your drivers in step one.</li>
<li><strong>Be kind to yourself:</strong> You’ll have setbacks when you feel like doing anything but the routine. Progress, not perfection, is the goal.</li>
</ol>
<p>What’s one change you’d like to make to your morning routine? I’d love to discuss what’s working and what isn’t, and your victories and challenges!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Streaks, and not letting go of a good one</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/streaks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2024 21:23:15 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/streaks/</guid>
      <description>There’s just something about streaks.
The dopamine hitting as I see the numbers go higher, the satisfaction of knowing I kept a small promise to myself.
Then there are the actual benefits of these streaks, which are the habits that are now ingrained in my life, like the mental clarity with mediation, the documentation of my days and life while journaling, the cultivating of a more resilient and happier mindset with a gratitude practice, and then some.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There’s just something about streaks.</p>
<p>The dopamine hitting as I see the numbers go higher, the satisfaction of knowing I kept a small promise to myself.</p>
<p>Then there are the <em>actual</em> benefits of these streaks, which are the habits that are now ingrained in my life, <a href="/non-negotiables"  >like the mental clarity with mediation, the documentation of my days and life while journaling, the cultivating of a more resilient and happier mindset with a gratitude practice, and then some</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p>I started keeping streaks after reading the popular books about habits — Atomic Habits, Tiny Habits, The Power of Habit and so on.</p>
<p>The premise is simple: you start, and then you do it again the next day.</p>
<p>Then the next.</p>
<p>And the next.</p>
<p>Before you know it, you’re well into habit formation territory, and it’ll be a part of your day and life from here on out.</p>
<p>The extra benefit of seeing a big number is not wanting your perceived momentum to stop.</p>
<p>I experimented with different methods:</p>
<ul>
<li>Analog, with a habit tracker drawn out on a page and crossing boxes out</li>
<li>A tracking app that consolidates the streaks during that season of life</li>
<li>Individual apps with their own tracking widgets (and, as I am learning after using Duolingo for nearly two weeks, threats of meltdowns)</li>
</ul>
<p>But there is a dark side to this.</p>
<hr>
<p><em>&ldquo;I don&rsquo;t really have a lot to write today, but I&rsquo;m still opening this app and typing something so that I don&rsquo;t lose my streak.&rdquo;</em></p>
<p>Entries like this in my journaling app happen once every few months, when I’m dead tired and it’s 11pm, way past my bedtime, and I have the widget telling me there’s a circle that needs filling in.</p>
<p>Or the days when I would startle out of bed when I remember I haven’t done something, and the slight relief when I sneak in under the wire.</p>
<p>There is a subtle shift, I think, from the purpose of building the habit, to keeping the streak alive.</p>
<p>Such as:</p>
<p>Am I being intentional and mindful of the time spent with my thoughts, or am I going through the motions to settle into a session, simply to maintain my meditation streak?</p>
<p>Do I practice actual gratitude when I’m writing it first thing in the morning, or am I being grateful for grateful’s sake for the continued motion?</p>
<p>Then there is that toxic view of how I feel like I’m erasing all my past <em>xxx</em> days worth of effort, by not continuing for a day.</p>
<hr>
<p>Still, though, I think the good outweighs the bad.</p>
<p>There’s something grounding about having the structure in place. Sure, some days they feel like an obligation, but they’re also a guard rail to me veering off-course when things get overwhelming and messy (and they do!).</p>
<p>And maybe it’s less about being perfect, and more about being a human and being persistent. These streaks are the tangible things I can hold and say hey, I’m trying. I’m showing up for myself. It is less about the habit, and more about who I am and I’m becoming.</p>
<p>So I’ll keep going. Because in the daily repetition, I see the quiet promise of growth, and the reminder that showing up still counts, even if it’s imperfect.</p>
<p>Just like I’ll show up to write these every week, or thereabouts. Not for the streak, but for the story that I’m still learning to tell.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trying a new wind-down routine</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/winddown/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 07:34:51 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/winddown/</guid>
      <description>The last time I talked about my sleep was in 2020, where I laid out how terrible my night routine was, amidst other things.
This year, I have been working on being more consistent with sleeping by 10:30pm so that I can be awake by 6:45am, at the latest. I enjoy being up just before the sun is, and I find that I get more done in the early hours.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The last time I talked about <a href="/sleep"  >my sleep was in 2020</a>, where I laid out how terrible my night routine was, amidst other things.</p>
<p>This year, I have been working on being more consistent with sleeping by 10:30pm so that I can be awake by 6:45am, at the latest. I enjoy being up just before the sun is, and I find that I get more done in the early hours.</p>
<p>It’d worked, judging from my <a href="/waking"  >daily log in Notion</a>; a time range between 6:20am, and 7am when I snooze, which isn’t that often as the months progressed.</p>
<h2 id="the-wind-down-routine">The wind-down routine</h2>
<p>Around or before 9:30pm, I brush my teeth, wash my face and put my moisturizer on, and start reading on my Kindle; usually fiction.</p>
<p>Then, at 10pm, the Day One notification kicks in for my <a href="/non-negotiables"  >journaling practice</a>, where I write in two entries: one to recap the day and my free-flowing thoughts, and the other as a response to the daily prompt.</p>
<p>Once I’m done, I put the phone on the charging dock at my desk, away from the bed.</p>
<p>Then I’ll put the eye mask and night guard on, and off to sleep I go.</p>
<h2 id="and-then-tragedy-strikes">And then… tragedy strikes</h2>
<p>Okay, well, it isn’t that serious:</p>
<p>Mid-July, I started on a shifted work schedule. This new schedule has me ending work at 10pm, and with calls that extend beyond for some nights.</p>
<p>With the timeline laid out above, it’s clear that I can’t start winding down before 10 at the earliest.</p>
<p>While I get additional hours in the morning to myself, my energy management at night is, understandably, impacted.</p>
<p>My brain is going at 100 mph, as a result of being an active participant in calls, trying to wrap up work-related tasks, and staring at the bright screen.</p>
<p>I also have to fit in showering, an activity that happened much earlier in the evening before.</p>
<p>Two patterns have emerged at the point when I get to my bed:</p>
<ol>
<li>I skip reading altogether, and find myself doom-scrolling on social media and Reddit, despite knowing these are not important activities</li>
<li>Or, I try to read, and feeling revenge bedtime procrastination, I stay up until past midnight to finish reading instead</li>
</ol>
<p>So, that’s not great.</p>
<p>I’m not sure when this time shift would end, as the client engagement is slated to go on for a while longer.</p>
<p>But I’m also not sure how long I can sustain this lack of a structure and routine.</p>
<h2 id="fixes-to-try">Fixes to try</h2>
<p>For the next week, here is my plan:</p>
<ul>
<li>Add a 5-minute meditation after I unplug my work devices, to try and nudge the brain to a more shut-down state</li>
<li>Shift reading to the morning, and truncate my wind-down to general cleanliness, meditating, and journaling</li>
<li>Explore buying a pair of clip-on blue light blocking glasses. <a href="https://nocry.com/products/overspecs-orange"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >These ones from NoCry</a> look okay, but they don’t ship to Singapore</li>
</ul>
<p>The root of the problem is the schedule itself though, I know. Let’s see how successful I am in trying to shift things back to normalcy, an hour at a time.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adding an iPad to my personal workflow</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/ipad/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2024 09:54:50 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/ipad/</guid>
      <description>I’ve recently acquired an old, barely-responsive iPad in my arsenal.
It’s a 5th generation unit, and something my mother has used for at least 18 hours every day, since 2017.
Truth be told, I’m surprised that it isn’t in a worse condition, as it was used for intensive video playing for 18 hours, every single day:
There is noticeable burn in the screen, right in the middle The backlight is yellow and flickering The response time isn’t what you’ll call speedy The battery is at 70% of its capacity Those are my observations from a week’s usage, and it’s far from its hey day.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’ve recently acquired an old, barely-responsive iPad in my arsenal.</p>
<p>It’s a 5th generation unit, and something my mother has used for at least 18 hours every day, since 2017.</p>
<p>Truth be told, I’m surprised that it isn’t in a worse condition, as it was used for intensive video playing for 18 hours, every single day:</p>
<ul>
<li>There is noticeable burn in the screen, right in the middle</li>
<li>The backlight is yellow and flickering</li>
<li>The response time isn’t what you’ll call speedy</li>
<li>The battery is at 70% of its capacity</li>
</ul>
<p>Those are my observations from a week’s usage, and it’s far from its hey day.</p>
<p>But it <em>works,</em> and I’m having fun, experimenting how it fits in my workflow.</p>
<h2 id="as-a-consumption-device">As a consumption device</h2>
<p>This is undoubtedly the lowest-hanging use case, and the one with the least friction.</p>
<p>Cutting down screen time on my phone has been a recent focus, with culprits like Reddit monopolizing much of my time and attention. Even with the app deleted on the phone!</p>
<p>I offloaded the streaming apps from my phone, and while I’ll continue to use my Kindle for reading, it looks like I can read PDF books easier on the bigger, zoomable screen.</p>
<h2 id="as-a-capture-device">As a capture device</h2>
<p>My general knowledge management system revolves around… a pen, and an internet connection. It’s something I am actively experimenting with, outside the iPad conundrum.</p>
<p><em>But</em>, until I figure that out, Notion remains my primary tool for long-form capture, and Telegram’s ability to send short messages to myself for quick capture notes.</p>
<p>Which brings me back to connectivity as a main driver of my capture system: this iPad is WiFi-only.</p>
<p>If I’m at home, it wouldn’t be the first thing I reach for when it comes to notes, and if I’m outside, it is less of a hassle to capture it on my phone, than if I were to tether a connection from it to the bigger device.</p>
<p>So, that’s a no-go for my typical note-taking.</p>
<p>But there is an edge here: scribblings and drawings.</p>
<p>Right now, I use a random notebook from Muji capturing ideas and diagrams. I haven’t figured out the offline-to-online syncing of these ideas, other than sinking in a lot of money for a reMarkable for that purpose.</p>
<p>But, I’ll be spending more time seeing if this new addition to the flow works.</p>
<h2 id="as-a-writing-device">As a writing device</h2>
<p>I was pretty delighted to realize that my keyboard connects to the iPad, even if it takes about a second for the lag to catch up.</p>
<p>Half of this article was typed half the iPad, while I’m hanging out at a cafe.</p>
<p>I’ll admit, the first question I posed to myself was: when will it ever be more convenient to go out with a keyboard and an iPad, versus going out with my (also new) MacBook Air?</p>
<p>It could be the novelty speaking, but writing on the iPad might give me an edge of focus.</p>
<p>Again, something I’ll have to experiment with a little more.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non-negotiable habits</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/non-negotiables/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2024 11:53:40 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/non-negotiables/</guid>
      <description>There are things in life that people do automatically, like motor reflexes with blinking and swallowing, or actions like locking the door and — unfortunately — checking the phone for notifications.
Similar to values that you do not compromise on, your actions stack towards habits that form the cornerstones of your life. These actions set the tone for how you feel and provides the momentum for other positive habits you’re trying to build.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There are things in life that people <em>do</em> automatically, like motor reflexes with blinking and swallowing, or actions like locking the door and — unfortunately — checking the phone for notifications.</p>
<p>Similar to <a href="https://www.rd.com/article/non-negotiables/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >values that you do not compromise on</a>, your actions stack towards habits that form the cornerstones of your life. These actions set the tone for how you feel and provides the momentum for other positive habits you’re trying to build.</p>
<hr>
<p>With a few years of experiments on my belt, here are my non-negotiable habits as of August 2024.</p>
<h3 id="one-liner-gratitude-when-i-wake-up">One-liner gratitude when I wake up</h3>
<p>When the alarm on the phone goes off, I make the ten-step hike from my bed to the table and switch it off.</p>
<p>I start a new entry in my daily log on Notion; take a pause through the haziness of sleep, and write one thing that I am grateful for, in the title of the entry.</p>
<p>Logging it on Notion serves as a time stamp for my wake-up times, which is always useful for trend-spotting each month.</p>
<p>I try to log down my dream(s) in the body of the note. <a href="/waking"  >They disappear like wisps, sometimes.</a></p>
<h3 id="tracking-my-time-nutrition-and-expenses">Tracking: My time, nutrition, and expenses</h3>
<p>Even though we now know that the quote <a href="https://nesslabs.com/what-gets-measured-gets-managed"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >“what gets measured gets managed”</a> is a misnomer at best, and an opposite interpretation at worst, it is still helpful for me.</p>
<p>First, it gives me the outputs for my behaviour.</p>
<p>Want to know how many minutes I’ve invested in traveling this year? I see it in <a href="https://toggl.com/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >Toggl</a>, and because I’ve been tracking since 2018, I can work out how many experience dividends I’m getting from year to year.</p>
<p>Want to know how much money I’m spending on groceries up until today for the month? <a href="https://www.spendee.com/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >Spendee</a> tells me the amount, because I’ve made it a habit to log every purchase the moment I make them.</p>
<p>And for nutrition? It’s the same logic, and helpful as I keep track of the amount of protein I ingest every day.</p>
<p>Secondly, and more importantly, the act of doing the thing makes me want to be more conscientious and deliberate. This has been a huge mind shift in the way I approach these building blocks of life.</p>
<p>(Though there is something to be said about the scarcity mindset I have observed in me sometimes. Something to experiment more on!)</p>
<h3 id="work-outs-at-least-three-times-a-week">Work outs, at least three times a week</h3>
<p>My workout routine has me completing four workouts a week, so three times is keeping it safe on weeks where I feel like <a href="/spondy"  >my back can’t handle more than</a>, or if I fall sick/injured.</p>
<p>On typical weeks when I’m not traveling, I pick myself up first thing in the morning to do them. It sets my energy levels higher through the day when I do, but there are slight differences in power and endurance when I do them later on in the day.</p>
<p>As an addition, at a minimum I’m aiming for <em>activity</em> every day. It’s a morning walk these days, on days I don’t go to the gym.</p>
<h3 id="meditating-at-least-10-minutes-a-day">Meditating, at least 10 minutes a day</h3>
<p>I don’t have a set time for when I do this; even with a 1,695 day streak, I’m still playing around with what works best.</p>
<p>But the important thing is that I <em>do</em> it, whether it is right before I settle into working, during a break in the middle of the day, or when I am walking.</p>
<h3 id="reading-at-least-ten-minutes-a-day">Reading, at least ten minutes a day</h3>
<p>My Kindle (a pretty laggy 7th-gen Paperwhite) is never far from me — on my desk, on the table, in my bag — and if I have free moments in between calls at work, I’m trying to reach the end of a chapter in a non-fiction book.</p>
<p>Additionally, I block half an hour before bedtime to do light fiction reading, though the time expands and contracts depending on when the work day ends; something to work on more diligently.</p>
<h3 id="journaling-before-i-sleep">Journaling before I sleep</h3>
<p>Through my life I have trialed and tested many different mediums (digital vs. a proper journal), timings (mornings vs. nights), and methods (free writing, lists, bullet, unsent letters…).</p>
<p>For now, I journal on <a href="https://dayoneapp.com/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >Day One</a> through my phone (it’s telling me I have a 1,413 day streak today!), where I have two journals: one for free-form writing about what happened during the day, and another to answer the daily prompt.</p>
<p>The free-form writing journal gives me the chance to unload what is on my mind that has been playing incessantly throughout the day.</p>
<p>I find that reflecting on my actions, and dumping the contents of my brain to work through potential solutions, ways I should be reacting, and paths forward has been helpful in clarity.</p>
<p>For the daily prompts, that’s just a fun way to surface topics I wouldn’t think of, and reach to the edges of diving into them.</p>
<hr>
<p>I’m probably forgetting non-negotiables that are second nature to me (i.e. drinking 2 litres of water, using dental floss, applying sunblock), but that is not a bad thing.</p>
<p>More that I am thinking about: Is there an optimal number or a maximum of habits before the system falls apart? What about rigidity vs. fluidity of the way I act upon them? Psychological barriers or breakthroughs?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Digital gardening</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/digital-garden/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2024 22:48:16 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/digital-garden/</guid>
      <description>I write: in my journal every night, chronicling my frustrations at myself and working through the mess in my head.
I write: in my notebook that I carry with me, scribbles of snippets from podcasts and books and articles.
I write: in Notion, in chat messages, in emails, in documentations that I am sure no one reads but it is still good to keep a second brain for the team at work (or so I tell myself for comfort).</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I write: in my journal every night, chronicling my frustrations at myself and working through the mess in my head.</p>
<p>I write: in my notebook that I carry with me, scribbles of snippets from podcasts and books and articles.</p>
<p>I write: in Notion, in chat messages, in emails, in documentations that I am sure no one reads but it is still good to keep a second brain for the team at work (or so I tell myself for comfort).</p>
<p>I write: fiction, tucked away in documents not many people have seen.</p>
<p>And so &ndash; am I a writer?</p>
<hr>
<p>I started <a href="/beginnings"  >my blog journey at the very tippy end of 2019</a>, with some ups and plenty of downs.</p>
<p>It was a slow start, with the pandemic roaring through without warning. Then, I tried to tackle consistency in 2021 and 2022, writing every single week, no matter the topic or the banality.</p>
<p>I succeeded, mostly, but writing fell to the wayside when I started preparing for the GMAT in 2023. Writing started to feel like a chore, and so I stopped doing it.</p>
<p>That is, on hindsight, one of the bigger oops on my personal growth journey.</p>
<p>Even in the age of AI and the threat of elimination with our core stack of skills, I believe writing still remains something that would differentiate the thinkers from the followers.</p>
<p>At the very least, the act of writing helps me to synthesize my own thoughts and understanding of myself, the world, and the society we live in.</p>
<p>(And boy, do we live in a society.)</p>
<hr>
<p>For four and a half years, this site lived on Wordpress, bloated with features as they came. I could never get my theme to work the way I wanted; half-baked widgets installed to try things, and hacks in custom css to make it <em>passable</em>.</p>
<p>So I decided: I wanted to build my own <a href="https://maggieappleton.com/garden-history"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >digital garden</a>.</p>
<p>From the perspective of the concept:</p>
<ul>
<li>It should evolve as I do</li>
<li>I get to learn in public</li>
<li>Ideas get to pollinate and cross-cultivate (maybe I am taking the garden analogy to far)</li>
</ul>
<p>For the tech stack:</p>
<ul>
<li>It has to be lightweight</li>
<li>Updating needs to be easy</li>
</ul>
<p>Above all, I want to have fun writing in public again.</p>
<hr>
<p>All of that to say: this site is now powered by Hugo, I had a steeper-than-expected learning curve with git, and my html/css skills are rusty but not completely down.</p>
<p>It also means that I am manually migrating entries over, but this gives me the chance to prune my thinking, and reflect on my past writing.</p>
<p>So &ndash; please expect breakages in links, and things not working (yet! consider this an MVP) as I figure this out. I&rsquo;m excited to be excited about writing again.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Argh, Apple (and how to get unstuck on the iOS update during setup)</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/ios-unstuck/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 19:18:16 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/ios-unstuck/</guid>
      <description>My dad’s phone was an iPhone 11 that he’s had for several years now, and one day, with no warning, it stopped charging.
My stop-gap solution was to hand him my wireless charger, which worked for a bit technically, but wasn’t suited for his work flow.
That’s okay; it was nearly Father’s Day so my sister and I got the iPhone SE for him.
After a week or so of waiting (which was about 6 days longer than I had anticipated; something to unpack here about my apparent high standards for delivery timelines), it arrived.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My dad’s phone was an iPhone 11 that he’s had for several years now, and one day, with no warning, it stopped charging.</p>
<p>My stop-gap solution was to hand him my wireless charger, which worked for a bit technically, but wasn’t suited for his work flow.</p>
<p>That’s okay; it was nearly Father’s Day so my sister and I got the iPhone SE for him.</p>
<p>After a week or so of waiting (which was about 6 days longer than I had anticipated; something to unpack here about my apparent high standards for delivery timelines), it arrived.</p>
<h2 id="the-ordeal">The ordeal</h2>
<p>I thought it would be simple with the data transfer — he doesn’t have too many apps or personal data on his phone, and I only needed to preserve the connection to his work VPN, and chat history on the handful of chat apps he has that aren’t cloud-based.</p>
<p>(Yeah, looking at you, Whatsapp.)</p>
<p>I thought it would be simple and that it would only take a few minutes, because that’s how Apple has conditioned us to behave, right?</p>
<p>Instead, after pairing the phone and hitting ‘next’ on the steps, it got stuck on the iOS download and update screen.</p>
<p>I thought: this must be a mistake, so I restarted the process, did the pairing again, clicked ‘next’ again.</p>
<p><em>Sigh.</em></p>
<p><a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=iphone&#43;new&#43;phone&#43;setup&#43;software&#43;update&#43;2&#43;days&#43;site:discussions.apple.com"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >A cursory search found this issue starting back from at least 2020</a>; at one point it told me it would take 5 days for it to finish downloading and transferring.</p>
<h2 id="the-solution">The solution</h2>
<ol>
<li>Set up the phone as if it’s a new phone, and do not choose to import your settings and data from your old phone — no worries, you can do the transfer after these steps</li>
<li>With the brand new phone, navigate to Settings &gt; General &gt; Software Update</li>
<li>Wait a reasonable 15 – 20 minutes for the iOS update to be downloaded and updated</li>
<li>Then, reset this phone to its factory settings, by going to Settings &gt; General, and scrolling all the way down to Transfer or Reset iPhone</li>
<li>Ignore the confusing taxonomy and select the ‘Erase All Content and Settings’ option</li>
<li>Voilà. <em>Now</em> you can go through the phone data transfer and not run into the 5-day-wait problem</li>
</ol>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning and blundering in chess and life</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/blundering/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2024 17:21:47 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/blundering/</guid>
      <description>Looks like this year is an actual year of learning, because I decided to pick chess up on a whim.
A real whim, or a procrastination technique from doing up my portfolio? You decide.
I knew how to play the basics of Chinese chess (象棋), which just meant I knew how the pieces moved, so there are some parts that now feel familiar. I mean, am I calling the knight a horse (馬), because that’s what the Chinese piece is and they move in the exact same way in the L shape, except there are more restrictions on a Chinese horse?</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Looks like this year is an actual year of learning, because I decided to pick chess up on a whim.</p>
<p>A real whim, or a procrastination technique from doing up my portfolio? You decide.</p>
<hr>
<p>I knew how to play the basics of Chinese chess (象棋), which just meant I knew how the pieces moved, so there are some parts that now feel familiar. I mean, am I calling the knight a horse (馬), because that’s what the Chinese piece is and they move in the exact same way in the L shape, except there are more restrictions on a Chinese horse?</p>
<p>Obviously.</p>
<p>Also, no flying King, which is something the General can do, which makes it a little less exciting for 5 year old me who wanted that General to fly every single time.</p>
<hr>
<p>I can’t say enough great things about <a href="https://www.learnchesswithdrwolf.com/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >Learn Chess with Dr. Wolf</a>, which is structured enough that I feel like I’m learning something new every time I open the app, but also gamified enough that I <em>want</em> to open the app. Some dialogue made me laugh outright, especially when I blunder — and I am blundering <em>so</em> much.</p>
<p>One important thing that I’m learning is just how many blind spots I have. There’s that analogy to the decisions I’m making not just in playing a match, but in real life. I’m not someone you can call impulsive, but in games, I can see how my inexperience and lack of focus make my decisions a liability. Sometimes I’m too eager to win pieces, but I end up losing material instead because I failed to see that the piece was protecting another more important one.</p>
<p>A bigger issue that I’m still working through is not being able to instinctively see when a move leads to a stalemate. I think this is slightly worse than losing pieces, and again, analogously to life, have I doomed myself to a lose/lose situation instead of one that would be beneficial on whichever metric I frame it with?</p>
<p>I’m excited to learn more, both about chess, and about how it feeds back into my life.</p>
<hr>
<p>(Also, yes, I speed-watched Queen’s Gambit because I missed that boat in 2020 and only saw it for the first time last weekend. I love complex competent characters )</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On skiing and trying things for the first time</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/skiing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2024 19:42:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/skiing/</guid>
      <description>I’m generally risk-averse, I learned about myself a long time ago. I’m overly cautious, frenetically anxious, and incessantly worry about the unknowns. (Which, yes, is an issue in itself, and something I’m trying to manage, to varying degrees of success.)
Yet, in the last week, I found myself strapping into boots and skis that made my body cry in agony. I fell no less than half a dozen times on the first day.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’m generally risk-averse, I learned about myself a long time ago. I’m overly cautious, frenetically anxious, and incessantly worry about the unknowns. (Which, yes, is an issue in itself, and something I’m trying to manage, to varying degrees of success.)</p>
<p>Yet, in the last week, I found myself strapping into boots and skis that made my body cry in agony. I fell no less than half a dozen times on the first day. And the second, and the third.</p>
<p>I wished I didn’t have that much churning in my amygdala, as I chanted “oh no, oh no, oh no”, both in my head and aloud as I skidded, stumbled, and skittered across an icy landscape so unfamiliar to me.</p>
<p>In contrast, my nephews — who turned six today! — took to the sport so naturally, unfazed by falls and bumps. And it wasn’t like they had a lot of practice before this vacation either; just perhaps a combined five days of skiing ever in their lives as of yet.</p>
<p>I envy the fearlessness, and the ability to embrace learning something new and making themselves better.</p>
<h2 id="the-fun-scale">The fun scale</h2>
<p>There is this concept about different kinds of fun, <a href="https://kellycordes.com/2009/11/02/the-fun-scale/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >defined as</a>:</p>
<ul>
<li>Type I: Enjoyable while it is happening</li>
<li>Type II: Enjoyable in retrospect</li>
<li>Type III: Not enjoyable at all</li>
</ul>
<p>I’m a few days removed from burning up under my layers in the freezing weather (a really interesting dichotomy I had never experienced before).</p>
<p>My wide feet ached, my thick shins hurt (partly because of my rookie mistake of wearing my base layer under my socks), and I reeked of cigarette smoke because my instructor was smoking at a rate of a pack per hour, not helped by the fact that he had to wait patiently for me.</p>
<h3 id="day-one">Day one</h3>
<p>Him: You won’t fall.</p>
<p>Me, with skis shifting under my weight and not being able to do anything about them: I’m SLIDING!</p>
<p>Him, laughing: Yes, you are on ice.</p>
<p>Me: <em>falls</em></p>
<hr>
<p>Spoiler: I really enjoyed myself.</p>
<hr>
<p>If Day 1 was me terrified and obstructed by my mental barriers, Day 2 would be about turning my disbelief into confidence. At the start of the day, I was still scared of everything — sliding on the snow, going onto <a href="https://www.the-ski-guru.com/2019/12/06/different-types-lifts-resortshow-ride-them/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >the magic carpet</a>, hanging on to dear life on a rope tow, and then falling while going up on a surface lift.</p>
<p>I wouldn’t say something <em>clicked</em>, but I’d even managed to steer myself by imitating the instructor in front of me, who did very leisurely turns very slowly for my benefit. In 6 total hours by the end of the second day, I was much, much more in control, and that definitely built my confidence.</p>
<p>I’m really proud of myself. I’m proud of embracing the learning of something new, and for not succumbing to my anxiety and managing to push through.</p>
<p>I hadn’t realized it explicitly before then, but I hadn’t felt like I was trying something new for the first time in a very long time. (I guess <a href="https://jalyn.co/its-me-hi-im-the-problem/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >the GMAT attempt</a> didn’t count in my head!)</p>
<h2 id="random-observations">random observations</h2>
<p>(Placeholder image space!)</p>
<ul>
<li>The incredible mountain views did some healing on my ruined city psyche. We’ll see how long this high lasts as I slide back, unfortunately not onto the snow, but work instead</li>
<li>I want to continue to strengthen myself: I know what my limiting factors are (broken back, weak core, and weirdly-shaped feet), so I might start doing specific workouts to focus on movements that would aid in my next skiing experience</li>
<li>Direction is more important than speed, but to shift, you still need some speed. How’s that for inspiration?</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2023: Year in review</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/2023-year-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 19:53:50 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/2023-year-in-review/</guid>
      <description>Once again, I’m looking back on the year that’s passed. (See: 2020, 2021, 2022)
It seems a little tougher this year — and I won’t say whether it’s because I haven’t been consistently and habitually writing on this site — but I’m always happy to reflect and introspect on what has gone well and what I could’ve done better with.
What went well: Learning and growth: Last year, one of my goals was to try and figure out whether to take my MBA aspiration more seriously.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Once again, I’m looking back on the year that’s passed. (See: <a href="/2020-year-in-review"  >2020</a>, <a href="/2021-year-in-review"  >2021</a>, <a href="/2022-year-in-review"  >2022</a>)</p>
<p>It seems a little tougher this year — and I won’t say whether it’s because I haven’t been consistently and habitually writing on this site — but I’m always happy to reflect and introspect on what has gone well and what I could’ve done better with.</p>
<h2 id="what-went-well">What went well:</h2>
<p><strong>Learning and growth:</strong> Last year, one of my goals was to try and figure out whether to take my MBA aspiration more seriously. To that end, one of the hurdles was taking the GMAT. After some on-off studying for half a year, I scored a 645 on the GMAT Focus, which clears that 700 barrier on the classic GMAT.</p>
<p>It’s a score that I’m pleased with (and proud of, considering I hadn’t taken a standardized test for more than half my life at this point), but it is also a score that I think I <em><strong>can</strong></em> improve on if I studied and grinded for a little longer. I haven’t started doing that, but maybe — let’s see where I’m at with applications in Q1 of this year.</p>
<p><strong>Reading:</strong> Surprisingly, even with studying taking up all/most of my free time, I still managed to read 25 books in 2023. The last book that I read was <em><strong>The First Fifteen Lives of Harry August</strong></em>, and oh, boy. One of my favorite books is <strong>Replay</strong>, which deals with a Groundhog Day situation but with an entire life (almost), and <strong>Harry August</strong> turned that up a notch. I might re-read it now.</p>
<p><strong>Traveling:</strong> This was almost a given, given how we’re recovering from the pandemic and figuring out what that looks like with traveling. I’ve not traveled as much as I wanted to as an adult, so I’m happy to get back into this and train this muscle of experiencing other cultures, environments, and weathers.</p>
<p><strong>New hobbies:</strong> I’m slowly getting into completely new things, like appreciating matcha (and the art of making a cup), and watches (I got a Seiko Presage in Tokyo, and it’s one of my favorite purchases). On the other hand, I’m also… (Author’s note: I forgot where I was going with this, and left this dangling.)</p>
<h2 id="what-couldve-gone-better">What could’ve gone better:</h2>
<p><strong>Fitness and health:</strong> Sigh. With the stress of studying, fitness got wildly deprioritized. Even then, I managed 116 workouts in 2023 — nearly 1 in 3 days, which is a complete shock to me as I spent all of December not working out at all. Definitely something to push on in 2024!</p>
<p>I’ve also spent most of the day in a haze; my asthma coming back the last week of the year.</p>
<p><strong>Finance:</strong> I only hit a 59% savings rate. I don’t know — can I partially justify that by saying I didn’t get a raise (not even a salary adjustment to inflation) this year? I don’t <strong>regret</strong> making the purchases, though.</p>
<p><strong>Work:</strong> Ah, something that is a mainstay through the years. It’s a pattern that I don’t like, but it’s not something I can shake easily. In 2023, my corporate life was rocked a little by layoffs and restructuring, and though I kept my job and stepped (the fuck) up to several positions beyond me, it’s been a mostly thankless endeavor and I’ve even got my promotion case denied, so…</p>
<p>I guess I’m evaluating a lot about what work, and this workplace, means to me. There is some cognitive dissonance here with my pursuit of a potential MBA, given the implication of working hard and elevating myself career-wise. But we’ll see.</p>
<h2 id="themes-from-my-gratitude-journal">Themes from my gratitude journal:</h2>
<ul>
<li>Space for me to try my best</li>
<li>My nephews being happy</li>
<li>Being excited about possibilities</li>
<li>Time away to travel and think</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="what-i-want-to-do-in-2024">What I want to do in 2024:</h2>
<ul>
<li>Learn to drive and obtain my license</li>
<li>Apply for and get admitted to an MBA program</li>
<li>Evolve my style beyond Uniqlo and t-shirts</li>
<li>Travel even more (this is shaping up quite excitingly with a trip to Germany/Austria in January!)</li>
<li>Figuring out my skincare routine</li>
</ul>
<p>As always, I hope the next 365 days (leap year!) are going to be kind and good to all of us.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When did I stop having fun?</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/fun/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 20:00:07 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/fun/</guid>
      <description>“只是玩toy toy而已，不要做东西” (or: I just want to play toys, and not do anything).
Wise words from my 5-year old nephew about his ideal day made me crack up, but also made me wonder: When did I stop having fun?
—
Last year, I ruminated a little on having fun, with the full intention of trying out a year of fun. Then, in typical me fashion, this all got pushed to the wayside because of work, and also because of the bigger health concerns I discovered during that same time.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>“只是玩toy toy而已，不要做东西” (or: I just want to play toys, and not do anything).</p>
<p>Wise words from my 5-year old nephew about his ideal day made me crack up, but also made me wonder: When did I stop having fun?</p>
<p>—</p>
<p>Last year, I <a href="/how-to-fun"  >ruminated a little on having fun</a>, with the full intention of trying out a year of fun. Then, in typical me fashion, this all got pushed to the wayside because of work, and also because of the bigger health concerns I discovered during that same time.</p>
<p>But it’s really plain to see: I have grown really, really bad at producing serotonin. If I’m not doing work, I’m thinking about work or work-adjacent things, like mentoring and productivity and optimizing. If something I’m doing doesn’t build towards learning, I feel guilty.</p>
<p>Here’s a laundry list of things that I do already do that I think are fun, and also ways I have made them… just a little bit stressful:</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Activity</th>
<th>Stress-inducing approach</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Writing</td>
<td>Worrying about feedback and engagement</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Reading</td>
<td>Setting yearly targets that I cram into December</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Playing</td>
<td>Getting the best times, or perfect scores</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Watching cleaning videos</td>
<td>Wondering what I’m <em>actually</em> getting out of it</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Then there are the other buckets of activities that require money, and, well. I’m someone who takes about five years to make money decisions.</p>
<p>So, given this, I’ve asked my friends on Instagram to give me suggestions.</p>
<h2 id="the-suggestions">The suggestions</h2>
<p>(Curated, based on physical feasibility)</p>
<p><strong>Physical activity:</strong> Walking/hiking, skating, dancing, geocaching, bouldering, yoga</p>
<p><strong>Non-physical</strong> a<strong>ctivities:</strong> Watching nature, Drinking, K-Pop, skincare, shopping, reading</p>
<p><strong>Games and puzzles:</strong> Legos, chess, video games</p>
<p><strong>New skills</strong>: Knitting/crocheting, guitar, photography, cooking, painting, baking, drawing, cycling, pottery/carpentry</p>
<p><strong>Volunteering</strong></p>
<p>—</p>
<p>I think it’s a pretty good list to get started.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2022: Year in Review</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/2022-year-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 20:11:25 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/2022-year-in-review/</guid>
      <description>It’s become a habit now; a yearly one, to look back on the year that has passed and reflect on what has gone well and what could’ve gone better (see: 2021, 2020). My writing is rusty now, with my non-rigour and letting my habit die off this year.
2022 has been a mixed bag of blessings and regrets, and of going on auto-pilot and letting things fall on the wayside.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It’s become a habit now; a yearly one, to look back on the year that has passed and reflect on what has gone well and what could’ve gone better (see: <a href="/2021-year-in-review"  >2021</a>, <a href="/2020-year-in-review"  >2020</a>). My writing is rusty now, with my non-rigour and letting my habit die off this year.</p>
<p>2022 has been a mixed bag of blessings and regrets, and of going on auto-pilot and letting things fall on the wayside.</p>
<h2 id="what-went-well">What went well:</h2>
<p><strong>Fitness:</strong> This is separate from health, for reasons we’ll go into in the <em>what could’ve gone better</em> section</p>
<p>This year, I got a gym membership in March, and then in July, a personal trainer. I ended up with 75 sessions in total, which comes up to around a session every 3.8 days. My main drive for going to the gym is to get stronger — something that is a little hard to do as I can’t consistently overload because of my <a href="/spondy"  >Back Situation™</a>.</p>
<p>I hit several PRs in the last two sessions of the year — made possible only because I ate at maintenance for these last two weeks; I’m in a deficit otherwise. PRs make me feel like I’m unlocking achievements, but I know it’s a really unpredictable road that I’m on, and I’m still learning how to accept my limitations.</p>
<p>My weakest exercises definitely have to do with my back and core, which are… important, you know, to the general anatomy.</p>
<p>But also: I meal prepped for the majority of the year, and was a little more consistent with my meal timings! I’ll take that as a W.</p>
<p><strong>Finance</strong>: My savings rate dropped to 63% this year, from my target of 70%. Yet — I’m at peace with it, since I’m <a href="/frugal"  >trading money for my health and fitness</a>. The hugest chunk of money went to aforementioned personal training sessions, as well as physiotherapy sessions which was an unexpected expense, and insurance only covered a minuscule part of it.</p>
<p>I also finally upgraded my iPhone X to a 14 Pro! Other than that, I didn’t travel this year at all, and kept to my yearly budget in all other categories.</p>
<p><strong>Relationships and connections</strong>: I got much closer to a few work-buddies-elevated-to-friends, and I’m glad to have forged these friendships as I surround myself with people who inspire me and push me to be better.</p>
<p><strong>Hair</strong>: <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/CZ_9fkCvOUx/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >I got it cut!</a></p>
<h2 id="what-couldve-gone-better">What could’ve gone better:</h2>
<p>Probably everything else.</p>
<p><strong>Health</strong>: I have had back problems for a few years now, and in April I decided that I wanted to get a referral letter from my general practitioner so that I could go to a physio and go on my merry ways, with a few easy exercises that would fix it once and for all.</p>
<p>Except that’s not how it went. The visit to the doctor spawned a few radiography sessions, with X-rays and MRIs, and instead of a simple referral to a physio, I was referred to a neurosurgeon. Turns out, the back issue isn’t just bad posture and a lack of working out. Instead, I have spondylolysis and spondylolisthesis, which could have an even more significant decrease in my quality of life at some point.</p>
<p>Aside from that, in these last two weeks of the year, I got a cold that just wouldn’t go away, with a cough that I couldn’t manage at all. This cough would make my throat spasm uncontrollably, to the point of gagging and throwing up. A visit to the doctor (after two weeks of resisting it — I know, I know) brought up the hypothesis that my asthma is back — the last time was when I was 7, I think — and I’m going to have to monitor it and see how it goes.</p>
<p>And then, to top it all off — a trip to the dentist confirmed that my implant site (of my left bottom molar) has significant bone loss, and necessitates more visits to the specialist. I foresee this to be the budget killer in 2023.</p>
<p><strong>Work</strong>: It’s not hyperbole to say that I over-indexed on work this year, and ended up making everybody else’s priorities my worry.</p>
<p>My work day generally starts around 8:30am, and on some days they end at 11pm. This is, as anyone would know, completely unsustainable. A lot of the late night meetings are because of the leadership program I’m in, and it definitely doesn’t feel like the outputs and outcomes match the amount of effort and time I put into it. I’m still trying to figure out how to properly balance this without me accelerating the burnout that I can see coming.</p>
<p>I also worked too many weekends, and even started dreaming about doing work — as in, Figma is open and I’m staring at a screen in my dream. The worst thing about this is that I’ll wake up and the work isn’t magically actually done.</p>
<p>There was also a lot of angst and anger around some things at work, and these are things out of my direct control. I got extremely reactive to things happening, and then that makes me even more annoyed and angry because theoretically I know that I am the only thing I can control, and I’m definitely not doing that.</p>
<p>Even in this last week of the year, while the office is closed down, I’m still logging hours and having to review work, send out emails, and still generally not being able to fully unplug. This is probably going to be extremely detrimental as I head back in next week, unrested, and I’m not looking forward to it.</p>
<p><strong>Reading</strong>: Did I reach my reading challenge? Yes. Did I leave it til the last possible weeks to cram half of it in, despite the goal being halved from last year? Also yes.</p>
<p>I seriously contemplated that I should aim for 90 books in 2023, since I was going to cram with whatever I target.</p>
<p>My friends do not think it’s funny.</p>
<p><strong>Writing</strong>: It’s been an abysmal year, both writing on this blog, and also writing fiction in general. Of all the habits and priorities, I have definitely let this slide the most. I’m hopeful that 2023 will allow me the time and grace to pick this back up again in a more consistent fashion.</p>
<p>I also want to write more long-form content, both around my craft specialties (UX and product design, leadership amongst others), as well as more helpful and actionable content for my non-work interests, like productivity and minimalism.</p>
<p><strong>Hobbies and skills</strong>: Sadly to say, I didn’t pick up anything new in 2022.</p>
<p>I did continue my habits of daily meditating and daily journaling, and continued with playing poker, and actually downloading apps for Sudoku and Chinese chess towards the later part of the year.</p>
<p>Other than that, I abandoned learning/refreshing my Javascript skills pretty early.</p>
<h2 id="themes-from-my-gratitude-journal">Themes from my gratitude journal:</h2>
<ul>
<li>Great food with great friends</li>
<li>Opportunities to try things</li>
<li>Having time to rest / weekends / days off</li>
<li>Agency to do what I want, to some degree</li>
<li>Ability to do hard work</li>
<li>My nephews expressing their affections / witnessing my nephews playing with dogs</li>
<li>Projects ending</li>
</ul>
<p>I’ve also neglected this gratitude journal and left it blank more often than not. That’s something I really want to improve on.</p>
<h2 id="what-i-want-to-do-next-year">What I want to do next year:</h2>
<p>I’m just going to list things down, and maybe in a year’s time we’ll see how accountable I’ve held myself with these:</p>
<ul>
<li>Expand my music listening so I’m not listening to the same 20 songs all year round</li>
<li>Take learning programming more seriously
<ul>
<li>Change my tech stack for my portfolio and blog — they’re running on WordPress now, which is too chunky for what I want it to do. I want to see if I can run it off Notion as a database, but my knowledge and expertise isn’t at a level where I can do that easily</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Take my MBA dream more seriously and see if it’s worth it + prepare for it if it is</li>
<li>Make more mentor relationships</li>
<li>Learn driving?</li>
<li>Finally learn guitar for real?</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>As always, I hope the next 364 days ahead are safe and happy for everyone.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Being frugal</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/being-frugal/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2022 20:27:33 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/being-frugal/</guid>
      <description>I’m a pretty frugal person.
I don’t think I’m cheap (though maybe some people might think otherwise?) but there are some things that I know I don’t want to spend money than necessary on. It’s not about depriving myself, or getting the last cent shaved off, or trying to be a bargain hunter.
(Here’s an interlude to acknowledge that I’m definitely speaking from a place of privilege, to be even able to have choices to be frugal.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’m a pretty frugal person.</p>
<p>I don’t <em>think</em> I’m cheap (though maybe some people might think otherwise?) but there are some things that I know I don’t want to spend money than necessary on. It’s not about depriving myself, or getting the last cent shaved off, or trying to be a bargain hunter.</p>
<p>(Here’s an interlude to acknowledge that I’m definitely speaking from a place of privilege, to be even able to <em>have</em> choices to be frugal. It’s been a long, long time since I’ve had that kind of financial anxiety that only living paycheck to paycheck can gather, and now I can spend money without worrying too much.)</p>
<p>There are a few reasons why my spending habits are this way:</p>
<ol>
<li>I like being intentional with what I’m spending my money on, since there are other things I would rather spend my money on</li>
<li>Having options with my money — bulking up my emergency savings, putting aside money for bigger ticket purchases like a new device or a vacation, or even just taking advantage of a bear market — brings me a sense of security</li>
<li>I have a percentage in mind when it comes to my savings rate (and yes, this comes into the whole Financial Independence (and maybe Retire Early) thing, but the jury is still out on the latter)</li>
</ol>
<p>And yet, in the past month, I found myself with a huge money decision to make: whether or not to sign up with a personal trainer so that I can really dial my fitness levels in. This is on top of the physiotherapy sessions I go to, because of my back betraying my body in general.</p>
<p>It’s not an insignificant sum of money: personal training would take up a huge percentage of my monthly expenses, and would set me back a bit of my target “retirement” age. It’s also a pretty huge cost upfront.</p>
<p>I’m doing it, though. As I’ve so rapidly found in the past couple of years, my health is worth more than the money I can afford to throw at it.</p>
<p>Believe me, it took a couple of days for me to come to this decision and reframe my position on it.</p>
<p>My initial thoughts: no way, I can just go to my cheap gym on my own, this is way too much, this is going to affect my spending by a whole lot.</p>
<p>Eventually, the combination of knowing exactly what my body fat percentage is right now (hint: way, way worse than I had always estimated) as well as wanting a professional to spot my form and fixing it where it’s hurting me won out.</p>
<p>Now, excuse me while I buy some gym shoes, because my Metcon 5s are literally breaking apart at the seams.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reframe, rethink</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/reframe/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 20:28:59 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/reframe/</guid>
      <description>(Inspired by Brianna Wiest’s 101 Essays That Will Change The Way You Think)
You’re still functional — physically, at least. You can walk and you can sit, and you can shrug off the pain when it gets a little too much. You hold on to your values, even when it’s easier to just go with the path of least resistance. You can be proud of who you are. Work is tough, and some days it’s annoying, but so many people would love to be doing what you do.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>(Inspired by Brianna Wiest’s 101 Essays That Will Change The Way You Think)</p>
<ol>
<li>You’re still functional — physically, at least. You can walk and you can sit, and you can shrug off the pain when it gets a little too much.</li>
<li>You hold on to your values, even when it’s easier to just go with the path of least resistance. You can be proud of who you are.</li>
<li>Work is tough, and some days it’s annoying, but so many people would love to be doing what you do.</li>
<li>You earn enough to live comfortably, to go where you want and eat what you desire; enough to live on your own terms.</li>
<li>You’re allowed to think and ponder about what <em>living on your own terms</em> mean, and know that even though life isn’t ideal or where you’d thought it would be, it’s still a journey to get to where you envision it to be.</li>
<li>You have the weekend to decompress, even if decompressing means losing track of time as you doom-scroll through Reddit.</li>
<li>You just spent a good hour preparing for your lunches in the week ahead, and that is going to help with keeping track of actually eating lunch, which is something that has been a miss for so much of the last two years.</li>
<li>You have comfort shows and movies that you can dive back into; an embrace into a familiarity that makes your brain feel happy.</li>
<li>You have amazing friends. Quality &gt; quantity, especially in this case.</li>
<li>You think about all the different ways to get better, and to be better. You might fail and stumble along the way, but you’re still trying. You’re figuring it out. You’re still here.</li>
</ol>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>a little (Little Mix) mix</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/little-mix/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2022 14:43:15 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/little-mix/</guid>
      <description>I went through the entire year between 2016 – 2017 just solely listening to Little Mix, and not much of anything else. Before that, I was an iNdIe™ person (think Bon Iver, Sufjan Stevens, Blind Pilot, Frightened Rabbit, etc) and a show tunes (jazz hands) kind of person.
So, not so much Top 40.
I wish I could remember how I got into listening to Little Mix, but it was definitely right around when Shout Out To My Ex came out (along with the Glory Days album).</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I went through the entire year between 2016 – 2017 <em>just</em> solely listening to Little Mix, and not much of anything else. Before that, I was an iNdIe™ person (think Bon Iver, Sufjan Stevens, Blind Pilot, Frightened Rabbit, etc) and a show tunes (<em>jazz hands</em>) kind of person.</p>
<p>So, not so much Top 40.</p>
<p>I wish I could remember <em>how</em> I got into listening to Little Mix, but it was definitely right around when Shout Out To My Ex came out (along with the Glory Days album). I listened to that album, and then suddenly I’m listening to all of the previous albums and watching their journey through The X Factor.</p>
<p>These girls are such amazing vocalists and performers – sometimes they’re even better live (or ‘live’, as in the case of festival performances with backing tracks) and a cappella, which is insane considering that the produced and recorded tracks are just non-stop pop and fun.</p>
<p>Their tour performances, too, are <em>phenomenal</em>. You can tell how much fun they have on stage, and of performing with each other, as well as the sisterhood and love they have for each other. I had the privilege and pleasure to watch them on <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/B4V1rQVHYaO/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >LM5: The Tour</a>, on Halloween 2019 – right before the pandemic. For a quick minute, I was tempted to fly to London for a couple of days to watch them on their last tour, but ultimately the fiscal side of me won out.</p>
<p>In celebration of them performing their last show (for now) as they embark on their personal careers in this hiatus from the group, I’m just pulling together some videos that have wow-ed me over the years. I’m going to miss them as a unit, but I’m so excited to see how each of them are going to excel on their own too, while always having a home to go back to.</p>
<h2 id="my-favorite-performances">My favorite performances</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=j3GN_ZsgjOA"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >Confetti (Acoustic)</a> – The harmonies? The belting? The fact that they were doing this in the face of losing a member, and having to round out their voices to create a still-full sound? Holy shit.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Jtf4tuLn6ug"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >Secret Love Song Pt. II</a> – Listen, I will go to battle for any performance of this song. It’s rallied so much LGBTQ+ support, and genuinely propelled the girls to properly become allies to the community, and for that I will always love it</li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KroQLUHVqk8"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >Touch (Acoustic)</a> – The original pop version was a banger, and was my “first” single that I’d experienced from them. The way the acoustic version was arranged to showcase all of their voices? Just magic.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=J6RjeJsT0nc"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >How You Doin’?</a> – Not my favorite song on the album, but the live performances of this song always hype me up.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OyhgIuNoWvo"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >Dance With Somebody (cover)</a> – They’ve done plenty of covers through the years, but I’ve always really enjoyed this one.</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meditating (and how I kind of suck at it, but that&#39;s the whole point)</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/meditating/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2022 14:43:15 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/meditating/</guid>
      <description>My mind is not a quiet place.
It’s full of thoughts; rooted in anxiety, in worry, over things I can’t control and things I can. More often than not, random lyrics and quotes are also bouncing in the ol’ noggin, in specific cadences and lilts as they were spoken in the medium I watched them in.
Late in 2019, I decided to give meditating a spin. I’ve heard the benefits of meditation many, many years ago, but have always dismissed it as a woo-woo new-age alt-medicine (is that enough hyphens yet?</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My mind is not a quiet place.</p>
<p>It’s full of thoughts; rooted in anxiety, in worry, over things I can’t control and things I can. More often than not, random lyrics and quotes are also bouncing in the ol’ noggin, in specific cadences and lilts as they were spoken in the medium I watched them in.</p>
<p>Late in 2019, I decided to give meditating a spin. I’ve heard the benefits of meditation many, many years ago, but have always dismissed it as a woo-woo new-age alt-medicine (is that enough hyphens yet?) practice. Yet, it has been shown that there are actual benefits to doing it: improving focus, decreasing anxiety, reducing stress, amongst others.</p>
<p>So, I did what I knew best: I read books<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, and used All The Apps<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>. I fumbled and wondered what I was doing wrong, and tried different things to see if this time, it’ll be the one that sticks.</p>
<h2 id="how-it-started">How it started</h2>
<p>I began with guided meditations.</p>
<p>Sometimes I fell back asleep if I did it as part of my waking up routine, which is bad because I would have turned my alarm off by that point. I’ve been lucky that I haven’t overslept by too much!</p>
<p>Meditating at night, too, helps me fall right asleep (except for recordings that have long pauses in between voices, in which case I would be on the precipice of sleep before getting jerked awake because of the unexpected voice in the dark). Now, if my aim was meditating for deep sleep, then this is a good outcome.</p>
<p>My priority was to build my focus and attention through mindfulness though, so the next thing I tried was using just the timer. I breathe in for four seconds, hold for four, and breathe out in – you guessed it – four seconds.</p>
<h2 id="how-its-going-badly-right">How it’s going (badly, right?)</h2>
<p>Meditation seems simple, but it’s not easy.</p>
<p>Here’s the thing that I’ve learned: Like sets of exercise for your body for your body, each ‘loss of focus  awareness  focus’ rep is your brain working out. That goes for every time you catch yourself drifting away, and bring yourself back to the present.</p>
<p>Now, I’m by no means an expert obviously, since I’m still fumbling. Even with 376 consecutive days under my belt, every morning still feels like a really tough 10 – 15 minutes. I find myself trying to remember more of my dreams that are slowly fading away, the things I need to put on my things-to-do list, or the next steps I need to take once the session is over.</p>
<p>I’m not gonna lie, I’ve been frustrated because I find myself getting distracted with tangential thoughts and having to pull myself back into focus. Sometimes the latter doesn’t happen, and I catch myself in the middle of a daydream as the ending bell sounds its gong.</p>
<h2 id="how-to-meditate-if-you-want-to">How to meditate, if you want to</h2>
<ol>
<li>Decide if you want to try it guided or unguided – I really like Insight Timer for both, especially for the latter, but Headspace is pretty cool for guided practice, with different lengths that you can choose from</li>
<li>Choose when you want to meditate, and make that a habit. I do it in the morning when I wake up, but that means I have to fit that in my morning schedule. If that doesn’t work for you, at night works as well</li>
<li>Close your eyes, and while they are close, lower your gaze (I learned this in Jay Shetty’s book, Think Like A Monk)</li>
<li>Start with short sessions, and build incrementally</li>
<li>You’re not doing it <em>wrong</em>, because there isn’t a right or wrong way</li>
</ol>
<p>Here’s to building your brain muscle!</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Mindfulness in Plain English, 10% Happier by Dan Harris, Conscious by Annaka Harris, Mindfulness: A Practical Guide to Awakening by Joseph Goldstein, Think Like A Monk by Jay Shetty&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Insight Timer, Calm, Headspace, and most recently, the Fitbit app&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Back Situation™</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/spondy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2022 14:44:56 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/spondy/</guid>
      <description>Over the course of the last week and a half, while I’ve gotten my official diagnosis of what makes up my back issues, one phrase stood out from at least four different health care professionals:
“You’re so young.”
Am I, though?
spondylos “spine” or “vertebra”
lysis “defect”
–listhesis “slipping, sliding or movement”
From the x-rays and the MRI scan, the doctors are able to pinpoint the actual issues I have. Specifically for my lower back pain, the main culprits are:</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Over the course of the last week and a half, while I’ve gotten my official diagnosis of what makes up my back issues, one phrase stood out from at least four different health care professionals:</p>
<p><em>“You’re so young.”</em></p>
<p>Am I, though?</p>
<h3 id="spondylos"><em>spondylos</em></h3>
<p>“spine” or “vertebra”</p>
<h3 id="lysis"><em>lysis</em></h3>
<p>“defect”</p>
<h3 id="listhesis"><em>–listhesis</em></h3>
<p>“slipping, sliding or movement”</p>
<p>From the x-rays and the MRI scan, the doctors are able to pinpoint the actual issues I have. Specifically for my lower back pain, the main culprits are:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Disc desiccation</strong> between my L1 and S1 vertebrae, which means that the disc is dehydrated and has lost all the fluid. It’s also “protruding”, and has a tear where it is connecting both vertebrae;</li>
<li><strong>Foraminal stenosis</strong>, which means there is a narrowing of the cervical disc space</li>
<li><strong>Spondylolysis</strong>, with fractures through the pars bones (which are the soft little spiky bones on your spine), and;</li>
<li><strong>Spondylolisthesis</strong>, which is a mouthful, but means that the vertebra has slipped forward, out of place from the rest of the spine</li>
</ul>
<p>I’m still getting used to spelling these — all I know is that there’s an ‘lol’ in both spondy words.</p>
<p>I’ve had a week or so to sit with this diagnosis, and the neurosurgeon’s recommendation is to get back surgery done so that it doesn’t worsen.</p>
<p>I’ll know when it gets worse, because I’ll lose bladder and bowel function, so that’s <em>real</em> comforting.</p>
<p>But back surgery doesn’t come with zero risks: it’s not a guarantee that it’ll improve, and there is always a chance that something else might happen and the nerves might get nicked even more.</p>
<p>There’s also the other matter of how young I am, apparently. I can see two schools of thought here:</p>
<ol>
<li>I don’t need surgery at this point, because I can build up my core (for real for real this time) and the muscles will protect the spine from deteriorating — but I probably <em>will</em> have to do the surgery anyway when I’m older, even if I’ve built up the strongest core in the world</li>
<li>I need surgery right now, because I’m young and can withstand the recovery period than if I do it when I’m much older — but I might not fully recover; there might be complications; the recovery period is actually pretty long right now anyway (a year was what I have heard), and what if the nails fail in the next few decades?</li>
</ol>
<p>There’s still a lot of other things to think about too, beyond the actual medical aspect, like the economics of it. It’s actually cheaper to get the surgery because I’m covered by insurance, while physio sessions are capped at $750 a year, and — I’m not even kidding — I’ll be able to get a grand total of 3.75 sessions covered.</p>
<p>My hope is that I’ll be able to get some quality of life with no aching and pain when I do… pretty much anything at all, but especially when I arch my back. A stretch goal (haha stretch) would be getting back to lifting and squatting with no pain and no risk of anything cracking further.</p>
<p>Ultimately, right now I’m still in the information-gathering stage. I’ll probably suck it up and pay massively out-of-pocket for the physio sessions, and get second+ opinions on whether surgery is needed.</p>
<p>Until then, I’m just going to be paranoid every time I get a twinge or numbness in my butt or thighs, because that’s when I know this is progressing.</p>
<h2 id="frequently-asked-questions">Frequently Asked Questions</h2>
<p><em>Updated 11 May, 2022</em>, because I’ve been getting the same responses and questions, and thought it’ll make sense to document the responses to everyone’s concerns</p>
<p><strong>Q:</strong> How? What did you do?</p>
<p><strong>A:</strong> I truly do not know, and neither do the doctors and physio. The best assumption is because I naturally have hyper-extended joints, this has been happening through years of living. It could be from working out as well, but I have my own doubts about it as I’m not lifting super heavy, and my form is good (and vetted by the physio!).</p>
<p><strong>Q:</strong> How does it feel?</p>
<p><strong>A</strong>: Thankfully, I’m not in constant pain. Instead, it’s a dull ache that I have taken as my baseline for the past three years. I mostly feel it when I stay in one position for too long. The level of achiness, from most annoying to least: laying down on my stomach, walking down stairs, sitting, standing, laying down on my back, laying down on my back with my knees tucked to my chest.</p>
<p>I also absolutely cannot jump or do any sort of impact activity, without feeling like something is actually shattering within me</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Fun</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/how-to-fun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Apr 2022 14:48:04 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/how-to-fun/</guid>
      <description>I’m turning 33 in 3 days, and for a couple of days, I was contemplating if I wanted to do that thing where I try to come up with 33 life lessons and pithy quotables. Maybe I’ll still do it next week, but this week I wanted to talk about something I’ve been trying to do these days.
I’ve been listening to a lot of podcasts on the Pushkin network, like Cautionary Tales, Bad Women; right now I want to think a little more about a specific episode on The Happiness Lab: How to have fun.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’m turning 33 in 3 days, and for a couple of days, I was contemplating if I wanted to do that thing where I try to come up with 33 <del>life lessons</del> and pithy quotables. Maybe I’ll still do it next week, but this week I wanted to talk about something I’ve been trying to do these days.</p>
<p>I’ve been listening to a lot of podcasts on the Pushkin network, like Cautionary Tales, Bad Women; right now I want to think a little more about a specific episode on <a href="https://www.happinesslab.fm/season-3/episode-7-laurie-gets-a-fun-tervention-part-one"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >The Happiness Lab: How to have fun.</a></p>
<p>I don’t know when or how it started, but I have always felt like I’m the most boring person in the room. It’s probably a combination of: 1) not doing things literally, 2) not being appreciative of what I do, and 3) the ‘grass is always greener’ fallacy.</p>
<p>And then it’s sometimes because my idea of fun is trying to catalogue everything I own, on a Notion database that I’m still finding tips and tricks on using.</p>
<p>Or trying to rebuild this blog and my portfolio, so that it’s lightweight, accessible, <em>and</em> easy to maintain outside of the WordPress setup I have them on right now.</p>
<p>Or binging <em>Selling Sunset</em>’s latest season, because that is something seriously mindless that I found myself absorbed in this past weekend.</p>
<hr>
<p>Anyway, back to the point: How can I have (more) fun? What can I do?</p>
<p>I feel like a hypocrite sometimes because I’m always like, “I love to learn and having new experiences!”, but then the weekend rolls about and I’m more content sitting in front of my screen (that I do for 16 hours a day on weekdays) or laying in my bed (that I do for the rest of my hours in the day).</p>
<p>I just got the book though, so I’m going to do my own idea of fun (reading) and seeing how I can come up with a game plan (which is also fun). Let’s see what I come up with, and how I might put it in action</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What&#39;s in a name?</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/design-title/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Mar 2022 13:00:28 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/design-title/</guid>
      <description>Should I be looking for a job with a specific title?
Are there roles I should avoid?
And what do I do when the job description says I have to do everything?
This topic actually comes up quite a lot with people who have booked sessions with me on ADPList, and entering the job market in the first few years of their career in this field.
The point of confusion seems to be around labelling, which is ironic given the work we would do with content, information architecture, and taxonomy.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Should I be looking for a job with a specific title?</p>
<p>Are there roles I should avoid?</p>
<p>And what do I do when the job description says I have to do everything?</p>
<hr>
<p>This topic actually comes up quite a lot with people who have booked sessions with me on ADPList, and entering the job market in the first few years of their career in this field.</p>
<p>The point of confusion seems to be around labelling, which is ironic given the work we would do with content, information architecture, and taxonomy.</p>
<h2 id="the-case-against-uiux">The case against &ldquo;UI/UX&rdquo;</h2>
<p>I’ve called myself, at one point through my journey from mid-weight to principal designer, these titles: Experience Designer, UX Designer, Product Designer, Interaction Designer, Service Designer, Information Architect, CX Consultant…</p>
<p>But there is something I would never call myself, and that is: a UX/UI designer.</p>
<p>(And, spoiler: it isn’t because I don’t do UI!)</p>
<p>There are two different arguments here:</p>
<h3 id="1-user-interface-design-is-a-sub-set-of-skills-that-make-up-user-experience-design">1) User interface design is a sub-set of skills that make up user experience design</h3>
<p>You won&rsquo;t call someone a &ldquo;Menu Developer/Cook Chef&rdquo; in the same breath, would you? Calling a designer a &ldquo;UI/UX Designer&rdquo; is similar to that comparison, as you cannot separate the interface from the experience, nor the experience from how it works when it looks a certain way.</p>
<p>There is an inherent connection between both skills: the design and interactivity of the interface is a key aspect to the general user experience.</p>
<p>Without the visual and interactive elements of the design, it becomes much more difficult to sell the problem-solving perspective of the structure and experience.</p>
<p>There is that old analogy about UX being the blueprint of a house, while the UI is the exterior and interior design of the property. Without the other, one cannot call itself a complete house.</p>
<h3 id="2-visual-design-skills-are-very-different-in-application-to-interaction-design-skills">2) Visual design skills are very different in application to interaction design skills</h3>
<p>This distinction goes back to the histories of both careers &ndash; from library sciences that grew into information architecture and the structuring of content through human-computer interaction, and GUI design that came as an evolution of computers, then the internet.</p>
<p>Not to mention the graphic designers who paved the way across different media!</p>
<p>Both sets of skills are integral to the success of the product that you’re building, and the value you’re bringing across to the cross-functional team you’re in.</p>
<p>(On a side note, and possibly for another article: I have also often seen designers boxing themselves in “the way the brain is wired”, i.e. a visual designer is seen as a more creative individual, while a UX designer is more structured and analytical.</p>
<p>Sometimes, it is very egregious to read definitions in job descriptions, and even in articles laying out the differences in skills and scope of UX and UI &ndash; I&rsquo;ve hypothesized they&rsquo;re written by UX-leaning folks &ndash; that basically boil down to, &ldquo;a UX designer is a critical thinker and a problem solver&rdquo;, and a UI designer, uh, &ldquo;can choose typography and colors&rdquo;.)</p>
<hr>
<h3 id="the-result-blurred-lines">The result? Blurred lines.</h3>
<p>The lines blur with each given individual designer, their shape and their stack. One designer can be comfortable hands-on with all the tasks, but they also need to learn how to prioritize: first based on user and business value, then based on what is needed at the point of time. Circling around a content model might not make as big an impact as a working prototype for a set of stakeholders, but might be the motherlode for another.</p>
<p>As a design leader, understanding the scope of what needs to be delivered often starts with identifying the team’s strengths, what they can deliver in a reasonable time, and balancing the deep specialization each designer can bring holistically.</p>
<p>Companies often want that fabled unicorn who can do it all, but I’m reminded of a quote:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You can do anything, but you can’t do everything.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Not at the same time, anyway!</p>
<p>At the end of the day, great experiences are delivered when you have a good mix of both types of skills.</p>
<p>Even if you’re a designer who can straddle across the skills and deliverables (and on a good day, I feel like I can), you still need checks and balances to make sure that the outcomes are balanced.</p>
<p>That means collaborating with your product manager to understand the metrics in which the deliverable will be measured on, or discussing with the engineer who’s feeling a deep sense of despair as you demo the impossible interaction from Figma.</p>
<p>(Just kidding — please don’t do that! We can talk more about desirability, feasibility and viability at another time, though.)</p>
<h2 id="making-an-impact">Making an impact</h2>
<p>Beyond the actual business metrics, and beyond titles, what we do as practitioners impacts to a great degree what people experience in their lives. It doesn’t start and end with &ldquo;I made this app look really nice,&rdquo; or even “translating business requirements from my product owner&quot;.</p>
<p>Worse still: “My stakeholder wants to do this so I guess we’ll do this”.</p>
<p>Instead, there’s a lot for us to be intentional about: the language we use, the people we include, and the (hopefully positive) impact we make on their lives.</p>
<p>Then there are questions like, how do we make sure that accessibility is a foundation and not just an afterthought, a checklist of items only for it to get a passing rate, or a plugin on Figma to make sure colors are contrasted enough? How do we make sure that we are not unintentionally excluding people by calling them “edge-cases”?</p>
<p>And even beyond the fabled “user” — what about our own employees? What about the newcomer who’s joining the team, and wants to hit the ground running but still with ample support? Or the hiring partner who needs to understand exactly what skills to screen for when they find someone? (Ah, full circle on this piece.)</p>
<hr>
<p>Design lives beyond roles and nomenclature. Leading by design and curiosity, and the North Star of creating meaningful impact is the intersection I believe we can make the most of our skills and time on, and honestly? That goes beyond the title I call myself.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>#IAmRemarkable</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/iamremarkable/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2022 14:49:09 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/iamremarkable/</guid>
      <description>Two weeks ago, I had the pleasure of attending an #IAmRemarkable session hosted by Akua Nyame-Mensah. The hour and a half flew past like it was nothing, and filled me with the hope that one day, too, I will not be filled with dread when it comes to talking about my own achievements.
(Even typing that! “My own achievements”…)
Why I attended this More than just for personal growth though, I definitely want the ladies and other marginalized members of my team to be able to have the confidence and competence to talk about what they have done and achieved.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Two weeks ago, I had the pleasure of attending an <a href="https://iamremarkable.withgoogle.com/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >#IAmRemarkable</a> session hosted by <a href="https://www.akuanm.com/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >Akua Nyame-Mensah</a>. The hour and a half flew past like it was nothing, and filled me with the hope that one day, too, I will not be filled with dread when it comes to talking about my own achievements.</p>
<p>(Even typing that! “My own achievements”…)</p>
<h2 id="why-i-attended-this">Why I attended this</h2>
<p>More than just for personal growth though, I definitely want the ladies and other marginalized members of my team to be able to have the confidence and competence to talk about what they have done and achieved.</p>
<p>I’ve never been someone who likes talking about myself, and I used to prefer sticking to the background and “doing the work” — just like a good little worker should, I thought. It served me well for a few years early in my career, because I had bosses who noticed the good work done, and I was rewarded appropriately.</p>
<p>When I moved to a consultancy, that changed. It was a culture shock in that area, being given the agency to chart your own career and having that be the norm. It wasn’t the greatest of workplaces though, and there were a lot of factors going into an appraisal beyond “work” done, like utilization hours… and how well you knew your leaders.</p>
<p>Now, though, where I work? There has been a giant shift to ‘owning’ your career, and the biggest change is having to put your own promotion package together and deciding when you’re ready to take the leap, instead of passively waiting for your manager to tell you that you’re ready. I went through that whole process earlier this year, and it was nerve-wracking and filled me up with so much imposter syndrome.</p>
<h2 id="moving-from-criticizing-to-self-love">Moving from criticizing to self-love</h2>
<p>There was definitely a lot of emphasis on shifting our mindsets, and moving yourself from one end of this spectrum to the other:</p>
<p>Criticizing → Constructive criticism → Self promotion → Self-love</p>
<h2 id="iamremarkable-because">#IAmRemarkable, because:</h2>
<p>The workshop also included some time for us to think about our own #IAmRemarkable statements, both writing them down and speaking out loud (or typing it in the chat).</p>
<p>I’m not gonna lie, I had to google for some inspiration because I needed a starting point, but here are my statements just in case I come up in your search, and you needed something to guide you too</p>
<ul>
<li>#IAmRemarkable, because I am always looking out for my team’s well-being</li>
<li>#IAmRemarkable, because I always want to do better and <em>be</em> better</li>
<li>#IAmRemarkable, because I am resilient through life changes and revelations</li>
<li>#IAmRemarkable, because I pay attention to the small details</li>
<li>#IAmRemarkable, because I try to live through my <a href="/authentic-life"  >core values</a> and using them to guide my decisions</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2021: Year in Review</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/2021-year-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 15:57:49 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/2021-year-in-review/</guid>
      <description>I like having a chill and quiet last day of the year, and I was ready to spend the whole of this last day of the year writing this, just as I had done last year.
Instead, my laptop wouldn’t start up when I woke up yesterday morning — seemed emblematic of 2021’s vibes — and I spent half the day going to a couple of repair shops, receiving the bad news about a corroded motherboard, balking at the price for repair, trying to make the call on whether I should just buy a new MacBook Air/Pro and let this 2017 laptop’s value after amortization be higher than I anticipated…</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I like having a chill and quiet last day of the year, and I was ready to spend the whole of this last day of the year writing this, just as I had done <a href="/2020-year-in-review"  >last year</a>.</p>
<p>Instead, my laptop wouldn’t start up when I woke up yesterday morning — seemed emblematic of 2021’s vibes — and I spent half the day going to a couple of repair shops, receiving the bad news about a corroded motherboard, balking at the price for repair, trying to make the call on whether I should just buy a new MacBook Air/Pro and let this 2017 laptop’s value after amortization be higher than I anticipated…</p>
<p>Eventually I settled on spending the repair money, because I feel like I’ll be able to stretch the lifespan out a little more and get a better value over time. Plus, I’ll be able to comfortably wait for the <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/guide/2022-macbook-air/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >M2 MacBook Air</a> when it comes out too.</p>
<p>But yes. That’s 2021 in a nutshell, I think: something happens and I react, and I push all previously-laid plans aside. Including having to write this post in the new year instead!</p>
<h2 id="what-went-well">What went well:</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Money:</strong> Before the laptop fiasco, I was locking in an 70% savings rate. This is going to be my third full year of pursuing FIRE (or at least the FI part of things), and I’m well on track, so that makes me happy. With the repair costs hastily calculated in, I’m down a couple of percents, but all in all it’s still below my budgeted expenses of the year.</li>
<li><strong>Work</strong>: I had so much to talk about during my impact discussion, which was further bolstered by my colleagues’ really kind feedback and words for my improvement. There was also the matter of getting into the Next Generation Leadership Team (<a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/CXi6VawgxuO/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >second slide in this post!</a>) when I didn’t think I would.</li>
<li><strong>Writing:</strong> This is threefold — I wrote a post here every week for a year (minus the weird month last month that I paused), wrote 2 journal entries every day (one for a more regular recap, and another with Day One’s daily prompts), and also wrote a few pieces of fic which I’m proud of, because I’d never done that for my ride-or-die fandom despite being in it for nearly a decade now.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="what-couldve-gone-better">What could’ve gone better:</h2>
<ul>
<li>Everything about my <strong>health</strong>, including:
<ul>
<li>My eating habits — timing, quantity, and quality;</li>
<li>Working out — I won’t blame it on the vaccines, but I turned “no strenuous activity for 2 weeks” into much longer;</li>
<li>Hitting my daily step count — some time around June I said fuck it to 10k a day, scaled it down to 5k, <em>and</em> then had trouble hitting those</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Reading</strong>: <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/user_challenges/24940419"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >I did it.</a> I did 60 books. I’m not proud of it, because I speed-read the fuck out of those last 15 books and let’s just say I do <em>not</em> want to do it again, so this year? This year I’m going to slow down, and read just “enough”.</li>
<li><strong>Skills:</strong> Did not learn a new language. Or calligraphy. Picked up a couple of Thai swear words though, does that count?</li>
<li><strong>Mentality</strong>: I heard it over and over again from my colleagues and friends — stop being so hard on yourself.</li>
<li><strong>Money:</strong> Even though I’d talked about all the good stuff with money in the previous section, one thing did make me feel slightly embarrassed: in-app purchases for chips in my poker games. It’s illegal in Singapore to gamble online, so I was just frivolously spending real money in exchange for fake money.Luckily (and this is a huge luckily), the support team accidentally unlinked my account and I can’t access that anymore, which made my refund requests to Apple legitimate when I did it after 2 weeks of no response from said support team.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="other-stuff">Other stuff:</h2>
<ul>
<li>I met some pretty cool people this year, and I’m thankful to have crossed paths with them and looking forward to forging even tighter friendships going forward!</li>
<li>2021’s major learning-in-a-structured-manner was the <a href="/learning-harder"  >d.MBA</a>, and I’m itching to apply that knowledge to actual work.</li>
<li>2021 was also my second year of meditating every morning</li>
<li>Got extremely into poker near the end of October — thanks to Maria Konnikova’s <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/49814228-the-biggest-bluff"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" ><em>The Biggest Bluff</em></a> — and while I’ve just been playing it online (with fake stakes), I think I might consider taking a vacation somewhere and playing some super low stakes games in person.</li>
<li>Getting to be <a href="https://adplist.org/mentors/jalyn-cai"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >a mentor on ADPList</a> had been really fulfilling, though really time-consuming! Alas, I think I’m no longer getting any traffic from the actual directory, and haven’t been getting any new bookings since… I wanna say November? So there’s that.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="themes-from-my-gratitude-journal">Themes from my gratitude journal:</h2>
<ul>
<li>My nephews being themselves</li>
<li>Being allowed [space / time ] to try/do [thing]</li>
<li>WEEKENDS</li>
<li>Working with good people</li>
<li>Good food with good people</li>
</ul>
<p>I’ve been joking that we should be very quiet about 2022 and not startle it, and the first day of the year is already rainy and dreary, so… I hope the next 364 days ahead are safe and happy for everyone</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In/out of control</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/control/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Oct 2021 15:59:46 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/control/</guid>
      <description>My mentor asked me a simple question when I was catching up with her: What’s in your control, and what’s not?
—
I’ve touched on this topic before, while talking about stoicism and what we can control. That was February of this year, which seems both like a short time and a lifetime ago. I had a pretty pithy line to summarize then:
Things happen, and the only thing we can control is how we respond to them.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My mentor asked me a simple question when I was catching up with her: What’s in your control, and what’s not?</p>
<p>—</p>
<p>I’ve touched on this topic before, while talking about <a href="/control"  >stoicism and what we can control</a>. That was February of this year, which seems both like a short time and a lifetime ago. I had a pretty pithy line to summarize then:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Things happen, and the only thing we can control is how we respond to them.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Well, turns out, in life, things do happen.</p>
<p>With work, what is it that I can control? What is it that I struggle with accepting that I can’t control?</p>
<h3 id="i-cant-control">I can’t control:</h3>
<ul>
<li>The (types of) clients the team engages with</li>
<li>Other people’s actions, reactions, and decisions</li>
<li>Whether people would participate in one thing, and not another</li>
<li>How others perceive me</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="what-i-can">What I can:</h3>
<ul>
<li>How I react to these things happening</li>
<li>How I respond — a slight nuanced difference from the first thing, which is more in the moment</li>
<li>How much action I take, or do not take</li>
<li>The mindfulness I take towards my actions</li>
</ul>
<p>I vaguely alluded to a big shocking announcement at work last week; cue me googling ‘what to do when manager is laid off’ — <a href="/work-ethics"  >the same manager that was understanding of my morals at work</a> — and still trying to process it, about a week and a half after.</p>
<p>I’m still trying to figure out what it means for me (my own job security, my next step forward, building my promotion case) but it’s definitely given me a lot to think about, when I’m not being busy with actual work and calls, and dealing with bad timing (on my part) to try and get a CSR initiative off the ground.</p>
<p>I’m still on that adjusted working week — from Sunday to Thursday — for at least two more weeks, and I don’t think I’m ever going to get used to that, as long as the rest of my team is on Monday to Friday.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Life &amp; poker</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/posts/poker/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Sep 2021 16:04:11 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/posts/poker/</guid>
      <description>This weekend started out with a book – Maria Konnikova’s The Biggest Bluff – before it escalated to me downloading a poker game app, and spending quite some time playing it.
“Casual playing”, that’s what they all say, right?
Kidding aside, I’m not putting “real” money on it, so the only thing I’m really losing is time. I’ve played poker on and off, learned the very basics when I was 15.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This weekend started out with a book – Maria Konnikova’s <em>The Biggest Bluff</em> – before it escalated to me downloading a poker game app, and spending quite some time playing it.</p>
<p>“Casual playing”, that’s what they all say, right?</p>
<p>Kidding aside, I’m not putting “real” money on it, so the only thing I’m really losing is time. I’ve played poker on and off, learned the very basics when I was 15. I’m still a very basic player and I lose more hands than I win them, but I’m pretending that it’s helping my decision making skills somewhat.</p>
<p>I’m glad this is also online because as my friends and colleagues will attest to, I have absolutely no poker face. I also now understand why there are so many poker analogies out there.</p>
<h2 id="sunk-cost-fallacy--fear-of-missing-out">Sunk cost fallacy &amp; fear of missing out</h2>
<p>There are two scenarios here:</p>
<ol>
<li>When I’m the small blind (i.e. a mandatory position where you put in half the minimum bet)</li>
<li>When I don’t have a bet in the game</li>
</ol>
<p>In the small blind position, I’m always thinking to myself — I’ve already ‘invested’ a small amount now, and if my hand is okay (to me this means a combination of at least one royal card and &gt;8 cards), shouldn’t I maximize my chances of getting a good</p>
<p>When I don’t have a bet yet, but if I’m holding good cards (again, to me, something like high pairs), I’d also more likely than not put in a call. Sometimes it works out, other times, people either have higher pairs or the round goes into other combinations that they win with.</p>
<h2 id="opportunity-costs-regrets-and-what-ifs">Opportunity costs, regrets and what ifs</h2>
<p>Now, in some cases I would fold immediately, especially if I don’t have any stakes in the round. Usually this means I have bad cards, like a combination of any cards between 2 – 6, or if I’m at a table with someone I can tell just keeps raising and going all-in (their strategy, I suppose).</p>
<p>Then comes the flop. Then the turn. Then the river.</p>
<p>I realize my cards would have given me a win, usually via a straight, a three of a kind, or a flush.</p>
<p>This realization is followed by me heaving a sigh, especially if I’m down on my chips too. This is made worse if the winning player had bluffed. What if I had forged forward anyway? What if I had put in the minimum bid to “see what happens”?</p>
<h2 id="privilege">Privilege</h2>
<p>More than that, I have been drawing parallels to everybody’s starting points and how, even if you have a great hand, you might not be able to capitalize on it.</p>
<p>Take for example a game where you have a buy in of 500 chips, but another player has 10,000 chips. You can bet and go all in, and the most you’ll get — assuming the other player matches your all in of 500 chips — is 1,000. It’s barely a drop of the ocean for the other player.</p>
<p>I think about equity, and how hard some people have to work to even achieve parity. About how some opportunities have to be passed up sometimes because you aren’t sure of it working out. It’s also not a complete equivalency — equity in real life doesn’t mean that you are “giving up” your privilege(s), not like in a game of poker.</p>
<p>Now I should really go back to reading the book, instead of making empty air bets.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I live an authentic life</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/authentic-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Sep 2021 16:05:39 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/authentic-life/</guid>
      <description>I’ve alluded to my core values in the past (note to self: actually use tags to make navigating posts better!) and since I’ve spent the past two weeks thinking about my values and where they fall on my personal scale of morality, why not talk more about them?
(Also, literally this afternoon as I sat down to write this, my mom lost a needle on the ground and I had to find it without really knowing where it had dropped.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’ve alluded to my core values in the past (note to self: actually use tags to make navigating posts better!) and since I’ve spent the past two weeks thinking about my values and where they fall on my personal scale of morality, why not talk more about them?</p>
<p>(Also, literally this afternoon as I sat down to write this, my mom lost a needle on the ground and I had to find it without really knowing where it had dropped. I suppose it can be quite analogous, heavy-handed as it is, to what I’m articulating right now.)</p>
<hr>
<p>I began this exercise in — I think — 2018, when I started to think about the Big (capital B, note) questions and themes in my life. What do I stand for? How can I live my life in the most meaningful way? Am I being myself at my most authentic?</p>
<p>Not that I wasn’t in a general sense, but in hindsight, I was drifting through life a little.</p>
<hr>
<p>There are different things you value, depending on what life stage you’re at. That means that change is the only constant (groan, right?) and that you might have different priorities at different points in your life.</p>
<p>Yet, I think there are structural tenets that you build your belief system and your decision making around. For me, these are the values I have come up with, after weeks of thinking, more thinking, and running them past my friends.</p>
<h2 id="kindness">Kindness</h2>
<p>Easy, right? Being nice to people? Wroooong. I had a whole post drafted out about how nice is not kind, and kindness isn’t being nice. My friend <a href="https://siew.online/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >Siew</a> recommended <em>Radical Candor</em> to me this past weekend, and the broad strokes of the principles definitely underscore what I define kindness as.</p>
<p>It’s also the value that I try the hardest to “achieve”, I think.</p>
<h2 id="respect">Respect</h2>
<p>Respect, though I need to have a caveat here that if you’re anti-science and anti-vax, I would override my personal respect. I suppose it’s still an umbrella of respect that I’m following here, the one to everyone else in society.</p>
<h2 id="inclusivity">Inclusivity</h2>
<p>Unlocking and opening up gates, trying to achieve different perspectives and viewpoints. Beyond that, actively trying to lift people who might not have the same opportunities or be in the same privileged situation as I am.</p>
<h2 id="growth">Growth</h2>
<p>Just keep learning, just keep learning.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Articulate speaking</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/speech/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 16:10:09 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/speech/</guid>
      <description>During a first session with a mentee (my ADPList profile, if you want to book a session!) I discovered my latest speech habit: prefacing what I say with “obviously”, with examples like:
“Obviously, this varies from place to place…” “Obviously, this is a sweeping statement; I don’t mean everything…” “Obviously, when we’re doing this, we won’t do it exactly like I’m saying now…” I’m trying to figure out why or when I’ve started doing this.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>During a first session with a mentee (my <a href="https://adplist.org/mentors/jalyn-cai"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >ADPList profile</a>, if you want to book a session!) I discovered my latest speech habit: prefacing what I say with “obviously”, with examples like:</p>
<ul>
<li>“Obviously, this varies from place to place…”</li>
<li>“Obviously, this is a sweeping statement; I don’t mean <em>everything…”</em></li>
<li>“Obviously, when we’re doing this, we won’t do it exactly like I’m saying now…”</li>
</ul>
<p>I’m trying to figure out why or when I’ve started doing this. I have other habits — using <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BgVieDYFp35/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >too many ‘like’</a>, the word ‘basically’ (which, after being called out sometime last year, I’ve switched over to using ‘essentially’. Same problem, different word) — but “obviously” is new. Or at least, in an ironic way, something that hadn’t been obvious to me.</p>
<p>Whatever the defence mechanism is fueling this, I think I’ll do well to stop doing it. I forget things that are obvious to me might not be obvious at all to the person I’m speaking to.</p>
<p>Even if it’s obvious, it also seems redundant to call that out, now that I’m thinking about it. Maybe it’s my need to cushion my words with fillers to make myself less nervous about human interaction?</p>
<p>Observations like this used to (?) make me super self-conscious.</p>
<p>I remember a class called Speech Communications in my mass communications course, when during an evaluation of a speech, I was told that I tug at my shirt a lot when I’m talking. I took that feedback and suddenly I’m a rigid robot the next time I’m trying to present something.</p>
<p>Then, when <em>that</em> was called out as well, I started gesticulating a lot; big movements with my hands. It’s something that I still do now, I think.</p>
<p>I went away with a loss of confidence in public speaking after the class, which is pretty much the opposite of what the intended outcome was.</p>
<p>Now that Singapore is opening up again with a majority of the population vaccinated, and people are trickling back into the office (and we are also encouraged to go back at least once a week), I’m trying to figure out how to do presentations in-person again. I haven’t done that in the past year and a half, and I know it’ll be a curve I have to overcome.</p>
<p>Still, the annoying thing about skills of this nature is that the more you do it, the better you get at it. Right before the pandemic hit, I was looking into joining a Toastmasters club.</p>
<p>Maybe it’s time to start looking again.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why and how I track every minute of my life</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/tracking-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Aug 2021 16:11:11 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/tracking-time/</guid>
      <description>It’s 2015, and my workplace was exploring different tools for resource management.
It started when the team lead wanted a way to “sell” our services as an in-house team (and I’ll be honest, I’m not sure that quantifying time spent was the way to do it but that’s a story for another day), so we went through a few, finding the pros and cons of each before settling on Harvest.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It’s 2015, and my workplace was exploring different tools for resource management.</p>
<p>It started when the team lead wanted a way to “sell” our services as an in-house team (and I’ll be honest, I’m not sure that quantifying time spent was the way to do it but that’s a story for another day), so we went through a few, finding the pros and cons of each before settling on Harvest.</p>
<p>I think it’s because it was the cheapest per seat, maybe?</p>
<p>But that whole exercise of finding a tool and figuring out what worked and what didn’t also led me to think about my <em>own</em> hours, outside of work.</p>
<p>I hadn’t come across <a href="https://lauravanderkam.com/2017/09/welcome-168-hours-time-tracking-challenge/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >Laura Vanderkam</a>‘s content at that point, so it was trial and error on my part to figuring out what I was tracking.</p>
<p>I remember polling my friends and colleagues about my information architecture — or really just categories or buckets of time, occupational hazard aside — and trying to see if I was being too pedantic about some things, and too general for others.</p>
<p>So… I guess the question begs: Why do I track my time?</p>
<p>It started out as a way for me to find out where I was spending (wasting) my time — back in 2015, the time I took to commute was definitely an issue on my mind, and I feel like being able to clock that time made me aware of 1) how much it was, and 2) where it ranked amongst my other ‘smaller’ activities, like going to the gym.</p>
<p>More than that, I figured that if I knew what I was doing, and for how long, I could in theory optimize my time and productivity. I also remember thinking a lot about what that tipping point would be, for me to use money to buy time, instead of spending my time to get money instead.</p>
<h3 id="things-i-should-know-with-common-sense-but-instead-knew-for-sure">Things I should know with common sense, but instead knew for sure:</h3>
<ul>
<li>I spend way too much time beyond my 40 hours a week for work</li>
<li>(That isn’t counting the work-adjacent activity, which includes things like training, development courses/classes that are specifically applied at work, and as of 2021, mentoring sessions)</li>
<li>Meal prep is a really effective time saver, even though the upfront cost of it seems high (I spend about 45 minutes every Sunday doing it, compared to ~25 minutes a day)</li>
<li>Being lazy in bed is an actual bad habit of mine</li>
<li>Sometimes I chunk a lot of activity under “Internet”, even though I have specific buckets for media consumption, reading, fandom stuff etc. Pretty sure that’s indicative of a bigger problem, which is that I (falsely) think I can multitask</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>That said, Toggl — the app I’ve been using since 2015 — <a href="https://twitter.com/toggltrack/status/1431554352506884096"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >had a functional error</a> over the weekend, and it’s thrown me off the loop as I keep trying to open the app on my phone. Hopefully that gets resolved soon.</p>
<p>Let me know if you try out tracking your time, even if just for a week, and if you see any surprises in there!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The seven sins (and why my top-ranked is gluttony)</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/gluttony/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Aug 2021 16:12:18 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/gluttony/</guid>
      <description>Out of the seven sins, I feel like my top three rotate between gluttony, sloth and pride.
Some days, I am one with sloth; I am the sloth; sloth becomes me, etc.
Gluttony, on the other hand, strikes me in cycles.
(Note: Possible trigger for disordered eating here!)
I try to put guardrails on my life, with habits like meal prepping, or working out and hitting a specific step count every day.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Out of the seven sins, I feel like my top three rotate between gluttony, sloth and pride.</p>
<p>Some days, I am one with sloth; I am the sloth; sloth becomes me, etc.</p>
<p>Gluttony, on the other hand, strikes me in cycles.</p>
<p>(Note: Possible trigger for disordered eating here!)</p>
<p>I try to put guardrails on my life, with habits like meal prepping, or working out and hitting a specific step count every day.</p>
<p>This year… has been kind of rough, on all these aspects. I’m not sure what has changed, and if it’s just an accelerated version of burnout in the time of this pandemic, but it is somehow significantly worse than this time last year.</p>
<p>Instead of meal prepping, I either:</p>
<ul>
<li>Skip a meal because there’s nothing I really want to eat, or;</li>
<li>Go on my phone and start (to the tune of Waving Through a Window) tap-tap-tapping for food to magically show up at my door steps, anytime from 30 to 50 minutes later</li>
</ul>
<p>In Thomas Aquinas’ <a href="https://www.newadvent.org/summa/3148.htm#article4"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >Summa Theologica</a>, he outlined the five ways that gluttony is committed. These include food that is:</p>
<ul>
<li>too expensive (I have two extremes with my cravings: 40 cents instant noodles, or a $250 buffet)</li>
<li>too elaborately prepared (Maybe not so much on this one? Score?)</li>
<li>too much in quantity ()</li>
<li>eaten too quickly (I guess? It depends. If I’m eating by myself, I tend to do it quite fast so that I can do other things)</li>
<li>eaten too early (my teammates might dispute this, because I eat lunch at 3pm, reallll healthily like, so… reverse-gluttony?)</li>
</ul>
<p>Oooh, boy. Lots to unpack here. I also know that the only way is through, so I just have to identify my obstacles in meal prepping again to do it more consistently now.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happy 30th, World Wide Web!</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/world-wide-web/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Aug 2021 16:13:50 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/world-wide-web/</guid>
      <description>Age 6 (maybe 7?) I get my first email address. My journey to start understanding this WWW thing begins properly.
Age 11 My computer/internet usage time is limited by two factors: Sharing a single desktop computer with my sister, and school/homework. Still, I find time to use it.
I research for a presentation all about dolphins, complete with videos and .wav sounds that I download from different webpages. Pretty sure it’s an awesome presentation.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3 id="age-6-maybe-7">Age 6 (maybe 7?)</h3>
<p>I get my first email address. My journey to start understanding this WWW thing begins properly.</p>
<h3 id="age-11">Age 11</h3>
<p>My computer/internet usage time is limited by two factors: Sharing a single desktop computer with my sister, and school/homework. Still, I find time to use it.</p>
<p>I research for a presentation all about dolphins, complete with videos and .wav sounds that I download from different webpages. Pretty sure it’s an awesome presentation.</p>
<h3 id="age-12">Age 12</h3>
<p>I win third place at a website building competition.</p>
<p>My secret to the reason why I learned to code? Neopets.</p>
<h3 id="age-14">Age 14</h3>
<p>I discover so many things that are just starting to get its footing: <a href="/beginnings/"  >Blogger, LiveJournal, hosting on someone’s cool-sounding domain as a subdomain</a>; fandom forums; Yahoo Groups; Friendster, e-greetings; Napster and then later, LimeWire; Geocities…</p>
<p>I don’t know that it’ll be referred to in the future as the dot com bust, but here we are.</p>
<h3 id="age-16">Age 16</h3>
<p>I switch between appearing offline and online on MSN Messenger, hoping for specific someones to notice me and strike up a conversation.</p>
<p>In March of this year, I’ll buy jalyn.org. Unfortunately, like most good things that have happened in my life, I don’t keep a good hold of it, and it’ll be under the ownership of a domain squatter from 2006 onwards.</p>
<p>Even more unfortunately, my name is now also the name of a prescription medicine used by men to treat the symptoms of an enlarged prostate.</p>
<p>Around this time I also start earning some money on the web — installing WordPress and other web-based software for people (sometimes not even for actual money, but credits towards hosting) and providing customer service support for web hosting companies. Everything just seems to click in my head, and it’s easy.</p>
<h3 id="age-17">Age 17</h3>
<p>I’m an arrogant little shit in my web design class, and start using divs in my code with an externally-linked CSS file, ignoring the lecturer’s requirement for us to use tables for layouts and in-line styling. I don’t get a good grade in the class.</p>
<p>Oh, also, I get a BlackBerry, and completely go over my monthly 15 MB limit in about two hours flat.</p>
<h3 id="age-32-right-now">Age 32, right now.</h3>
<p>Honestly, I feel like I’ve been taking the world wide web for granted.</p>
<p>Beyond the primary function it serves in my life, it has also brought me closer to people I never would have met without the internet/web. I’ve met best friends through so many different ways on the web, done so many things — like this blog! but also other creative endeavors, and of course, some of my work — and will continue to do them.</p>
<p>Pretty amazing for 30 years.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Less/More</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/less-more/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jul 2021 16:16:46 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/less-more/</guid>
      <description>I came across this post on Minimalism Life that talks about a simplicity framework.
Now, you know me, and you know I love frameworks, whether I’m testing them or creating them or debunking them.
So let’s see if I can come up with my own list that reflects where I am right now (not the best mentally or physically, unfortunately).
Need Less Need More Anxiety Consistency Negativity Patience Self-criticism Gratitude Blame Clarity Comparing with others Making space for others Guilt Writing Sluggishness Movement </description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I came across <a href="https://minimalism.life/journal/constructing-a-simplicity-framework"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >this post</a> on Minimalism Life that talks about a simplicity framework.</p>
<p>Now, you know me, and you know I love frameworks, whether I’m testing them or creating them or debunking them.</p>
<p>So let’s see if I can come up with my own list that reflects where I am right now (not the best mentally or physically, unfortunately).</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Need Less</th>
<th>Need More</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Anxiety</td>
<td>Consistency</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Negativity</td>
<td>Patience</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Self-criticism</td>
<td>Gratitude</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Blame</td>
<td>Clarity</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Comparing with others</td>
<td>Making space for others</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Guilt</td>
<td>Writing</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sluggishness</td>
<td>Movement</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The commoditization of the design case study</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/design-commoditization/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jun 2021 16:19:26 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/design-commoditization/</guid>
      <description>I’ve done, I think, four portfolio reviews with the folks over at General Assembly.
I enjoy it, mostly (sometimes the imposter syndrome kicks in and I get self-conscious about whether or not I’m bringing value to these young designers). I get to talk to groups of 3 to 6 designers from each graduating batch, and have them play back their portfolios to me.
It’s not a failing of the individuals, to be sure, but—</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’ve done, I think, four portfolio reviews with the folks over at General Assembly.</p>
<p>I enjoy it, mostly (sometimes the imposter syndrome kicks in and I get self-conscious about whether or not I’m bringing value to these young designers). I get to talk to groups of 3 to 6 designers from each graduating batch, and have them play back their portfolios to me.</p>
<p>It’s not a failing of the individuals, to be sure, but—</p>
<p>It. is. all. the. same.</p>
<ul>
<li>Each case study starts and ends in exactly identical ways — though some students do expand on the more insightful things rather than the process;</li>
<li>Too much emphasis on the output rather than the outcomes, even for the self-identified UX researchers of the bunch;</li>
<li>The design process used might be ‘textbook’, but things in real working situations might not play out exactly that way in those steps;</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="so-what-does-this-have-to-do-with-me">So… what does this have to do with me?</h2>
<p>I published my own portfolio in 2016 (or maybe 2017), which is a lifetime — and two jobs — ago. At that time, the UX portfolio scene hasn’t been commoditized to the same regurgitation of “the design process”. I remember scrambling to find other portfolios with case studies that I could benchmark as a best practice. You know, like a real UX nerd.</p>
<p>Looking at my own portfolio now, though, I honestly can’t tell if I would pick myself from a stack of other portfolios. It’s not the exact same design process as the GA grads have, but the construct of it is largely similar: problem statements, what we did to unpacking them, and how we came up with solutions. Pretty flows and sketches and wireframes, and then the grand reveal.</p>
<p>Anyway.</p>
<p>I do remember getting commends from reviewers during that first job search with this portfolio, on the effort made and time spent on crafting it out.</p>
<p>How do I tell this story of working on awesome stuff with awesome people, without going through this template of a case study? Much to think about, now that I’m moving along in my career.</p>
<p>I suppose that is a design problem to be solved.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Racism in Singapore / Anti-racism</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/antiracism-singapore/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jun 2021 16:20:30 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/antiracism-singapore/</guid>
      <description>I’m a Chinese Singaporean, which means that while I’m in Singapore, I have not encountered racism, and will never experience it.
In the past couple of weeks, some racists have been caught on video:
Tan Boon Lee, a lecturer at the school I went to, confronted an interracial couple with some harmful stereotypes, as well as being an Islamophobe A Chinese woman banged on a gong to cause distress during her Hindu neighbor’s prayer ritual Yet another Chinese influencer used the trauma of the hurtful recording to create content for the sole purpose of entertainment So so so many accounts being documented on the #CALLITOUTSG tag The thing is, we know these aren’t isolated incidents.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’m a Chinese Singaporean, which means that while I’m in Singapore, I have not encountered racism, and will never experience it.</p>
<p>In the past couple of weeks, some racists have been caught on video:</p>
<ul>
<li>Tan Boon Lee, a lecturer at the school I went to, <a href="https://www.channelnewsasia.com/news/singapore/racist-man-interracial-couple-ngee-ann-poly-lecturer-14967624"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >confronted an interracial couple with some harmful stereotypes</a>, as well as being an Islamophobe</li>
<li>A Chinese woman <a href="https://www.channelnewsasia.com/news/singapore/police-investigate-woman-hit-gong-hindu-prayer-bell-neighbours-14988764?cid=telegram_cna_social_28112017_cna"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >banged on a gong to cause distress</a> during her Hindu neighbor’s prayer ritual</li>
<li>Yet another Chinese influencer used the trauma of the hurtful recording to <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/CP-LTgQjNJy/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >create content for the sole purpose of entertainment</a></li>
<li>So so so many accounts being documented on the <a href="https://www.instagram.com/explore/tags/callitoutsg/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >#CALLITOUTSG</a> tag</li>
</ul>
<p>The thing is, we know these aren’t isolated incidents. For every instance caught on camera, there are hundreds and thousands more of them.</p>
<p>Last year, when the Black Lives Matter movement went global, there was a surge of activist initiatives, including here in Singapore. There were also plenty of people who brushed it off by saying that this “doesn’t happen here”.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, we can see that the reality can’t be further from the statement.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Anti-racism is the commitment to fight racism wherever you find it, including in yourself.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>As an ally, here’s what I think is the bare minimum of what we should do:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Listen</strong>: Don’t assume that your lived experience (especially as the majority race) is the same for everyone else</li>
<li><strong>Call out:</strong> Don’t let acts of racism slide when you see them, even if — especially if — it’s an uncomfortable discussion</li>
<li><strong>Learn</strong>: And don’t expect your friends or strangers on the internet to educate you. They don’t need that additional burden</li>
<li><strong>Correct:</strong> Look out for micro-aggressions in the way you think and behave. Systemic and institutionalized racism manifest in ways that you might never have realized was discriminatory</li>
</ul>
<p>Of course, in no way is that an exhaustive list.</p>
<p>For more resources, check <a href="https://racerelations.better.sg/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >Race Relations in Singapore</a> out. Let’s all be better.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lapse in mental fortitude</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/lapse/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jun 2021 16:21:28 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/lapse/</guid>
      <description>I had a moment of intense FOMO earlier this week.
A new friend of mine had told me that she’d put in some money in AMC earlier this year, and she’s looking at a pretty big chunk of profit. Like, enough-for-a-downpayment, enough-to-pay-off-an-entire-student-loan, kind of big chunk.
For me, if I had done the same at the same time, it would have been enough-to-accelerate-my-financial-independence-plan-by-a-quarter. (I know, I know, I’ll stop with the dashes.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I had a moment of intense FOMO earlier this week.</p>
<p>A new friend of mine had told me that she’d put in some money in AMC earlier this year, and she’s looking at a pretty big chunk of profit. Like, enough-for-a-downpayment, enough-to-pay-off-an-entire-student-loan, kind of big chunk.</p>
<p>For me, if I had done the same at the same time, it would have been enough-to-accelerate-my-financial-independence-plan-by-a-quarter. (I know, I know, I’ll stop with the dashes.)</p>
<p>In a near moment of weakness, I looked up r/wallstreetbets.</p>
<p>I opened up my trading app and typed in $BB.</p>
<p>I placed a (pretty sizeable) bid at market rate.</p>
<p>This was around 6:30 PM here, which was several hours before the market opens.</p>
<p>And thank goodness for that. Five minutes later, I decided I was out of my fucking mind, and canceled it before it could go through.</p>
<hr>
<p>Guess I’ll continue on my slow path.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A snapshot of my waking moments</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/waking/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 May 2021 16:23:41 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/waking/</guid>
      <description>When I wake up, I reach for my phone.
Not checking for messages or notifications (though sometimes I sneak a glimpse), but to start a new entry in my daily log on Notion.
The first thing I do is start typing all that I remember from — hopefully — a night of dreaming. I dream quite vividly, and it’s a race against time to record that down, translating something that had made so much sense in dream land to something that is coherent in actual words.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When I wake up, I reach for my phone.</p>
<p>Not checking for messages or notifications (though sometimes I sneak a glimpse), but to start a new entry in my daily log on Notion.</p>
<p>The first thing I do is start typing all that I remember from — hopefully — a night of dreaming. I dream quite vividly, and it’s a race against time to record that down, translating something that had made so much sense in dream land to something that is coherent in actual words.</p>
<p>(Yesterday I dreamt I’d forgotten my mask and had to use the hood from my hoodie to cover my face while walking.</p>
<p>The day before: I had to hide in the toilets from a man who was hunting me but it wasn’t not working, and he was also the father of the witches who’s at fault for all the deaths (???).</p>
<p>Yeah. Exciting!)</p>
<p>When I’m done with scrambling to write everything I can remember before they all dissolve into wisps of nothingness in my memory, I fill up the title of the entry with one thing I’m grateful for in my life.</p>
<p>These days, I find that I’m thankful for these general patterns:</p>
<ul>
<li>Getting through a work day or week</li>
<li>Having free time/anticipating free time</li>
<li>Spending quality time with people</li>
</ul>
<p>Thematically, they all have to do with time and how I spend it, which tracks.</p>
<p>(And then I proceed to spend another twenty minutes in bed just lazing.)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>(and at once i knew i was not magnificent)</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/writing-stuff-playlist/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2021 16:26:33 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/writing-stuff-playlist/</guid>
      <description>I call this my ‘writing stuff’ playlist, in which I do everything but.
Run – Daughter Tip of my Tongue – The Civil Wars Set the Fire to the Third Bar – Snow Patrol ft. Martha Wainwright When I Go – Slow Club Blood Bank – Bon Iver Off I Go – Greg Laswell Alaska – Maggie Rogers Thunder Clatter – Wild Cub Challengers – The New Pornographers My Backwards Walk – Frightened Rabbit There’s another version of this playlist that’s basically just all of Little Mix’s discography, Broadway recordings, and The Barden Bellas, so there’s that.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I call this my ‘writing stuff’ playlist, in which I do everything but.</p>
<ol>
<li>Run – Daughter</li>
<li>Tip of my Tongue – The Civil Wars</li>
<li>Set the Fire to the Third Bar – Snow Patrol ft. Martha Wainwright</li>
<li>When I Go – Slow Club</li>
<li>Blood Bank – Bon Iver</li>
<li>Off I Go – Greg Laswell</li>
<li>Alaska – Maggie Rogers</li>
<li>Thunder Clatter – Wild Cub</li>
<li>Challengers – The New Pornographers</li>
<li>My Backwards Walk – Frightened Rabbit</li>
</ol>
<p>There’s another version of this playlist that’s basically just all of <a href="/little-mix"  >Little Mix’s discography</a>, Broadway recordings, and The Barden Bellas, so there’s that.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stoicism, and what we can control</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/stoic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2021 16:27:43 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/stoic/</guid>
      <description>I am the one thing in life I can control, Hamilton‘s Aaron Burr sings.
I grew up in a household where behaviours are mostly reactive, when sometimes it felt like things happening to you are a personal affront. It’s something that I have grown to reject, as I grew older (and hopefully wiser), but I also wanted a way to frame my thoughts and attitudes around things.
That’s when I discovered stoicism.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I am the one thing in life I can control, <em>Hamilton</em>‘s Aaron Burr sings.</p>
<p>I grew up in a household where behaviours are mostly reactive, when sometimes it felt like things happening to you are a personal affront. It’s something that I have grown to reject, as I grew older (and hopefully wiser), but I also wanted a way to frame my thoughts and attitudes around things.</p>
<p>That’s when I discovered stoicism.</p>
<p>There’s a lot with stoicism that leaves me scratching my head, confused if these men (all of them are, naturally) really did live their lives void of emotion when bad things happen, and worshipped logical thought as its own god.</p>
<p>Epicetetus wrote, “If, for example, you are fond of a specific ceramic cup, remind yourself that it is only ceramic cups in general of which you are fond. Then, if it breaks, you will not be disturbed.”</p>
<p>I thought, yeah, that makes sense. Things belong to you, and you don’t belong to things.</p>
<p>Then, he followed it up with, “If you kiss your child, or your wife, say that you only kiss things which are human, and thus you will not be disturbed if either of them dies.”</p>
<hr>
<p>Excuse me, <em>what</em>?</p>
<hr>
<p>I dove into Marcus Aurelius’ Meditations too.</p>
<p>That was an interesting read – I know it’s heralded as one of the leading texts to stoicism, and the emperor himself is regarded as one of the most influential humans and not just on stoicism. Some parts of the journal definitely felt like he was trying to convince himself that stoicism is the answer, too. It made sense, since he’d apparently never intended these private journal entries to be published.</p>
<p>I know if my journal entries, safely logged on Day One, were to be published one day, people would be befuddled too.</p>
<p>Ultimately, stoicism is still a domain that I’m <em>really</em> new at and exploring the different facets of.</p>
<p>At a glance, it seems like an answer, though at this point I’m not quite sure what the exact question is.</p>
<p>I’m still the one thing in life that I can control, which means: Things happen, and the only thing we can control is how we respond to them.</p>
<p>So I’m going to take this, probably struggle with it for a long time, but hey. At least I’ll be trying.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Feedback and growth in the workplace</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/workplace-goals/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jan 2021 16:29:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/workplace-goals/</guid>
      <description>I’m in the process of setting my 2021 OKRs for work right now. As a starting point, my mentor had requested for me to think about my strengths and how to tie it all together.
Me: Okay, I’m going to need some time to think about my strengths. Also me: Do you want weaknesses too? I can give them to you right now, if you want.
An experiment in gathering feedback I used to squirm at the idea of talking about myself.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’m in the process of setting my 2021 OKRs for work right now. As a starting point, my mentor had requested for me to think about my strengths and how to tie it all together.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Me:</strong> Okay, I’m going to need some time to think about my strengths.
<strong>Also me:</strong> Do you want weaknesses too? I can give them to you right now, if you want.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="an-experiment-in-gathering-feedback">An experiment in gathering feedback</h2>
<p>I used to squirm at the idea of talking about myself. Actually, that’s a lie – I still squirm at the idea, but now I (begrudgingly) recognize its value in allowing people to consider both the quality of my work, and the sum of my character.</p>
<p>I’m always trying to make things easier for myself though, and to that end, I’ve been experimenting.</p>
<p>At the end of each project or phase of work last year, I sent out a really simple Typeform survey to my teammates, which has 4 questions, and a scale to answer. They look something like this:</p>
<ul>
<li>Jalyn was helpful and was aligned to the team’s objectives.</li>
<li>Jalyn delivered a high quality of work and showed her value to the team.</li>
<li>I will work with Jalyn again / I will recommend Jalyn to other teams in the future.</li>
</ul>
<p>And finally, an open-ended area for comments.</p>
<p>This was also something my old team at a previous workplace had done, although that was done on a team/delivery level, and not a personal one.</p>
<p>It’s also interesting, as I have received more useful qualitative feedback through these surveys than the team did with it.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-it-good-for">What is it good for?</h2>
<p>Where it shines in my exercise to find my strengths and weaknesses (which said mentor has reframed as <em>road blocks</em>, which I thought was very nice) is that it gives me a way to cluster the feedback I received.</p>
<p>This way, I get to pull exact quotes across all the different work I’ve done, and be able to back my own perceived performance with this feedback.</p>
<h2 id="a-demonstration-in-action">A demonstration in action</h2>
<p>(Just an example each!)</p>
<p>For my self-anointed strength of:</p>
<p><strong>Collaboration between functions –</strong> “She has good technical knowledge and is able to bridge the gap between design and tech.”</p>
<p><strong>Positive and can-do attitude –</strong> “She radiates passion and inspires her peers to drive and push the work further.”</p>
<p><strong>Providing structure –</strong> “You came in with your usual neat and organised approach, and the new design system is super neat and easy to go through.”</p>
<p>So, let’s chalk this up as an experiment gone well. I’ll have to think about tweaking it to optimize it even further, but I’m definitely going to carry through asking my teammates for some kind of feedback now!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to stop being distracted when reading on iOS</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/reading-distraction/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jan 2021 16:30:59 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/reading-distraction/</guid>
      <description>Over the course of the last three months, I realized I’ve seriously slipped in my ability to focus deeply.
I’m constantly distracted by everything – messages on Telegram from friends, pings and calls on Teams, social media notifications, emails, refreshing Reddit… the list goes on.
I’d even break my own momentum by sliding the notification screen on my phone down, and noting that I don’t have any.
So, this is a problem.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Over the course of the last three months, I realized I’ve seriously slipped in my ability to focus deeply.</p>
<p>I’m constantly distracted by everything – messages on Telegram from friends, pings and calls on Teams, social media notifications, emails, refreshing Reddit… the list goes on.</p>
<p>I’d even break my own momentum by sliding the notification screen on my phone down, and noting that I don’t have any.</p>
<p>So, this is a problem.</p>
<p>One quick fix I’ve been using to focus is to force myself to stay on one app, using Guided Access.</p>
<hr>
<p>(Sorry, it&rsquo;s 2024 and I need to update images!)</p>
<h2 id="handy-dandy-instructions">Handy dandy instructions</h2>
<ol>
<li>Go to Settings &gt; Accessibility &gt; General (you’ll have to scroll to the bottom of the screen)</li>
<li>Click into Guided Access</li>
<li>Turn the toggle on</li>
<li>Go to Passcode Settings on this screen, and use Set Guide Access Passcode – I don’t use the Face ID option so that it gives me an additional barrier</li>
<li>???</li>
<li>Profit!</li>
</ol>
<p>Kidding aside – when you go to your reading app of choice, just click on your side button three times to lock usage to that app. It’ll mute notifications, prevent swipe ups/downs, and removes your ability to navigate to other apps as well.</p>
<p>Have fun!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2020: Year in Review</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/2020-year-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2020 19:21:16 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/2020-year-in-review/</guid>
      <description>Oh, 2020. A year that started out promisingly, and subsequently veered off-course about fifty million times over.
I’m one of the lucky ones – holding the privilege to hold my job and not worry about money, not having to experience the tremendous loss and the grief the pandemic brought, and living in a country where the response hasn’t been just a real life depiction of my favorite gif.
So, I’m happy to see 2020 behind us.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Oh, 2020. A year that started out promisingly, and subsequently veered off-course about fifty million times over.</p>
<p>I’m one of the lucky ones – holding the privilege to hold my job and not worry about money, not having to experience the tremendous loss and the grief the pandemic brought, and living in a country where the response hasn’t been just a real life depiction of <a href="https://media.giphy.com/media/e5kbmb3wX3J1S/giphy.gif"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >my favorite gif</a>.</p>
<p>So, I’m happy to see 2020 behind us.</p>
<h2 id="what-couldve-been-better">What could’ve been better</h2>
<p>Besides vague gestures in 2020’s general direction, I can break it down to two general buckets: physical autonomy, and mental fortitude.</p>
<p><strong>Physical autonomy</strong></p>
<p>In 2018, I injured my back, and it has never been the same ever since. I’ve gone to physical therapists and chiropractors, had scans done, and dutifully did my core exercises. Yet, nothing has helped that constant and consistent ache.</p>
<p>To exacerbate the problem, when I started working from home, I didn’t have a setup in place. I was using a kitchen chair, and sometimes when the pain of sitting up got to be too much, I would just lay down on my stomach. It worked – but at the expense of my neck (which cracks every time I turn it). Thankfully, <a href="https://www.ohlookiecookie.com/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >my</a>  <a href="https://www.siew.online/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >lovely</a>  <a href="https://www.instagram.com/facesofrow/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >friends</a> got me an office chair for my birthday, which definitely helped.</p>
<p>My strength training has plummeted too: I used to be able to squat 50kg and deadlift 65kg at the gym with barbells and plates; now 20kg dumbbells are making me doubt myself. Every twinge makes me paranoid that my body will soon crumple onto the floor.</p>
<p>It wasn’t a squat or a deadlift that caused an injury in my hip (an area that had never really hurt before) at the end of November, but an innocent sounding one-arm row. I felt something on the left of my lower body shift in a way that it shouldn’t, and immediately I literally said out loud: <em>oh fuck</em>, before I shuffled awkwardly to my bed and laid down to assess the damage done.</p>
<p>So yeah, long story short: my core strength is currently close to non-existent, and it’s giving me a real backache on top of a hypothetical headache.</p>
<p><strong>Mental fortitude</strong></p>
<p>I got frustrated – a lot – at things out of my control. I found myself annoyed at other people’s behavior, even while I kept reminding myself of the principles of stoicism and repeating <em>I am the one thing in life I can control</em> in my head.</p>
<p>I lost patience at myself more times I can count, whether it’s because of my back acting up, which also led to me screwing up my nutrition because of the old “might as well” mindset.</p>
<p>A slight burnout happened, despite me pretending it didn’t. I started a new job in February, and between trying to prove myself with a new group of colleagues, having to navigate the working-from-home situation, and adapting to really fast paced work, I didn’t want to admit that I was taking on more than I could.</p>
<h2 id="what-went-well">What went well</h2>
<p>Fun fact: I had to go hunting for my bullet journal, since I abandoned that in mid-October when I moved everything to Notion.</p>
<p><strong>Meditating once a day</strong></p>
<p>I started out with guided meditation, and now I’m just using the timer for 15 minutes every morning.</p>
<p><strong>Save 65% of income</strong></p>
<p>The numbers are officially in on this last day of the year, and it is: <strong>69.4%</strong>!</p>
<p>Of course, this is helped <em>massively</em> by the fact that I didn’t go on holiday at all, and that’s a nice chunk saved up.</p>
<p><strong>Work out twice a week</strong></p>
<p>This was like a see-saw, and on weeks when I felt well enough to, I managed to do at least two workouts a week. Right now for the past 8 weeks, I’ve been doing it six times a week, just to get myself in that routine.</p>
<p><strong>Read 52 books</strong> (58!)</p>
<p>The bulk of it happened in the last quarter of the year, but from a pure numerical standpoint, I think it’s fair to say that I hit this goal!</p>
<p><strong>5,000 steps/day</strong></p>
<p>January and February went well, with an average of 5,000 steps… and then, of course, the rest of the year happened. I didn’t pick this up until October, going for a walk in the evening. Then, when I got the Fitbit, I’ve consistently done that daily.</p>
<p><strong>Start and sustain a blog</strong></p>
<p>This has layers:</p>
<ol>
<li>I had a financial independence blog, where I was writing under a pseudonym (just because I was giving real numbers), but I’ve let that go gently into the good night when the pandemic hit. I didn’t want to flaunt numbers at a time when people were struggling, but I guess the good thing is that I can consolidate the content that I would’ve written over there as part of posts here too.</li>
<li>This blog, in which I wrote really inconsistently for the first quarter of the year, took a long break until October.</li>
</ol>
<p>Huh, I guess October gave me a kick in the ass about my goals.</p>
<p>Then there are the things that happened as the year went by:</p>
<p><strong>Playing the ukulele</strong></p>
<p><a href="https://www.instagram.com/psychhabitat/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >My friend Tanisha</a> gifted me one during the circuit breaker period, because I was trying to play my old guitar with steel strings that are really uncomfortable for my fingers. It’s gone well, and I’ve made it a habit to play at least one song every day.</p>
<p><strong>Waking up earlier</strong></p>
<p>This was a spur-of-a-moment thing, when I decided I wanted to <a href="/sleep"  >track my sleep</a>. So far, I’ve shifted my wake-up time from 8 AM to between 6:30 AM and 7 AM, which gives me ample time to work out, jog, and read!</p>
<p><strong>Drinking 2.5l of water</strong></p>
<p>I’ve been terrible with staying hydrated because I have a thing against public washrooms, but now that I’ve been at home for the majority of the year, I have no excuse. I usually front load my water intake to the first half of the day too.</p>
<h2 id="highlights-from-my-gratitude-journal">Highlights from my gratitude journal</h2>
<p>I note down one line every morning when I wake up, on Notion. It’s done plenty to shift my mindset to a more positive one.</p>
<ul>
<li>Progress, however slow</li>
<li>Making my own bubble tea</li>
<li>Thinking it’s Sunday when it’s still Saturday</li>
<li>Spending time with my nephews (this is a recurring one!)</li>
<li>Amazing friends</li>
<li>Opportunities at work</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="a-random-list-of-media">A random list of media</h2>
<p>And now, to cap it off, here’s a list of things I’ve enjoyed watching and listening to this year:</p>
<ul>
<li>She-Ra: The Princesses of Power</li>
<li>Babysitters Club</li>
<li>Haunting of Bly Manor</li>
<li>#blackAF</li>
<li>Brie Larson’s YouTube channel</li>
<li>Among Us streamers (Pokimane, Valkyrae, Hafu, Fuslie, Sykkuno and others!)</li>
<li>Behind the Bastards</li>
<li>Chameleon: Hollywood Con Queen</li>
<li>You’re Wrong About</li>
</ul>
<p>If you’re reading this, I hope you had at least a bearable 2020, and that 2021 would be much better for you and all of us. See you next year!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>One&#43; month with the FitBit Charge 4</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/fitbit-charge-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Dec 2020 19:23:39 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/fitbit-charge-4/</guid>
      <description>Two months ago, I talked about my terrible sleep habits, and how using an app on the phone to track my sleep wasn’t the best solution for me at the time.
Since then, I’ve gotten my FitBit Charge 4, and have been using it for a little over a month. I got the Storm Blue Classic Band — to be more accurate, my friend Siew who placed the order for me got me that variant (I told her to surprise me) — but any of the other choices would have fit my dark and neutral wardrobe anyway.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Two months ago, I talked about <a href="/sleep"  >my terrible sleep habits</a>, and how using an app on the phone to track my sleep wasn’t the best solution for me at the time.</p>
<p>Since then, I’ve gotten my <a href="https://www.fitbit.com/sg/charge4"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >FitBit Charge 4</a>, and have been using it for a little over a month. I got the Storm Blue Classic Band — to be more accurate, my friend <a href="https://www.siew.online/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >Siew</a> who placed the order for me got me that variant (I told her to surprise me) — but any of the other choices would have fit my dark and neutral wardrobe anyway.</p>
<p>This would be my first smart wearable, besides the one week I tried with a company-owned Apple Watch a few years ago. As far as wearing watches go, I’d consistently worn one until I was 17. Then, as phones got more ubiquitous, I ditched my watch.</p>
<p>By that count, that was almost half a lifetime ago.</p>
<p>Is it weird that I have something on my wrist again? Not really. It doesn’t bother me as much, but I have definitely forgotten I was wearing the Charge, and somehow slammed my wrist against a window frame after opening the window. But that is more of a ‘me’ thing, and not so much a ‘wearable’ thing.</p>
<h2 id="some-things-i-really-like">Some things I really like:</h2>
<p><strong>Consistently wanting to hit my goal:</strong> Seeing my step count gives me the visual reminder that I need to hit my goal. It’s currently “just” 5,000 steps a day, and I’m working on extending that bit by bit. In fact, I usually try to get that before 9:30 AM aka the time I start work in front of my laptop, and it’s absolutely a new habit with wearing this device.</p>
<p>Previously, with just the tracking from the odometer on my phone, it’s out of sight and out of mind for me on some days when I was clocking in just a few hundred steps.</p>
<p>Also, it’s definitely good for me that it tracks steps while I’m running in place.</p>
<p><strong>Tracking parameters I wasn’t before:</strong> I get to see my heart rate, which is cool because when I walk out with my mask on, it reminds me of my poor, asthmatic self when it goes +40 my resting heart beat rate.</p>
<p>The Charge also tracks my <a href="https://blog.fitbit.com/active-zone-minutes/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >active zone minutes</a>, which should in theory help me improve my cardio health.</p>
<p><strong>Battery life is pretty good:</strong> I’m still figuring out the optimal time to charge, but I’ve been doing it in the morning right after my workout + aforementioned jogging session while I shower. You can see it in the picture in this post actually, and it is surprisingly consistently at 87% when I start charging it. I haven’t noticed how long it takes to charge exactly, but I would pick it up half an hour to an hour after, and it would be fully charged until the cycle continues the next day.</p>
<p><strong>Gradually shifting my wake up time earlier:</strong> The Charge has the vibrating alarm that happens in a half-hour window for my wake up time, which works by tracking when it would be the least disruptive to your sleep cycle.</p>
<p>A month ago, I started off waking up at 8 AM, with the alarm window between 7:30 – 8 AM. Now, I’m waking up between 6:30 AM and 7 AM, and I want to see if I can shift that even earlier.</p>
<h2 id="and-some-things-i-wish-could-be-improved">And some things I wish could be improved:</h2>
<p><strong>Sleep monitoring could use more stats:</strong> In addition to the sleep alarm, the device and app also come with sleep monitoring stats. I get to see how long I slept, how much time I spent in each category of REM, Light and Deep sleep (with a 30-day average, and a benchmark against women my age), a sleep score (I’m only getting 10% Goods, and Fairs the rest of the time), estimated oxygen variation which is supposed to detect breathing issues, and… that’s it.</p>
<p>Fitbit Premium is needed to unlock two more stats: my sleeping heart rate, and a restlessness score. I’m not sure that is worth ten bucks a month, to be honest. I’d also like to see other meaningful stats, like time taken to fall asleep.</p>
<p><strong>Trapped dirt:</strong> Could be another ‘me’ thing, because my room does get really dusty. But between the detachable straps and the watch face, I have to wipe it daily to get the layer of dust off.</p>
<p><strong>Responsiveness of touch screen:</strong> Compared to the Apple Watch – even the earlier Series that I was testing with – it seems a lot more delayed in reaction time, and the screen wake via a hand raise works 80% of the time.</p>
<p>It’s not a huge deal though, because I don’t actually use it as a phone accessory (I’ve turned notifications off because I don’t want it buzzing all the time when I already have vibration off even on my phone) so I don’t need to swipe through the screens all that often. Still a little annoying though.</p>
<p><strong>Contactless payment:</strong> I can’t use it. My bank isn’t on it. End of story.</p>
<p>There are some other features on the watch and app that I don’t really use, like meditation/mindfulness (I already have one too many app for it, which are Headspace and Insight Timer), period tracking (thank you, Clue), food logging (been on My Fitness Pal for far too long), and I don’t have a fancy weighing scale to automatically sync my weight.</p>
<p>In all, though, I still think this was one of my best purchases of 2020.</p>
<p>Which isn’t <em>a lot</em>, because I didn’t buy too many things.</p>
<p>Being able to track sleep and getting that consistency to hit my steps are huge deals though! We’ll see if I will upgrade to a Sense or Versa in a few years, but I can say that I’ll continue to wear this for as long as it lasts.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Photo Storage &amp; Google&#39;s Take-Backsies</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/photo-storage/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 19:24:50 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/photo-storage/</guid>
      <description>“Noooooo,” I typed dramatically to my chats after taking a screenshot of this storage change from Google. To recap: From June 2021, high quality photos uploaded to Google Photos will count towards the storage limit, instead of the current unlimited uploading.
I’ve talked a little before my digital clutter in general, and glossed over how my cloud storage is set up. I’ve had Dropbox for years before I let it lapse this year, and was planning on getting a Google One subscription.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>“Noooooo,” I typed dramatically to my chats after taking a screenshot of this <a href="https://blog.google/products/photos/storage-changes/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >storage change from Google</a>. To recap: From June 2021, high quality photos uploaded to Google Photos will count towards the storage limit, instead of the current unlimited uploading.</p>
<p>I’ve talked a little before <a href="/digital-hoarding"  >my digital clutter</a> in general, and glossed over how my cloud storage is set up. I’ve had Dropbox for years before I let it lapse this year, and was planning on getting a Google One subscription. That is, until I realized that photo storage was going to be a non-issue with Google Photos, and held off getting a plan.</p>
<p>Until now.</p>
<p>Honestly, that pause for effect is a little unwarranted — it’s $28/year for me, and a manageable amount for the value it would bring.</p>
<p>Of my digital assets, photos and videos storage remain the thing that is the most cluttered for me. I don’t take the time to go through each photo and only keep things that matter. Screenshots make up a not-insignificant percentage of my images.</p>
<p>Occupational hazard, you might say.</p>
<p>So, I guess this is as good a time to carve a new intentional practice with my images:</p>
<ul>
<li>Review the photos and videos on my phone and delete bad and irrelevant files on an ongoing basis</li>
<li>Create automated workflows to shift other files where they need to be:
<ul>
<li>Store design-related screenshots on a Figma board</li>
<li>Upload important images and screenshots on Notion</li>
<li>Back up important images and videos via the Google Photos app</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Now, off I go to delete some photos.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sleep, or how I&#39;m pretty bad at it</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/sleep/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 16:10:09 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/sleep/</guid>
      <description>My nephews do this thing where they resist sleep for at least half an hour each time they’re laid down in their beds. It’s a whole production of denying, bargaining, and finally acceptance.
It turns out I’m not that different with these two-and-a-half-year-olds.
I’ve started tracking my sleep these past few weeks. The results, like all click-bait titles promise, are unbelievable, astonishing… which is to say, completely not at all.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My nephews do this thing where they resist sleep for at least half an hour each time they’re laid down in their beds. It’s a whole production of denying, bargaining, and finally acceptance.</p>
<p>It turns out I’m not that different with these two-and-a-half-year-olds.</p>
<p>I’ve started tracking my sleep these past few weeks. The results, like all click-bait titles promise, are unbelievable, astonishing… which is to say, completely not at all.</p>
<h2 id="how-my-night-routine-has-been-pretty-much-my-whole-life">How my night routine has been, pretty much my whole life</h2>
<ul>
<li>Late dinners, because of my habit of having late lunches (anytime before 2:30 PM is early for me)</li>
<li>Coffees and cokes all through the day, baby!</li>
<li>Screens (laptop), screens (phone), screens (both) all the way before bed</li>
<li>“Just one more thing” before I switch the lights off</li>
<li>Inconsistent sleeping hours; 12:30 AM is pretty early, kinda</li>
<li>Lying stomach-down on my bed with my laptop in front of me, and falling asleep with the lights still on before startling myself awake sometime in the middle of the night, around 3 AM</li>
<li>Using my phone in bed after lights out, on the occasions when I <em>do</em> switch the lights off</li>
<li>Using my phone as an alarm, and hitting that snooze button but totally engineering it by setting an alarm that is earlier than I mean to wake up</li>
<li>I’m fortunate that even while doing all of these things like a real asshole, my body clock is still functional and I usually wake up around the same time, and sometimes before the alarm</li>
<li>…And then I hit the snooze button for just a few more minutes.</li>
</ul>
<p>There are some things that are unavoidable, like looking at screens before bed. It’s 9:57 PM and I’m drafting this out on my phone right now (my external monitor fizzled out earlier this week – moment of silence please).</p>
<p>I’m still not sure how to fit in all the things I want to accomplish within the hours of the day after work has taken up a whole chunk of it (read, write, watch stuff, play the ukulele, walk… the list goes on), and still be able to get to bed at a decent time.</p>
<p>Still, there’s at least some correlation that good sleep quality will perpetuate the healthy parts of our lives (even though this <a href="https://guzey.com/books/why-we-sleep/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >debunking and ongoing drama of Why We Sleep</a> cracked me up), which is why I’ve been trying to make my sleep environment and circumstances better.</p>
<h2 id="changes-ive-been-making">Changes I’ve been making</h2>
<p>What gets measured gets managed, and in hindsight, I’m actually surprised at myself that I wasn’t already tracking my sleep, given that I track every other aspect of my life.</p>
<p>For now, I’m using SleepScore and have been for the past three weeks, but there are a couple of issues. One of them is that I have to keep it by my bedside, which definitely keeps me in the habit of scrolling forever before I decide to drift off too.</p>
<p>The other bigger issue is its inaccuracy on some nights, where there will be long periods of no detection. This skews the tracking and obviously defeats the point. So, to that end, I have bought a FitBit Charge that should be getting to me soon!</p>
<p>Outside of that, I have also been trying to sleep before midnight. It’s a weird thing, because I feel like I’m losing precious time going to sleep at an earlier hour, even though I know that the effects of sleeping early will compound in ways that trying to keep myself awake would.</p>
<p>Especially when I’m trying to keep awake trying to read one last thing, or watch one last thing, or continue conversations.</p>
<p>Exactly like my two-and-a-half-years-old nephews.</p>
<p>(Check back on this experiment in a bit; I’ll probably write an update to track my progress!)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When is it time to upgrade a device?</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/upgrade/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Oct 2020 16:11:11 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/upgrade/</guid>
      <description>I love gadgets, and I’ll be the first to admit that I love Apple and its products. I have: an iPhone X; the AirPods with a wireless charging case, and I’m typing this from a MacBook Pro. For a while, I was contemplating buying an iPad, or an Apple Watch.
I got neither. Instead, as with a lot of things, I took too long to decide and lost interest in getting them.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I love gadgets, and I’ll be the first to admit that I love Apple and its products. I have: an iPhone X; the AirPods with a wireless charging case, and I’m typing this from a MacBook Pro. For a while, I was contemplating buying an iPad, or an Apple Watch.</p>
<p>I got neither. Instead, as with a lot of things, I took too long to decide and lost interest in getting them.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Fun little side story: In 2006, when I was but an impressionable freshman, I came up with a pitch in 15 minutes for an ‘MacPhone’. This is pre-iPhone, and you can see a speech outline I drafted. Everything about it, from the features to the price point, makes me laugh now.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>More than being an Apple fan, though, I also generally love technology and the gadgets it demands. Considering that my day job almost entirely relies on my skills and expertise in designing apps and experiences on these devices, keeping up ahead of the curve is almost mandatory.</p>
<h2 id="the-upgrading-dilemma">The upgrading dilemma</h2>
<p>Then there is the minimalist and fiscally-conscious part of me.</p>
<p>To that end, I have a framework for when I upgrade my devices:</p>
<ul>
<li>Is the device is on the verge of death?</li>
<li>Are there workarounds to pull the device back from the brink?</li>
<li>Is there is a feature on the upgrade I absolutely can’t not have?</li>
</ul>
<p>In March 2017, when my iPhone 6 fell with me into the water while I was kayaking and died an instant death, I used a loaner Android unit until the iPhone X got released.</p>
<p>And even then! I waited a whole month and a half to actually get the device, if my receipt trails are to be believed, since I only got it on December 21 of that same year.</p>
<h2 id="why-im-thinking-of-upgrading">Why I’m thinking of upgrading</h2>
<p>Recently, my iPhone X has been giving me plenty of usage problems — It goes from 100% to 10% in about 20 minutes when all I’m doing is listening to a podcast, or have the Libby app open. It also overheats, sometimes for no reason at all.</p>
<p>The most worrying incident happened about two weeks ago, when it died almost instantly as I unplugged it from its cable. When I eventually – harrowingly – got it to switch on again, a service notice tells me that the phone “experienced an unexpected shutdown because the battery was unable to deliver the necessary peak power”.</p>
<p>I’m not sure what it meant technically, but it also assured me it would not happen again.</p>
<p>So, my interest was piqued when Apple announced the new lineup of the phones.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Another story! When the iPhone 8 and iPhone X was released, I was part of the team at work who had to be in the office at 3 in the morning to receive the specs and images from Apple, when we then updated our page – typically the page with the most traffic all year round. Fun times.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>But here’s the brief rundown: My initial reaction was one of overwhelm, at the similar sounding model names.</p>
<p>Then I’m just underwhelmed.</p>
<h2 id="and-thats-why-im-not-upgrading">And… that’s why I’m not upgrading</h2>
<p>To make things easier for myself, let’s go back to my framework of upgrading my device.</p>
<p><strong>Is the device is on the verge of death?</strong></p>
<p>Yes, very much so. I can’t keep relying on my external power bank, especially if I’m just going out for a quick grocery run or an actual walk, so this is mission critical for me.</p>
<p><strong>Are there workarounds to pull the device back from the brink?</strong></p>
<p>Two, actually: I can get a new battery replacement for $99, or I can get a smart battery case for $199. Compared to $1,299 for the base iPhone 12 model, those seem like a steal.</p>
<p><strong>Is there is a feature on the upgrade I absolutely can’t not have?</strong></p>
<p>Some of the biggest updates on the new iPhones are a little exciting, I won’t pretend they aren’t — Higher quality photos and videos are always appreciated; I like the sound of 5G speeds, but I’m hooked up to my wifi anyway while working from home; and more efficient charging so I can find new ways to fuck up my new battery, probably. (I kid.)</p>
<p>At the end of the day, though, my iPhone X still serves all my needs. I’m content with the speed that I can use my apps to read, listen to music and podcasts, and play my games. I’m still largely a content consumer than a content creator, much less one who needs the latest and greatest photo and video taking abilities — and even then, I would assume I’ll need more specific tools for those at a more advanced stage, and that the iPhone X still has the capacity for that at my basic entry level!</p>
<p>Yeah. I guess I’ll hold on for a few more cycles.</p>
<hr>
<p>(There’s also a metaphor here, about my own mental battery and my own surge capacity being so messed up. Can someone replace <em>my</em> battery? Anyone?)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Non-Definitive Guide To Starting A New Job</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/new-job/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2020 20:11:51 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/new-job/</guid>
      <description>I’ve switched jobs — not counting freelance and contract work — twice in my career.
Three times, now, once I start my new job on Monday. My last day at my previous employee was Friday, so you can say that I love cutting things close.
Now, clearly this is an occupational hazard, but a UXer’s gotta UX, you know? So I’ve cobbled together some objectives I want to test out for my new job.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’ve switched jobs — not counting freelance and contract work — twice in my career.</p>
<p>Three times, now, once I start my new job on Monday. My last day at my previous employee was Friday, so you can say that I love cutting things close.</p>
<p>Now, clearly this is an occupational hazard, but a UXer’s gotta UX, you know? So I’ve cobbled together some objectives I want to test out for my new job.</p>
<h2 id="schedule-regular-one-on-one-catch-ups-with-the-manager">Schedule regular one-on-one catch-ups with the manager</h2>
<p>This should probably be self-explanatory.</p>
<p>Earlier in my career, I was more than happy to shy away from these, believing that my work would speak for itself.</p>
<p>Obviously, that’s a naive belief.</p>
<p>I’ve also had managers who were too busy, and these sessions usually got pushed and postponed and eventually, canceled. I’ll have to figure out what to do if this situation happens again, but fingers crossed it wouldn’t!</p>
<p><strong>The plan:</strong> Schedule weekly check-ins (at least for the first month), set expectations, and check in often to see if I’m missing the mark.</p>
<p>We go around recommending the notion of launching fast and failing fast, so why not translate that for my own development?</p>
<h2 id="get-to-proactively-know-my-new-colleagues">Get to proactively know my new colleagues</h2>
<p>I’m a textbook introvert, and some days, I’d rather be at my desk, hunkering down on the actual work. Not to the point of being anti-social, but I’m definitely more charming on a one-on-one basis than a group of more than 30 people, staring expectantly at me.</p>
<p><strong>The plan:</strong> Have lunch/coffee with at least one new person every week, unless I’m away in a project/agile team. And even then! The team will be new to me and vice versa, so it will be helpful for everyone.</p>
<p>The 2019-nCoV might hinder this plan if things keep escalating. We’ll see, though! I’ll still try my best.</p>
<p>This leads in nicely to…</p>
<h2 id="find-mentors">Find mentors</h2>
<p>One glaring thing that I’ve definitely lacked in my previous jobs was diversifying the mentorship I was getting.</p>
<p>I haven’t really branched out beyond direct management, even though I’ve always meant to find mentors outside of my team.</p>
<p><strong>The plan:</strong> Identify at least three mentors within the organization, and see how I can help them with their own goals and metrics.</p>
<p>So, there’s that to cover for the first quarter. There will be plenty to learn as I try to hit the ground running, but it’ll be a fun adventure nonetheless.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On digital clutter and hoarding</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/hoarding/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2020 20:12:36 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/hoarding/</guid>
      <description>I once told a friend that I would love to just own 50 items. Because, of course, my self-worth is tied up in the number of things I possess. I kid, but it’s true that I don’t have a lot of things.
What I do have, though, is digital clutter.
Oh, so many photos and videos and documents accumulated over the last 13 years as a Mac user. These are files that are dutifully backed up both over the cloud (Dropbox, for now) and on a hard drive (although it tells me it has been 183 days since I’ve last hooked that up ); these are configurations that have been Migration Assisted through the machines that have gone through the years with me.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I once told a friend that I would love to just own 50 items. Because, of course, my self-worth is tied up in the number of things I possess. I kid, but it’s true that I don’t have a lot of things.</p>
<p>What I do have, though, is digital clutter.</p>
<p>Oh, so many photos and videos and documents accumulated over the last 13 years as a Mac user. These are files that are dutifully backed up both over the cloud (Dropbox, for now) and on a hard drive (although it tells me it has been 183 days since I’ve last hooked that up ); these are configurations that have been Migration Assisted through the machines that have gone through the years with me.</p>
<p>I run a tighter ship on my email: There’s one email in my inbox, and that’s for a gift card that I haven’t yet used. Except, click on ‘All Mail’ and you’ll see that’s one email out of 18,391.</p>
<p>Switch to the Photos app, and you can see where things get a little out of control, with multiple shots of the same things.</p>
<p>Am I a digital hoarder? I wondered aloud, looking at screenshots from the year 2009, still neatly sitting in a folder.</p>
<p>Hoarding, of course, is a behavioral pattern that manifests in the unwillingness to discard objects, and the ensuing distress if someone is made to do so. It needs no introduction; we’ve all seen clips of <em>Hoarders</em> and Marie Kondo trying her best to help the people featured on her show.</p>
<p>My older sister is ruthless in throwing things away, while I have the tendency to be too sentimental. My mom, on the other hand, keeps CDs and books and magazines from the ’90s and ’00s, and my father, keeps annual reports from decades ago, “just in case”.</p>
<p>Yet, judging from our shared Google Photos folder of <a href="https://www.instagram.com/jie.ce"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >my nephews</a>, my sister has plenty of photos and videos of the two little munchkins. In a complete turn of events, I have helped my mom deleted every single text she has ever received on her phone. My dad also has terrible luck with devices, and has had to completely reinstall iOS at least twice, without backups.</p>
<p>So, it would seem that they are both fine with not having backups of their digital assets, or even having any at all.</p>
<p>Honestly? Much to think about and reflect on why I think I would have a mini anxiety attack if the content on my phone and all my backups were lost.</p>
<h3 id="i-pictures--videos">i. Pictures &amp; videos</h3>
<p>In 2017, I fell in the river kayaking, taking my iPhone 6 down with me. For 9 months, I used a loaned Android, with a camera that was bad, even by 2017 standards. Case in point: <a href="https://jalyn.co/wp-content/uploads/so-pale-i-should-be-translucent-scaled-e1578733184710.jpg"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >Here is a photo of me, taken on that phone, post-kayaking.</a> (I know, I know.)</p>
<p>With the quality of photos and videos, paired with an abundance of storage space on your device, it can be easy to forget about just how many photos we’ve accumulated over the years.</p>
<p>By the time I had deleted pictures that were no longer relevant – this included screenshots, random shots of dogs being walked on the street, and merchandise with pandas on them — I had 8 pictures left. To compare, I ended 2016 with 75 pictures.</p>
<p>Does that mean I had a less exciting year in 2017 than 2016? I had chicken pox in 2016 and I fell into a river in 2017, so I think you can say that they were both on par.</p>
<p>Still, the top reason I can even put time stamps on the two incidents is because of the photos I had taken, perfectly archived in a handy app on the phone. But photos aren’t memories, as much as they are a great way to create a digital time capsule; I’m trying to be mindful of that these days.</p>
<h3 id="ii-emails">ii. Emails</h3>
<p>I remember when Gmail launched, with so many people thinking it was an April Fool’s joke because of the 1 GB mailbox limit. Back in the day (I’m old enough to use that as a phrase, apparently), my trusted Hotmail limit was a whooping 2 MB limit. A quick check on Google (irony!) also leads me to <a href="http://www.dslreports.com/shownews/Yahoo-Raises-Mailbox-Limits-45865"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >this article, where Yahoo! boasted a 100 MB inbox</a>.</p>
<p>I’ve been using Unroll.Me since 2017; the service quietly and (mostly) efficiently filtering out all the sales pitches and newsletters and general emailers into a folder where I don’t get notified of their regal presence. Since starting on the journey to digital minimalism, I’ve been trying to mass delete emails (thank you, Gmail’s filtering mechanism) and unsubscribe from as many things as I can.</p>
<p>This is definitely a work in progress, though! I’ve managed to cut the 18k+ emails to nearly 4,300 emails right now. These emails take up 1.29 GB, according to Google, and I would like to see that go down more.</p>
<p>It’s not bad, though, considering that’s more than 10 years’ worth of emails!</p>
<h3 id="iii-cloud-storage">iii. Cloud storage</h3>
<p>To be perfectly honest, this is the reason why I even started thinking about digital minimalism in the first place. I have a Dropbox Plus (2 TB) subscription that is running out early next month. I first subscribed to that in 2015, when it was known as Dropbox Pro with a 1 TB limit.</p>
<p>At that time, it felt reasonable to shell out around $135 (US$99) for that space — I have plenty of source files since I’d started freelancing in 2008, and over the decade this repository has grown to a pretty enormous size.</p>
<p>Fast forward to now, with my smooth transition from a pure visual/brand designer to an experience designer — I no longer deal with Photoshop files upwards of 500 MB each, when everything I work on is either lightweight enough, or already in the cloud.</p>
<p>I have a folder called Portfolio, which — and you might be surprised to hear — contained branch folders labeled by the years I’ve explored job opportunities. It goes:</p>
<ul>
<li>2010 (3.3 GB)</li>
<li>2011 (2.4 GB)</li>
<li>2012 (3.22 GB)</li>
<li>2014 (147.1 MB)</li>
<li>2016 (97.3 MB)</li>
<li>2018 (665.4 MB)</li>
</ul>
<p>I really wish my 2018 folder could’ve followed the narrative, but alas, it contains super high-res images and photos. So that skewed my hypothesis a little, but my point remains about the type of files I handle.</p>
<p>The rest of the files in Dropbox utilizing that initial 1 TB storage were backups of photos and videos thanks to the nifty Camera Uploads folder that automatically does that for you, media (books, movies, TV shows… things I probably shouldn’t be admitting to that here ), and additional backups from previous work places.</p>
<p>I’ve since cleared most of it, in anticipation of switching over to Google One. Originally I’d thought that a purchase of the 100 GB plan (~$28, or ~US$20) was necessary, with after deleting more than 60,000 files, I’m clocking in at around 14 GB in total. I have a 19 GB limit in my Google Drive, so we shall see. Maybe I’ll continue to pare down and hold out on purchasing a bigger storage space.</p>
<p>As Parkinson’s Law states, “work expands so as to fill the time available for its completion.” Maybe it works tangentially for clutter as well — “stuff increases so as to fill the space available for its storage.”</p>
<h3 id="iv-bookmarks">iv. Bookmarks</h3>
<p>I gave up on this and shoved everything into a “Pre-2020” folder.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beginnings</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/beginnings/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2019 16:55:46 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/beginnings/</guid>
      <description>I want to start a blog.
This has been something that has been on my mind for the past ten years, although if I’m being honest with myself (and that’s the goal here!), it has definitely been something I’ve thought of for way longer than the last decade.
I’ve flirted with Blogger as a teen, painstakingly linking my high school friends’ blogs in the sidebar and refreshing each of them daily, before I discovered RSS (and before it faded away).</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I want to start a blog.</p>
<p>This has been something that has been on my mind for the past ten years, although if I’m being honest with myself (and that’s the goal here!), it has definitely been something I’ve thought of for way longer than the last decade.</p>
<p>I’ve flirted with Blogger as a teen, painstakingly linking my high school friends’ blogs in the sidebar and refreshing each of them daily, before I discovered RSS (and before it faded away). I had a carefully curated LiveJournal about my favorite TV shows and films and music, and for a few years, it was such a big part of my life online.</p>
<p>I’d even installed easily a dozen or so WordPress blogs when I started freelancing as a web designer when I was 18, and created endless mental reminders for myself to get the ball rolling on one myself when the blogs I was reading shifted into the mainstream.</p>
<p>Yet, the daunting expectations of being consistent in writing and putting something out into the world, coupled with the imposter syndrome of feeling like my thoughts aren’t worthy enough of documentation gave me pause in my steps towards doing just that.</p>
<p>There isn’t really a grand plan or strategy in place for this little corner of the internet I’m parking myself in, though. Plenty of things and conversations I want to have with people, and it would probably reflect the intersections of my life, my values, and things I find interesting.</p>
<p>More likely than not, it would chronicle my journey in optimizing my life, my path to financial independence, my attempts at intentionality and minimalism, and my lifelong pursuit of fitness (both physical and mental!).</p>
<p>I want to start a blog, and so, as a new year and decade begins – here I am.</p>
<p>Hello, world!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
