<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Year in Review on Jalyn Cai</title>
    <link>https://jalyncai.com/tags/year-in-review/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Year in Review on Jalyn Cai</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2025 15:47:33 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jalyncai.com/tags/year-in-review/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>2024: Year in review</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/2024-year-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2025 15:47:33 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/2024-year-in-review/</guid>
      <description>I’d started writing this on the first day of the new year, as has been my tradition since 2020, but my ceiling started leaking. I’m really hoping that it isn’t a harbinger of things to come in 2025.
Onward!
What went well Strength: If you know me, you know I’ve struggled with fitness my entire life: issues with my lower back, my lungs, a self-imposed limiting belief that I’m “just not athletic”.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’d started writing this on the first day of the new year, as has been my tradition since 2020, but my ceiling started leaking. I’m really hoping that it isn’t a harbinger of things to come in 2025.</p>
<p>Onward!</p>
<h2 id="what-went-well">What went well</h2>
<p><strong>Strength:</strong> If you know me, you know I’ve struggled with fitness my entire life: issues with my lower back, my lungs, a self-imposed limiting belief that I’m “just not athletic”.</p>
<p>But with great aplomb (and a drum roll, please): I lost ~13% of myself in 2024! My InBody scale tells me nearly all of it was fat loss, and I’m not about to argue with it.</p>
<p>This was a combination of nutrition, the 160 workouts I did — approximately one workout every 2.28 days — and physical therapy exercises for my back, which left me feeling lighter and stronger than ever.</p>
<p>A major breakthrough was finally cracking the cardio code: daily treadmill walks for 45 minutes — while reading on my Kindle (important! I look forward to these treadmill sessions because of this).</p>
<p>On the food intake end, my concept of <em>minimal viable protein</em> served me well for days that are both typical, and not (traveling, for example).</p>
<p>Lastly, I addressed loose ends (i.e. fixing my infected implant, getting a cyst on my scalp removed, being better at skincare and sunscreen application, etc etc.)</p>
<p>—</p>
<p><strong>Alignment:</strong> This has been a transformative year internally. A recurring theme in past yearly reviews had been about work, and how much that had vexed me. Those alone should’ve raised alarm bells, but I ignored them, year after year.</p>
<p>In the second half of the year, something clicked: it wasn’t finding another job in the corporate world, nor was it climbing the ladder and losing even more of myself in the process.</p>
<p>Instead, I started examining what my skills (design, operations, strategy) could create impact, beyond the confines of corporate structures.</p>
<p>That’s when the idea of turning the design process inward came, using it to fuel personal development and growth. From this emerged the concept of being a <em>full stack being</em>, centered on building strength, thinking, alignment, connection and knowledge.</p>
<p>This shift transformed my focus from merely staying afloat as a design leader in a consultancy, to writing and using design as a vehicle for exploration and experimentation. It’s a move beyond delivering user flows, screens, and slide after slide of a “UX strategy” destined to be dismissed.</p>
<p>(Can you feel my burnout and jadedness of the craft?)</p>
<p>So far, I’ve launched a newsletter, and an Instagram exploring this concept.</p>
<p>But more on these in the months ahead :)</p>
<p><strong>New skills:</strong> Like my GMAT exam on the day before a year-end trip last year, 2024 repeated that pattern with my driving license (though it was planned to be earlier in November, but I had failed the first attempt). I’m now able to legally terrorize the streets!</p>
<p>I also took on side quests that I hadn’t planned on, with skiing, learning Spanish, and playing chess as my top three highlights of skills acquired. They weren’t part of a grand plan, but they brought me joy and are stark reminders that staying curious and open are my core values.</p>
<p><strong>More traveling:</strong> I zipped around a fair bit: Germany, Austria, The Philippines, The UK, France, Malaysia, then finally to China. It’s a cliche, but I truly do love it.</p>
<h2 id="what-couldve-gone-better">What could’ve gone better</h2>
<p><strong>Improving focus and reducing screen time:</strong> This isn’t an uncommon issue amongst the chronically online. I found myself reaching for my phone, doom scrolling through social media and Reddit, even though I <em>know</em> I should be doing anything else instead.</p>
<p>Case in point: I just wasted 15 minutes scrolling through YouTube shorts. YouTube shorts! How did I even get there?!</p>
<p>Screen time was abysmal; huge chunks of hours without me even realizing it. I’ve put in a few guardrails, like using greyscale mode and setting time limits, but it’s clear I ned more deliberate approaches.</p>
<p>The lack of focus connects to a larger problem: avoiding discomfort and boredom. Recognizing it is half the battle (I hope!) and now it’ll be about sitting with these feelings and finding alternatives.</p>
<p>—</p>
<p><strong>Speed in decision making:</strong> A pattern of overthinking and analysis paralysis underpins this, and ends up with me wasting time by not moving forward and getting stuck in loops.</p>
<p>Or maybe it’s the perfectionist streak in me, with unrealistic expectations of how fast things should move. We’ll unpack this a lot more in 2025, I hope!</p>
<p>—</p>
<p><strong>Managing anxiety more effectively:</strong> I am, by default, wrought with anxiety. It’s basically background noise to me now. I’ve been trying all the usual tricks — meditating, journaling, working out — but there is a baseline that I return to.</p>
<p>Then there were the things I was excessively anxious about: the layoffs in the company, how my teammates were coping, my financial situation in the case that it drops on me.</p>
<p>But I learned an important lesson here: no amount of anxiety makes any difference to anything that is going to happen. Instead, I want to try and shift my focus on the things that are going to move the needle, and converting that into something constructive instead.</p>
<h2 id="themes-from-my-gratitude-journal">Themes from my gratitude journal</h2>
<ul>
<li>Having the time and space to think and experiment</li>
<li>Traveling and exploring new places</li>
<li>The nephews being happy; spending time with them</li>
<li>Doing new things that scare me</li>
<li>Being excited about life again</li>
<li>Doing things that brought joy</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="what-i-want-to-do-in-2025">What I want to do in 2025</h2>
<h3 id="strength">Strength</h3>
<ul>
<li>Feel lighter and more energetic</li>
<li>Get technically better at skiing</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="thinking">Thinking:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Let go of the scarcity mindset and internalize that “investing in yourself is not a waste</li>
<li>Reduce phone usage as default for boredom</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="alignment">Alignment</h3>
<ul>
<li>Build the full stack life in public</li>
<li>Redefine what good enough work and great work look like outside the corporate world</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="connection">Connection</h3>
<ul>
<li>More solo traveling</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="knowledge">Knowledge</h3>
<ul>
<li>Consistently learn how to play the guitar</li>
<li>Leave space for side quests</li>
</ul>
<p>I’m hopeful that the theme of 2025 is one of exploration, and giving myself permission to wander off the main path of conventions and expectations.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2023: Year in review</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/2023-year-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 19:53:50 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/2023-year-in-review/</guid>
      <description>Once again, I’m looking back on the year that’s passed. (See: 2020, 2021, 2022)
It seems a little tougher this year — and I won’t say whether it’s because I haven’t been consistently and habitually writing on this site — but I’m always happy to reflect and introspect on what has gone well and what I could’ve done better with.
What went well: Learning and growth: Last year, one of my goals was to try and figure out whether to take my MBA aspiration more seriously.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Once again, I’m looking back on the year that’s passed. (See: <a href="/2020-year-in-review"  >2020</a>, <a href="/2021-year-in-review"  >2021</a>, <a href="/2022-year-in-review"  >2022</a>)</p>
<p>It seems a little tougher this year — and I won’t say whether it’s because I haven’t been consistently and habitually writing on this site — but I’m always happy to reflect and introspect on what has gone well and what I could’ve done better with.</p>
<h2 id="what-went-well">What went well:</h2>
<p><strong>Learning and growth:</strong> Last year, one of my goals was to try and figure out whether to take my MBA aspiration more seriously. To that end, one of the hurdles was taking the GMAT. After some on-off studying for half a year, I scored a 645 on the GMAT Focus, which clears that 700 barrier on the classic GMAT.</p>
<p>It’s a score that I’m pleased with (and proud of, considering I hadn’t taken a standardized test for more than half my life at this point), but it is also a score that I think I <em><strong>can</strong></em> improve on if I studied and grinded for a little longer. I haven’t started doing that, but maybe — let’s see where I’m at with applications in Q1 of this year.</p>
<p><strong>Reading:</strong> Surprisingly, even with studying taking up all/most of my free time, I still managed to read 25 books in 2023. The last book that I read was <em><strong>The First Fifteen Lives of Harry August</strong></em>, and oh, boy. One of my favorite books is <strong>Replay</strong>, which deals with a Groundhog Day situation but with an entire life (almost), and <strong>Harry August</strong> turned that up a notch. I might re-read it now.</p>
<p><strong>Traveling:</strong> This was almost a given, given how we’re recovering from the pandemic and figuring out what that looks like with traveling. I’ve not traveled as much as I wanted to as an adult, so I’m happy to get back into this and train this muscle of experiencing other cultures, environments, and weathers.</p>
<p><strong>New hobbies:</strong> I’m slowly getting into completely new things, like appreciating matcha (and the art of making a cup), and watches (I got a Seiko Presage in Tokyo, and it’s one of my favorite purchases). On the other hand, I’m also… (Author’s note: I forgot where I was going with this, and left this dangling.)</p>
<h2 id="what-couldve-gone-better">What could’ve gone better:</h2>
<p><strong>Fitness and health:</strong> Sigh. With the stress of studying, fitness got wildly deprioritized. Even then, I managed 116 workouts in 2023 — nearly 1 in 3 days, which is a complete shock to me as I spent all of December not working out at all. Definitely something to push on in 2024!</p>
<p>I’ve also spent most of the day in a haze; my asthma coming back the last week of the year.</p>
<p><strong>Finance:</strong> I only hit a 59% savings rate. I don’t know — can I partially justify that by saying I didn’t get a raise (not even a salary adjustment to inflation) this year? I don’t <strong>regret</strong> making the purchases, though.</p>
<p><strong>Work:</strong> Ah, something that is a mainstay through the years. It’s a pattern that I don’t like, but it’s not something I can shake easily. In 2023, my corporate life was rocked a little by layoffs and restructuring, and though I kept my job and stepped (the fuck) up to several positions beyond me, it’s been a mostly thankless endeavor and I’ve even got my promotion case denied, so…</p>
<p>I guess I’m evaluating a lot about what work, and this workplace, means to me. There is some cognitive dissonance here with my pursuit of a potential MBA, given the implication of working hard and elevating myself career-wise. But we’ll see.</p>
<h2 id="themes-from-my-gratitude-journal">Themes from my gratitude journal:</h2>
<ul>
<li>Space for me to try my best</li>
<li>My nephews being happy</li>
<li>Being excited about possibilities</li>
<li>Time away to travel and think</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="what-i-want-to-do-in-2024">What I want to do in 2024:</h2>
<ul>
<li>Learn to drive and obtain my license</li>
<li>Apply for and get admitted to an MBA program</li>
<li>Evolve my style beyond Uniqlo and t-shirts</li>
<li>Travel even more (this is shaping up quite excitingly with a trip to Germany/Austria in January!)</li>
<li>Figuring out my skincare routine</li>
</ul>
<p>As always, I hope the next 365 days (leap year!) are going to be kind and good to all of us.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2022: Year in Review</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/2022-year-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 20:11:25 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/2022-year-in-review/</guid>
      <description>It’s become a habit now; a yearly one, to look back on the year that has passed and reflect on what has gone well and what could’ve gone better (see: 2021, 2020). My writing is rusty now, with my non-rigour and letting my habit die off this year.
2022 has been a mixed bag of blessings and regrets, and of going on auto-pilot and letting things fall on the wayside.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It’s become a habit now; a yearly one, to look back on the year that has passed and reflect on what has gone well and what could’ve gone better (see: <a href="/2021-year-in-review"  >2021</a>, <a href="/2020-year-in-review"  >2020</a>). My writing is rusty now, with my non-rigour and letting my habit die off this year.</p>
<p>2022 has been a mixed bag of blessings and regrets, and of going on auto-pilot and letting things fall on the wayside.</p>
<h2 id="what-went-well">What went well:</h2>
<p><strong>Fitness:</strong> This is separate from health, for reasons we’ll go into in the <em>what could’ve gone better</em> section</p>
<p>This year, I got a gym membership in March, and then in July, a personal trainer. I ended up with 75 sessions in total, which comes up to around a session every 3.8 days. My main drive for going to the gym is to get stronger — something that is a little hard to do as I can’t consistently overload because of my <a href="/spondy"  >Back Situation™</a>.</p>
<p>I hit several PRs in the last two sessions of the year — made possible only because I ate at maintenance for these last two weeks; I’m in a deficit otherwise. PRs make me feel like I’m unlocking achievements, but I know it’s a really unpredictable road that I’m on, and I’m still learning how to accept my limitations.</p>
<p>My weakest exercises definitely have to do with my back and core, which are… important, you know, to the general anatomy.</p>
<p>But also: I meal prepped for the majority of the year, and was a little more consistent with my meal timings! I’ll take that as a W.</p>
<p><strong>Finance</strong>: My savings rate dropped to 63% this year, from my target of 70%. Yet — I’m at peace with it, since I’m <a href="/frugal"  >trading money for my health and fitness</a>. The hugest chunk of money went to aforementioned personal training sessions, as well as physiotherapy sessions which was an unexpected expense, and insurance only covered a minuscule part of it.</p>
<p>I also finally upgraded my iPhone X to a 14 Pro! Other than that, I didn’t travel this year at all, and kept to my yearly budget in all other categories.</p>
<p><strong>Relationships and connections</strong>: I got much closer to a few work-buddies-elevated-to-friends, and I’m glad to have forged these friendships as I surround myself with people who inspire me and push me to be better.</p>
<p><strong>Hair</strong>: <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/CZ_9fkCvOUx/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >I got it cut!</a></p>
<h2 id="what-couldve-gone-better">What could’ve gone better:</h2>
<p>Probably everything else.</p>
<p><strong>Health</strong>: I have had back problems for a few years now, and in April I decided that I wanted to get a referral letter from my general practitioner so that I could go to a physio and go on my merry ways, with a few easy exercises that would fix it once and for all.</p>
<p>Except that’s not how it went. The visit to the doctor spawned a few radiography sessions, with X-rays and MRIs, and instead of a simple referral to a physio, I was referred to a neurosurgeon. Turns out, the back issue isn’t just bad posture and a lack of working out. Instead, I have spondylolysis and spondylolisthesis, which could have an even more significant decrease in my quality of life at some point.</p>
<p>Aside from that, in these last two weeks of the year, I got a cold that just wouldn’t go away, with a cough that I couldn’t manage at all. This cough would make my throat spasm uncontrollably, to the point of gagging and throwing up. A visit to the doctor (after two weeks of resisting it — I know, I know) brought up the hypothesis that my asthma is back — the last time was when I was 7, I think — and I’m going to have to monitor it and see how it goes.</p>
<p>And then, to top it all off — a trip to the dentist confirmed that my implant site (of my left bottom molar) has significant bone loss, and necessitates more visits to the specialist. I foresee this to be the budget killer in 2023.</p>
<p><strong>Work</strong>: It’s not hyperbole to say that I over-indexed on work this year, and ended up making everybody else’s priorities my worry.</p>
<p>My work day generally starts around 8:30am, and on some days they end at 11pm. This is, as anyone would know, completely unsustainable. A lot of the late night meetings are because of the leadership program I’m in, and it definitely doesn’t feel like the outputs and outcomes match the amount of effort and time I put into it. I’m still trying to figure out how to properly balance this without me accelerating the burnout that I can see coming.</p>
<p>I also worked too many weekends, and even started dreaming about doing work — as in, Figma is open and I’m staring at a screen in my dream. The worst thing about this is that I’ll wake up and the work isn’t magically actually done.</p>
<p>There was also a lot of angst and anger around some things at work, and these are things out of my direct control. I got extremely reactive to things happening, and then that makes me even more annoyed and angry because theoretically I know that I am the only thing I can control, and I’m definitely not doing that.</p>
<p>Even in this last week of the year, while the office is closed down, I’m still logging hours and having to review work, send out emails, and still generally not being able to fully unplug. This is probably going to be extremely detrimental as I head back in next week, unrested, and I’m not looking forward to it.</p>
<p><strong>Reading</strong>: Did I reach my reading challenge? Yes. Did I leave it til the last possible weeks to cram half of it in, despite the goal being halved from last year? Also yes.</p>
<p>I seriously contemplated that I should aim for 90 books in 2023, since I was going to cram with whatever I target.</p>
<p>My friends do not think it’s funny.</p>
<p><strong>Writing</strong>: It’s been an abysmal year, both writing on this blog, and also writing fiction in general. Of all the habits and priorities, I have definitely let this slide the most. I’m hopeful that 2023 will allow me the time and grace to pick this back up again in a more consistent fashion.</p>
<p>I also want to write more long-form content, both around my craft specialties (UX and product design, leadership amongst others), as well as more helpful and actionable content for my non-work interests, like productivity and minimalism.</p>
<p><strong>Hobbies and skills</strong>: Sadly to say, I didn’t pick up anything new in 2022.</p>
<p>I did continue my habits of daily meditating and daily journaling, and continued with playing poker, and actually downloading apps for Sudoku and Chinese chess towards the later part of the year.</p>
<p>Other than that, I abandoned learning/refreshing my Javascript skills pretty early.</p>
<h2 id="themes-from-my-gratitude-journal">Themes from my gratitude journal:</h2>
<ul>
<li>Great food with great friends</li>
<li>Opportunities to try things</li>
<li>Having time to rest / weekends / days off</li>
<li>Agency to do what I want, to some degree</li>
<li>Ability to do hard work</li>
<li>My nephews expressing their affections / witnessing my nephews playing with dogs</li>
<li>Projects ending</li>
</ul>
<p>I’ve also neglected this gratitude journal and left it blank more often than not. That’s something I really want to improve on.</p>
<h2 id="what-i-want-to-do-next-year">What I want to do next year:</h2>
<p>I’m just going to list things down, and maybe in a year’s time we’ll see how accountable I’ve held myself with these:</p>
<ul>
<li>Expand my music listening so I’m not listening to the same 20 songs all year round</li>
<li>Take learning programming more seriously
<ul>
<li>Change my tech stack for my portfolio and blog — they’re running on WordPress now, which is too chunky for what I want it to do. I want to see if I can run it off Notion as a database, but my knowledge and expertise isn’t at a level where I can do that easily</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Take my MBA dream more seriously and see if it’s worth it + prepare for it if it is</li>
<li>Make more mentor relationships</li>
<li>Learn driving?</li>
<li>Finally learn guitar for real?</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>As always, I hope the next 364 days ahead are safe and happy for everyone.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2021: Year in Review</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/2021-year-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 15:57:49 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/2021-year-in-review/</guid>
      <description>I like having a chill and quiet last day of the year, and I was ready to spend the whole of this last day of the year writing this, just as I had done last year.
Instead, my laptop wouldn’t start up when I woke up yesterday morning — seemed emblematic of 2021’s vibes — and I spent half the day going to a couple of repair shops, receiving the bad news about a corroded motherboard, balking at the price for repair, trying to make the call on whether I should just buy a new MacBook Air/Pro and let this 2017 laptop’s value after amortization be higher than I anticipated…</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I like having a chill and quiet last day of the year, and I was ready to spend the whole of this last day of the year writing this, just as I had done <a href="/2020-year-in-review"  >last year</a>.</p>
<p>Instead, my laptop wouldn’t start up when I woke up yesterday morning — seemed emblematic of 2021’s vibes — and I spent half the day going to a couple of repair shops, receiving the bad news about a corroded motherboard, balking at the price for repair, trying to make the call on whether I should just buy a new MacBook Air/Pro and let this 2017 laptop’s value after amortization be higher than I anticipated…</p>
<p>Eventually I settled on spending the repair money, because I feel like I’ll be able to stretch the lifespan out a little more and get a better value over time. Plus, I’ll be able to comfortably wait for the <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/guide/2022-macbook-air/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >M2 MacBook Air</a> when it comes out too.</p>
<p>But yes. That’s 2021 in a nutshell, I think: something happens and I react, and I push all previously-laid plans aside. Including having to write this post in the new year instead!</p>
<h2 id="what-went-well">What went well:</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Money:</strong> Before the laptop fiasco, I was locking in an 70% savings rate. This is going to be my third full year of pursuing FIRE (or at least the FI part of things), and I’m well on track, so that makes me happy. With the repair costs hastily calculated in, I’m down a couple of percents, but all in all it’s still below my budgeted expenses of the year.</li>
<li><strong>Work</strong>: I had so much to talk about during my impact discussion, which was further bolstered by my colleagues’ really kind feedback and words for my improvement. There was also the matter of getting into the Next Generation Leadership Team (<a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/CXi6VawgxuO/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >second slide in this post!</a>) when I didn’t think I would.</li>
<li><strong>Writing:</strong> This is threefold — I wrote a post here every week for a year (minus the weird month last month that I paused), wrote 2 journal entries every day (one for a more regular recap, and another with Day One’s daily prompts), and also wrote a few pieces of fic which I’m proud of, because I’d never done that for my ride-or-die fandom despite being in it for nearly a decade now.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="what-couldve-gone-better">What could’ve gone better:</h2>
<ul>
<li>Everything about my <strong>health</strong>, including:
<ul>
<li>My eating habits — timing, quantity, and quality;</li>
<li>Working out — I won’t blame it on the vaccines, but I turned “no strenuous activity for 2 weeks” into much longer;</li>
<li>Hitting my daily step count — some time around June I said fuck it to 10k a day, scaled it down to 5k, <em>and</em> then had trouble hitting those</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Reading</strong>: <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/user_challenges/24940419"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >I did it.</a> I did 60 books. I’m not proud of it, because I speed-read the fuck out of those last 15 books and let’s just say I do <em>not</em> want to do it again, so this year? This year I’m going to slow down, and read just “enough”.</li>
<li><strong>Skills:</strong> Did not learn a new language. Or calligraphy. Picked up a couple of Thai swear words though, does that count?</li>
<li><strong>Mentality</strong>: I heard it over and over again from my colleagues and friends — stop being so hard on yourself.</li>
<li><strong>Money:</strong> Even though I’d talked about all the good stuff with money in the previous section, one thing did make me feel slightly embarrassed: in-app purchases for chips in my poker games. It’s illegal in Singapore to gamble online, so I was just frivolously spending real money in exchange for fake money.Luckily (and this is a huge luckily), the support team accidentally unlinked my account and I can’t access that anymore, which made my refund requests to Apple legitimate when I did it after 2 weeks of no response from said support team.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="other-stuff">Other stuff:</h2>
<ul>
<li>I met some pretty cool people this year, and I’m thankful to have crossed paths with them and looking forward to forging even tighter friendships going forward!</li>
<li>2021’s major learning-in-a-structured-manner was the <a href="/learning-harder"  >d.MBA</a>, and I’m itching to apply that knowledge to actual work.</li>
<li>2021 was also my second year of meditating every morning</li>
<li>Got extremely into poker near the end of October — thanks to Maria Konnikova’s <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/49814228-the-biggest-bluff"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" ><em>The Biggest Bluff</em></a> — and while I’ve just been playing it online (with fake stakes), I think I might consider taking a vacation somewhere and playing some super low stakes games in person.</li>
<li>Getting to be <a href="https://adplist.org/mentors/jalyn-cai"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >a mentor on ADPList</a> had been really fulfilling, though really time-consuming! Alas, I think I’m no longer getting any traffic from the actual directory, and haven’t been getting any new bookings since… I wanna say November? So there’s that.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="themes-from-my-gratitude-journal">Themes from my gratitude journal:</h2>
<ul>
<li>My nephews being themselves</li>
<li>Being allowed [space / time ] to try/do [thing]</li>
<li>WEEKENDS</li>
<li>Working with good people</li>
<li>Good food with good people</li>
</ul>
<p>I’ve been joking that we should be very quiet about 2022 and not startle it, and the first day of the year is already rainy and dreary, so… I hope the next 364 days ahead are safe and happy for everyone</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2020: Year in Review</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/2020-year-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2020 19:21:16 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/2020-year-in-review/</guid>
      <description>Oh, 2020. A year that started out promisingly, and subsequently veered off-course about fifty million times over.
I’m one of the lucky ones – holding the privilege to hold my job and not worry about money, not having to experience the tremendous loss and the grief the pandemic brought, and living in a country where the response hasn’t been just a real life depiction of my favorite gif.
So, I’m happy to see 2020 behind us.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Oh, 2020. A year that started out promisingly, and subsequently veered off-course about fifty million times over.</p>
<p>I’m one of the lucky ones – holding the privilege to hold my job and not worry about money, not having to experience the tremendous loss and the grief the pandemic brought, and living in a country where the response hasn’t been just a real life depiction of <a href="https://media.giphy.com/media/e5kbmb3wX3J1S/giphy.gif"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >my favorite gif</a>.</p>
<p>So, I’m happy to see 2020 behind us.</p>
<h2 id="what-couldve-been-better">What could’ve been better</h2>
<p>Besides vague gestures in 2020’s general direction, I can break it down to two general buckets: physical autonomy, and mental fortitude.</p>
<p><strong>Physical autonomy</strong></p>
<p>In 2018, I injured my back, and it has never been the same ever since. I’ve gone to physical therapists and chiropractors, had scans done, and dutifully did my core exercises. Yet, nothing has helped that constant and consistent ache.</p>
<p>To exacerbate the problem, when I started working from home, I didn’t have a setup in place. I was using a kitchen chair, and sometimes when the pain of sitting up got to be too much, I would just lay down on my stomach. It worked – but at the expense of my neck (which cracks every time I turn it). Thankfully, <a href="https://www.ohlookiecookie.com/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >my</a>  <a href="https://www.siew.online/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >lovely</a>  <a href="https://www.instagram.com/facesofrow/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >friends</a> got me an office chair for my birthday, which definitely helped.</p>
<p>My strength training has plummeted too: I used to be able to squat 50kg and deadlift 65kg at the gym with barbells and plates; now 20kg dumbbells are making me doubt myself. Every twinge makes me paranoid that my body will soon crumple onto the floor.</p>
<p>It wasn’t a squat or a deadlift that caused an injury in my hip (an area that had never really hurt before) at the end of November, but an innocent sounding one-arm row. I felt something on the left of my lower body shift in a way that it shouldn’t, and immediately I literally said out loud: <em>oh fuck</em>, before I shuffled awkwardly to my bed and laid down to assess the damage done.</p>
<p>So yeah, long story short: my core strength is currently close to non-existent, and it’s giving me a real backache on top of a hypothetical headache.</p>
<p><strong>Mental fortitude</strong></p>
<p>I got frustrated – a lot – at things out of my control. I found myself annoyed at other people’s behavior, even while I kept reminding myself of the principles of stoicism and repeating <em>I am the one thing in life I can control</em> in my head.</p>
<p>I lost patience at myself more times I can count, whether it’s because of my back acting up, which also led to me screwing up my nutrition because of the old “might as well” mindset.</p>
<p>A slight burnout happened, despite me pretending it didn’t. I started a new job in February, and between trying to prove myself with a new group of colleagues, having to navigate the working-from-home situation, and adapting to really fast paced work, I didn’t want to admit that I was taking on more than I could.</p>
<h2 id="what-went-well">What went well</h2>
<p>Fun fact: I had to go hunting for my bullet journal, since I abandoned that in mid-October when I moved everything to Notion.</p>
<p><strong>Meditating once a day</strong></p>
<p>I started out with guided meditation, and now I’m just using the timer for 15 minutes every morning.</p>
<p><strong>Save 65% of income</strong></p>
<p>The numbers are officially in on this last day of the year, and it is: <strong>69.4%</strong>!</p>
<p>Of course, this is helped <em>massively</em> by the fact that I didn’t go on holiday at all, and that’s a nice chunk saved up.</p>
<p><strong>Work out twice a week</strong></p>
<p>This was like a see-saw, and on weeks when I felt well enough to, I managed to do at least two workouts a week. Right now for the past 8 weeks, I’ve been doing it six times a week, just to get myself in that routine.</p>
<p><strong>Read 52 books</strong> (58!)</p>
<p>The bulk of it happened in the last quarter of the year, but from a pure numerical standpoint, I think it’s fair to say that I hit this goal!</p>
<p><strong>5,000 steps/day</strong></p>
<p>January and February went well, with an average of 5,000 steps… and then, of course, the rest of the year happened. I didn’t pick this up until October, going for a walk in the evening. Then, when I got the Fitbit, I’ve consistently done that daily.</p>
<p><strong>Start and sustain a blog</strong></p>
<p>This has layers:</p>
<ol>
<li>I had a financial independence blog, where I was writing under a pseudonym (just because I was giving real numbers), but I’ve let that go gently into the good night when the pandemic hit. I didn’t want to flaunt numbers at a time when people were struggling, but I guess the good thing is that I can consolidate the content that I would’ve written over there as part of posts here too.</li>
<li>This blog, in which I wrote really inconsistently for the first quarter of the year, took a long break until October.</li>
</ol>
<p>Huh, I guess October gave me a kick in the ass about my goals.</p>
<p>Then there are the things that happened as the year went by:</p>
<p><strong>Playing the ukulele</strong></p>
<p><a href="https://www.instagram.com/psychhabitat/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >My friend Tanisha</a> gifted me one during the circuit breaker period, because I was trying to play my old guitar with steel strings that are really uncomfortable for my fingers. It’s gone well, and I’ve made it a habit to play at least one song every day.</p>
<p><strong>Waking up earlier</strong></p>
<p>This was a spur-of-a-moment thing, when I decided I wanted to <a href="/sleep"  >track my sleep</a>. So far, I’ve shifted my wake-up time from 8 AM to between 6:30 AM and 7 AM, which gives me ample time to work out, jog, and read!</p>
<p><strong>Drinking 2.5l of water</strong></p>
<p>I’ve been terrible with staying hydrated because I have a thing against public washrooms, but now that I’ve been at home for the majority of the year, I have no excuse. I usually front load my water intake to the first half of the day too.</p>
<h2 id="highlights-from-my-gratitude-journal">Highlights from my gratitude journal</h2>
<p>I note down one line every morning when I wake up, on Notion. It’s done plenty to shift my mindset to a more positive one.</p>
<ul>
<li>Progress, however slow</li>
<li>Making my own bubble tea</li>
<li>Thinking it’s Sunday when it’s still Saturday</li>
<li>Spending time with my nephews (this is a recurring one!)</li>
<li>Amazing friends</li>
<li>Opportunities at work</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="a-random-list-of-media">A random list of media</h2>
<p>And now, to cap it off, here’s a list of things I’ve enjoyed watching and listening to this year:</p>
<ul>
<li>She-Ra: The Princesses of Power</li>
<li>Babysitters Club</li>
<li>Haunting of Bly Manor</li>
<li>#blackAF</li>
<li>Brie Larson’s YouTube channel</li>
<li>Among Us streamers (Pokimane, Valkyrae, Hafu, Fuslie, Sykkuno and others!)</li>
<li>Behind the Bastards</li>
<li>Chameleon: Hollywood Con Queen</li>
<li>You’re Wrong About</li>
</ul>
<p>If you’re reading this, I hope you had at least a bearable 2020, and that 2021 would be much better for you and all of us. See you next year!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
