<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Learnings on Jalyn Cai</title>
    <link>https://jalyncai.com/tags/learnings/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Learnings on Jalyn Cai</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2024 17:21:47 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jalyncai.com/tags/learnings/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Learning and blundering in chess and life</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/blundering/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2024 17:21:47 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/blundering/</guid>
      <description>Looks like this year is an actual year of learning, because I decided to pick chess up on a whim.
A real whim, or a procrastination technique from doing up my portfolio? You decide.
I knew how to play the basics of Chinese chess (象棋), which just meant I knew how the pieces moved, so there are some parts that now feel familiar. I mean, am I calling the knight a horse (馬), because that’s what the Chinese piece is and they move in the exact same way in the L shape, except there are more restrictions on a Chinese horse?</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Looks like this year is an actual year of learning, because I decided to pick chess up on a whim.</p>
<p>A real whim, or a procrastination technique from doing up my portfolio? You decide.</p>
<hr>
<p>I knew how to play the basics of Chinese chess (象棋), which just meant I knew how the pieces moved, so there are some parts that now feel familiar. I mean, am I calling the knight a horse (馬), because that’s what the Chinese piece is and they move in the exact same way in the L shape, except there are more restrictions on a Chinese horse?</p>
<p>Obviously.</p>
<p>Also, no flying King, which is something the General can do, which makes it a little less exciting for 5 year old me who wanted that General to fly every single time.</p>
<hr>
<p>I can’t say enough great things about <a href="https://www.learnchesswithdrwolf.com/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >Learn Chess with Dr. Wolf</a>, which is structured enough that I feel like I’m learning something new every time I open the app, but also gamified enough that I <em>want</em> to open the app. Some dialogue made me laugh outright, especially when I blunder — and I am blundering <em>so</em> much.</p>
<p>One important thing that I’m learning is just how many blind spots I have. There’s that analogy to the decisions I’m making not just in playing a match, but in real life. I’m not someone you can call impulsive, but in games, I can see how my inexperience and lack of focus make my decisions a liability. Sometimes I’m too eager to win pieces, but I end up losing material instead because I failed to see that the piece was protecting another more important one.</p>
<p>A bigger issue that I’m still working through is not being able to instinctively see when a move leads to a stalemate. I think this is slightly worse than losing pieces, and again, analogously to life, have I doomed myself to a lose/lose situation instead of one that would be beneficial on whichever metric I frame it with?</p>
<p>I’m excited to learn more, both about chess, and about how it feeds back into my life.</p>
<hr>
<p>(Also, yes, I speed-watched Queen’s Gambit because I missed that boat in 2020 and only saw it for the first time last weekend. I love complex competent characters )</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On skiing and trying things for the first time</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/skiing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2024 19:42:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/skiing/</guid>
      <description>I’m generally risk-averse, I learned about myself a long time ago. I’m overly cautious, frenetically anxious, and incessantly worry about the unknowns. (Which, yes, is an issue in itself, and something I’m trying to manage, to varying degrees of success.)
Yet, in the last week, I found myself strapping into boots and skis that made my body cry in agony. I fell no less than half a dozen times on the first day.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’m generally risk-averse, I learned about myself a long time ago. I’m overly cautious, frenetically anxious, and incessantly worry about the unknowns. (Which, yes, is an issue in itself, and something I’m trying to manage, to varying degrees of success.)</p>
<p>Yet, in the last week, I found myself strapping into boots and skis that made my body cry in agony. I fell no less than half a dozen times on the first day. And the second, and the third.</p>
<p>I wished I didn’t have that much churning in my amygdala, as I chanted “oh no, oh no, oh no”, both in my head and aloud as I skidded, stumbled, and skittered across an icy landscape so unfamiliar to me.</p>
<p>In contrast, my nephews — who turned six today! — took to the sport so naturally, unfazed by falls and bumps. And it wasn’t like they had a lot of practice before this vacation either; just perhaps a combined five days of skiing ever in their lives as of yet.</p>
<p>I envy the fearlessness, and the ability to embrace learning something new and making themselves better.</p>
<h2 id="the-fun-scale">The fun scale</h2>
<p>There is this concept about different kinds of fun, <a href="https://kellycordes.com/2009/11/02/the-fun-scale/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >defined as</a>:</p>
<ul>
<li>Type I: Enjoyable while it is happening</li>
<li>Type II: Enjoyable in retrospect</li>
<li>Type III: Not enjoyable at all</li>
</ul>
<p>I’m a few days removed from burning up under my layers in the freezing weather (a really interesting dichotomy I had never experienced before).</p>
<p>My wide feet ached, my thick shins hurt (partly because of my rookie mistake of wearing my base layer under my socks), and I reeked of cigarette smoke because my instructor was smoking at a rate of a pack per hour, not helped by the fact that he had to wait patiently for me.</p>
<h3 id="day-one">Day one</h3>
<p>Him: You won’t fall.</p>
<p>Me, with skis shifting under my weight and not being able to do anything about them: I’m SLIDING!</p>
<p>Him, laughing: Yes, you are on ice.</p>
<p>Me: <em>falls</em></p>
<hr>
<p>Spoiler: I really enjoyed myself.</p>
<hr>
<p>If Day 1 was me terrified and obstructed by my mental barriers, Day 2 would be about turning my disbelief into confidence. At the start of the day, I was still scared of everything — sliding on the snow, going onto <a href="https://www.the-ski-guru.com/2019/12/06/different-types-lifts-resortshow-ride-them/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >the magic carpet</a>, hanging on to dear life on a rope tow, and then falling while going up on a surface lift.</p>
<p>I wouldn’t say something <em>clicked</em>, but I’d even managed to steer myself by imitating the instructor in front of me, who did very leisurely turns very slowly for my benefit. In 6 total hours by the end of the second day, I was much, much more in control, and that definitely built my confidence.</p>
<p>I’m really proud of myself. I’m proud of embracing the learning of something new, and for not succumbing to my anxiety and managing to push through.</p>
<p>I hadn’t realized it explicitly before then, but I hadn’t felt like I was trying something new for the first time in a very long time. (I guess <a href="https://jalyn.co/its-me-hi-im-the-problem/"   target="_blank" rel="noopener" >the GMAT attempt</a> didn’t count in my head!)</p>
<h2 id="random-observations">random observations</h2>
<p>(Placeholder image space!)</p>
<ul>
<li>The incredible mountain views did some healing on my ruined city psyche. We’ll see how long this high lasts as I slide back, unfortunately not onto the snow, but work instead</li>
<li>I want to continue to strengthen myself: I know what my limiting factors are (broken back, weak core, and weirdly-shaped feet), so I might start doing specific workouts to focus on movements that would aid in my next skiing experience</li>
<li>Direction is more important than speed, but to shift, you still need some speed. How’s that for inspiration?</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Life &amp; poker</title>
      <link>https://jalyncai.com/posts/poker/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Sep 2021 16:04:11 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalyncai.com/posts/poker/</guid>
      <description>This weekend started out with a book – Maria Konnikova’s The Biggest Bluff – before it escalated to me downloading a poker game app, and spending quite some time playing it.
“Casual playing”, that’s what they all say, right?
Kidding aside, I’m not putting “real” money on it, so the only thing I’m really losing is time. I’ve played poker on and off, learned the very basics when I was 15.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This weekend started out with a book – Maria Konnikova’s <em>The Biggest Bluff</em> – before it escalated to me downloading a poker game app, and spending quite some time playing it.</p>
<p>“Casual playing”, that’s what they all say, right?</p>
<p>Kidding aside, I’m not putting “real” money on it, so the only thing I’m really losing is time. I’ve played poker on and off, learned the very basics when I was 15. I’m still a very basic player and I lose more hands than I win them, but I’m pretending that it’s helping my decision making skills somewhat.</p>
<p>I’m glad this is also online because as my friends and colleagues will attest to, I have absolutely no poker face. I also now understand why there are so many poker analogies out there.</p>
<h2 id="sunk-cost-fallacy--fear-of-missing-out">Sunk cost fallacy &amp; fear of missing out</h2>
<p>There are two scenarios here:</p>
<ol>
<li>When I’m the small blind (i.e. a mandatory position where you put in half the minimum bet)</li>
<li>When I don’t have a bet in the game</li>
</ol>
<p>In the small blind position, I’m always thinking to myself — I’ve already ‘invested’ a small amount now, and if my hand is okay (to me this means a combination of at least one royal card and &gt;8 cards), shouldn’t I maximize my chances of getting a good</p>
<p>When I don’t have a bet yet, but if I’m holding good cards (again, to me, something like high pairs), I’d also more likely than not put in a call. Sometimes it works out, other times, people either have higher pairs or the round goes into other combinations that they win with.</p>
<h2 id="opportunity-costs-regrets-and-what-ifs">Opportunity costs, regrets and what ifs</h2>
<p>Now, in some cases I would fold immediately, especially if I don’t have any stakes in the round. Usually this means I have bad cards, like a combination of any cards between 2 – 6, or if I’m at a table with someone I can tell just keeps raising and going all-in (their strategy, I suppose).</p>
<p>Then comes the flop. Then the turn. Then the river.</p>
<p>I realize my cards would have given me a win, usually via a straight, a three of a kind, or a flush.</p>
<p>This realization is followed by me heaving a sigh, especially if I’m down on my chips too. This is made worse if the winning player had bluffed. What if I had forged forward anyway? What if I had put in the minimum bid to “see what happens”?</p>
<h2 id="privilege">Privilege</h2>
<p>More than that, I have been drawing parallels to everybody’s starting points and how, even if you have a great hand, you might not be able to capitalize on it.</p>
<p>Take for example a game where you have a buy in of 500 chips, but another player has 10,000 chips. You can bet and go all in, and the most you’ll get — assuming the other player matches your all in of 500 chips — is 1,000. It’s barely a drop of the ocean for the other player.</p>
<p>I think about equity, and how hard some people have to work to even achieve parity. About how some opportunities have to be passed up sometimes because you aren’t sure of it working out. It’s also not a complete equivalency — equity in real life doesn’t mean that you are “giving up” your privilege(s), not like in a game of poker.</p>
<p>Now I should really go back to reading the book, instead of making empty air bets.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
